Chapter Thirty Five: Prepared for the Future

While Starlight celebrated, I sat, and I thought.

I was no longer the only member of my hive. One hundred and twenty three eggs were held in cryogenic suspension. Every one had been meticulously hooked up to medical scanners, allowing the lab’s computer to monitor and record their status.

I had searched through those logs. Entry after entry came up clean. In the end, only a single egg had any warning over uneven freezing and crystallization, and even that was well below the threshold the program considered hazardous. They had all survived.

Starlight had stood nearby, waiting and watching. I could see her holding back the nervous excitement as I continued searching the logs. When I finally allowed a smile to show, she grinned and cheered, hopping around in excitement.

And so, she celebrated, while I sat, the smile fading away as I considered my new situation.

I do not mean to say that I was disappointed. I wasn’t. I was so wonderfully relieved to have found something after all of my searching. At the same time, I had hoped the changelings I had found would be adults, individuals who could help with the many difficulties our hive would face. Experts that could help us rebuild, perhaps even soldiers and other Infiltrators that could help combat the threats rising in the Wasteland. Instead, I had one hundred and twenty three eggs, all dependent on me.

So, while I wasn’t disappointed, I was concerned.

It was several minutes before Dusty approached me. “Something wrong?”

“No,“ I said, giving another weak smile, but it faded away almost immediately. “Not exactly. I’m just thinking.”

He nodded, but he seemed to pick up on some of the seriousness of the situation. “About what?”

I considered brushing it off, but this was something that needed to be addressed, and to be honest, something I thought needed to be discussed.

I stood, turning to face the rest of the group. Starlight immediately stopped, grinning at me. Echo stood nearby, tall and proud, though a hint of a smile touched her lips. Off to the side, Sickle lay kicked back against a cryo-freezer, the mostly empty ice-cream container resting on her belly.

“Everyone,” I said, looking around at them. “First off, I wanted to say… thank you. Thank you for helping me. You’ve gone out of your way just to help me find my hive when it would have been easier to just walk away. I couldn’t have done this without your help.”

“Of course we had to help!” Starlight said, laughing softly.

Dusty nodded along, giving a soft smile. Sickle grunted something unintelligible.

“That said… I have concerns.” With my words, Starlight’s grin instantly vanished. I continued on. “My hive will survive, but it’s still in a tenuous position, and its recovery will be even slower than I had expected. There are more than a hundred eggs. I… I can’t raise all of them on my own. I can’t feed all of them on my own.”

Starlight immediately spoke up. “We can help! I mean, I can help.”

“I appreciate the offer, but there are too many, even for all of us. They’ll need to be fed, cared for, educated, and protected. The best scenario I can think of is raising a small number of them until they’re old enough to help raise more. It means my hive will recover, but it’s going to take time. We’re talking two, maybe three generations before my hive becomes self-sufficient. Decades. Until then, it’s going to be in a very fragile state. It will be vulnerable.

“Right now, those young changelings are safe and stable. It would be... irresponsible of me to put them in danger. I can’t thaw them now.”

Starlight stepped forward. “But—”

I held up a hoof. “Not yet. They almost died once, already. I can’t waste the opportunity that’s presented itself. I have to do what I can to make sure the world is safe for them.”

“What exactly did you have in mind?” Dusty asked.

“Serenity,” I said. “They’re already a problem. Whatever it is they’re doing, it’s going to be bad for ponies. Even speaking in purely practical terms, my hive will need peaceful, friendly ponies, and Serenity puts that in danger. And if they should find out about my hive? I don’t doubt that they’d put every effort into wiping us out completely.

“I can not in good conscience hatch these changelings with a threat like that looming over them. Not until Serenity has been stopped. Since I’m the only active Infiltrator in my hive, that means the duty falls to me.”

Dusty was frowning, thinking. “That’s a pretty big thing you’re talking about. Maybe you should think a bit on it before deciding.”

“I’ve been thinking about this for days, now,” I said, slowly shaking my head. “This isn’t an impulsive decision. This is something I need to do, for both my hive and for the other people of the Wasteland.”

“If you’re sure,” Dusty said. “What are you thinking?”

“Serenity has two primary advantages,” I said. “So we destroy those.”

“What, the big fortified base and huge army?” Starlight asked. “How the heck do we do that? I mean, I guess we do have some balefire eggs…”

“Those are powerful, but too small to wipe out an entire Stable. Besides, those aren’t the advantages I was referring to.”

She cocked her head. “What did you mean?”

“Their first advantage is their secrecy. Most ponies don’t even know Serenity is out there. A few do, and some are spreading the word, but even they don’t know the details of Serenity’s capabilities. They don’t know how changeling Infiltrators work, what kinds of tactics and options they have, or how to effectively combat these changelings. I do. My hive has always tried to aid ponies with knowledge and assistance, working behind the scenes. My hive’s survival is going to depend on working with ponies, maybe even more openly than ever before.”

Dusty was slowly nodding. “Information is good. Good intel was one of the best advantages we could hope for, when I was in the Rangers. Still… I’m sure Serenity has near-perfect intel on every settlement around, and nopony has the forces to oppose them. Not even those Enclave guys.”

“Which is their second advantage: unity. They can focus all of their efforts against enemies that are completely disorganized. Right now, Serenity has the opportunity to pick apart ponies one settlement at a time. There is no unified front, just a bunch of small, easily defeated groups. Some of them are a hair’s breadth from fighting each other. If ponies don’t pull together, they’ll be picked off one-by-one.” I looked around the group. “We already saw that at Rust.”

Starlight’s ears drooped. Dusty’s expression, on the other hoof, hardened.

“We can’t fight them on our own,” I said. “Nobody can. The only way I can see for overcoming Serenity is going to as many ponies as I can, impress upon them exactly the level of danger we’re all facing, and convince them to work together to face it.”

Dusty gave a dry snort. “Oh, is that all? Shit, most settlements can’t even agree to things within their own walls.”

Starlight nudged him, managing a smile. “I dunno. If anyone can talk everypony into doing something, it’s Whisper.”

“I don’t expect it will be easy,” I said, “but a mutual threat can be a strong motivator to cooperate, and I expect I can leverage that to our advantage. Even if I can’t get everypony to work together, getting the information out will weaken Serenity’s position, perhaps enough that those who do band together will have a fighting chance.”

“And if they don’t?” Dusty asked.

“Then we lose nothing that we wouldn’t have lost, anyway,” I said. “The alternative would be to stand by and do nothing. Let hundreds or thousands of ponies be conquered, enslaved, or killed, and give up on any chance of my hive being able to thrive as it once had.”

“Yeah, yeah,” Dusty said, waving a hoof. “I get it. Shit. I don’t particularly like it, but I get it.”

“I don’t like it, either,” I said, “but I think this is something I have to do.”

“Yeah,” Dusty repeated, then sighed. “I see some problems with that idea, though.”

“What’s that?”

“Serenity’s already hit one settlement. We might not have much time. We also don’t know if we can even walk into Mareford without being shot. Sure, you can go in on your own, but the rest of us are all wanted ponies.”

“I am not,” Echo said from behind him, but he waved off her retort.

“The point is, it’s going to be hard dealing with Mareford, and she’d be basically on her own in a town we know has been infiltrated before.”

“It wouldn’t be the first time,” I said, “but that was when acting as an Infiltrator, impersonating a common citizen, rather than making myself the focus of attention. Given my recent experience, I’d much rather be able to have you nearby.” I cast a glance around. “That is, assuming you wish to help.”

“Of course!” Starlight said, grinning.

Dusty nodded. “If there’s a way to help ponies against Serenity, I’m all for it.”

Sickle made a vague, quiet grunt.

We looked to Echo. She was frowning, looking at me for a second before speaking. “Given your combination of persuasive argument skills and remarkable stubbornness, I presume any attempt short of physical restraint would fail to dissuade you, and I am still in need of you for my research. Very well, I shall assist.”

“Thank you,” I said, sharing a smile. Then I turned back to Dusty. “Mareford is still a possibility, but there might be other places to start. If we can get other groups involved, we might be able to use that to leverage Mareford. You know more about the political disposition of settlements in the region. Any suggestions?”

“Well…” He frowned, thinking for a moment. “Mareford isn’t the only big settlement. There’s also Trotsen, and we’re closer to it than Mareford. The two towns are trading partners. If we can get Trotsen in on this, that’s going to carry a lot of weight, and would give a good way to catch Mareford’s ear.”

“Starting big is probably a good idea,” I said, nodding. “Smaller settlements may be hesitant to commit if they aren’t sure the bigger settlements are in.”

“I have my doubts that they’ll be willing to work together,” Dusty said. “They might be trading partners, but the towns aren’t exactly friends. Still, it’s worth a shot, and even if they don’t act together, at least we might get them all acting. And hell, getting Trotsen stirred up could be useful on its own. They’re about the only force around that could compete with the Mareford Militia.”

“Oh?”

Dusty nodded. “Yep. The Militia is the better fighting force, mind you. More disciplined, better trained, and better equipped. Then there’s the Rangers, who are even better. Still, Trotsen has at least a dozen combat-focused motorwagons, and that’s just what we know about. Mareford has a pair of whirligigs, but that’s only enough to move a couple Ranger teams. The mobility Trotsen has in the field is a huge advantage.”

“I can certainly appreciate the advantage of mobility,” I said, thinking of our own motorwagon. “Though I imagine Serenity tops everyone in that regard.”

“Not the Enclave,” he noted. “Though it seems they’ve got their own fight.”

“If we do get other settlements to work together, we might try approaching them again,” I said. “They don’t want to compromise their own fight, but if we show them we’ve got a good chance of beating Serenity without excessive expenditure on their part, they might be willing to pitch in. I think I might be able to use the Cumulonimbus as a point of leverage. Despite how Commander Aurora dismissed it, I imagine they don’t like the idea of their own ship being in the hooves of a genocidal enemy of ponies.”

Dusty frowned at that, but nodded. “Yeah, I imagine not. Be careful pushing it too hard, though. If she realizes you’re trying to—”

“She’d be upset, yes,” I said, giving a lopsided smile. “People don’t tend to like being manipulated, and military types tend to be more forceful about it.”

Dusty gave a single chuckle. “Yeah, just a bit. So… Trotsen?”

I nodded.

“Okay, then,” he said, giving one final nod and turning to the others. “Let’s get—”

“Wait,” I said, holding up a hoof. “There’s one more thing, first.”

He cocked an eyebrow, but listened.

“I’m hesitant to ask it, but… I need to ask you all a favor.”

“Sure!” Starlight replied, then asked, “What is it?”

“I’m… rather uncomfortably aware that I am here at least partially by chance. There have been several times that I could have easily died. One lucky shot, a random piece of shrapnel, almost anything. Chances are, my odds of dying were probably better than my odds of getting here.”

Starlight’s smile had vanished, her eyes widening a touch in alarm. “What are you saying?”

“I’m saying that, right now… I’m the only active member of my hive. I’m the only member able to do anything, and the only one carrying our knowledge and values. If I were to die, they would be on their own. Taking on Serenity, it’s going to be dangerous. I’m already a target, and spreading the word about Serenity is going to catch their attention. I’ve been fortunate to get this far, but it would be irresponsible of me to endanger the future of my hive. So, I want to ask all of you for a favor.”

They watched and waited intently as I sat. It was difficult to say what I had to say. “I’d like to ask you to promise that, if I die, one of you will come back for them. That… if you’re the last one of us left, you won’t keep fighting. You’ll save yourself, leave, and come here. That you’ll make sure they still have a chance at life.”

Starlight’s ears had drooped as she slowly nodded. “Y-yeah… but we’re not letting you die.”

Dusty was frowning, looking down at the ground as he considered the request. “I don’t know. That’s…” He looked up, meeting my pleading eyes. He stared silently, as if trying to come up with a suitable argument, but he couldn’t hold my gaze. He instead looked over at the freezer, with the hundred-plus eggs within. His ears flicked back, and he sighed. “Yeah.”

“Well,” Echo said, “I suppose if you were to get yourself killed, I would be in need of another helpful changeling, anyway, and I do imagine a child would be more amenable. Still, I would prefer if you do not die, so I shall do my best to ensure your safety. I can shield you from harm just as well as I can shield myself.” She cocked her head to the side, looking off into space as she mused, “Perhaps I could repair that power armor you have acquired. It would certainly improve your odds of survival.”

“Thank you,” I said, feeling my throat tighten just a touch. I swallowed past the lump, doing my best to ignore it. Instead, I lifted my PipBuck-clad leg, touching a hoof delicately to the device. “I’ve been making recordings about what’s happened to me since waking up. I’ve talked a lot about my hive and its values. I’ve been keeping it all heavily encrypted, but… I’m going to decrypt the files. I’ll leave a copy of what I have here, maybe give you guys copies, too, but I’m going to be recording more. If I don’t make it, I’d like you to copy those files so these changelings can hear it. So they know who they are, where they come from.”

Starlight was nodding. “Yeah,” she said, her voice ever-so-slightly strained. “Now can we stop talking like you’re going to die?”

I gave a soft, reassuring smile. “I don’t plan on dying, but it would be irresponsible to not account for the possibility.”

Starlight stepped forward and wrapped me in a tight hug, her words coming out slightly choked. “Will you please stop being so depressingly practical for a bit?”

I couldn’t help chuckling slightly as I returned the hug. “Okay. I’m done.”

“Good,” she said. She still kept hugging me.

When she didn’t immediately stop, Dusty spoke up. “Okay, then. We should get ready to go. Starlight, see if you can get one of those spark generators. Everyone else, scavenge any essentials we might need, like food and water. We should head out as soon as possible.”

Starlight finally released me, and reluctantly walked off to begin the salvage. Echo said something about robots before hurrying off. As for myself, I simply remained sitting, lacking anything better to do with myself.

A minute passed before Sickle pushed her way up to her hooves and lumbered over to me. She came to a stop beside me, speaking in a quiet rumble. “So, yeah, it’s been fun and all, but I think it’s about time I took off.”

I looked up to her in surprise. “What? Why?”

Her armor rattled with a shrug. “Ain’t much for me to do around here,” she said. “Hell, figured I’d head up north a bit. Sounds like there’s still plenty of raiders and warlords and shit up there. Might be fun.”

“Going north?” I stared at her, legitimately shocked at her decision. “But… why? There’s still so much going on here.”

She snorted. “Yeah, sure. You’re going to go around and talk at a bunch of ponies. Woo. Loads of fun.”

“You know there’s going to be violence,” I said. “Serenity isn’t going to stop without a fight.”

“Yeah, great,” she said, and I’m pretty sure she rolled her eyes somewhere under that helmet. “And I’m sure I’ll have just as much fun as these last fights.”

And now it all made sense. “That’s what this is about? You’re feeling useless here?”

“I’m feeling bored is what it’s all about. I ain’t getting nearly enough fucking to hang around in the back doing nothing while you cunts have fun fighting. And Serenity? Hah. Bet those cunty bugs’ll all be flying and shit. Ain’t much for me to do.”

“There’s plenty you could do,” I said, reaching up a hoof and placing it gently on her shoulder. “They won’t all be flying, and I’m sure there’ll be other fights, too.”

“Dusty and Star can handle the long-range shit just fine, and that Luna-wannabe will probably do well, too. Ain’t much of a fight for me, and I ain’t playing second-up. So unless you’re planning on offering me some of the best fucking ever, I ain’t got much reason to stick around.”

Her head inclined slightly, as if waiting to see if I took up the not-so-subtle offer. I tried a different approach. “I think you’re wrong,” I said. “There’s still plenty you can do, even right in the front-line of the fight. Even against Serenity.”

She turned her head to face me more directly. “Like what, huh? Name one thing.”

I frowned, stepping up to face her squarely, and meeting her gaze without any sign of hesitation or fear. “Sickle, you’re probably the most stubborn, combative, unrelenting pony I’ve known. If you really think you’re going to be useless, why don’t you find a way to make yourself useful, instead of running away?”

Her head drew back a touch, jaw tightening. “You know… I kinda like that you ain’t so scared of me any more.” She lifted a hoof, pointing the vicious leg-blades at my chest, her lips curling back. “But don’t think I won’t beat your fucking ass to a pulp if you push me. I’ve killed plenty of ponies for less.”

“Because they were insulting you, no doubt,” I said, refusing to let my eyes waver despite the adrenaline teasing at my senses. Then I put on a thin smile. “But I’m not insulting you. I’m challenging you.”

She stared back at me for several long seconds before replying. “That clever mouth of yours is going to get you beat some day.”

“Maybe,” I replied, “but not today.”

We stood there, squared off, the metal-clad beast of a pony looming above me.

Sickle broke the silence with another snort, and shoved her way past me.

I staggered, wheeling around to watch her walking off. I mentally scrambled, trying to think of something else to say, and eventually just called out. “Sickle!”

She stopped, head half-turning, but said nothing.

Still, nothing came. Finally, I sighed. “Good luck,” I said, ears drooping. “And… thank you.”

Her head turned a little further, inclining almost curiously. Then, she looked away again and continued walking. She stepped out into the hall, and then she was gone.

I stood in the empty lab, watching the door as if I expected her to come back. Eventually, I turned away, slowly wandering.

I found myself again at the window of the giant cryo-freezer, rearing up to rest my forelegs on the rim of the window. I stared out into the chamber and the rows of dimly lit eggs. There were so many of them. They were safe, but they were also so fragile.

Hoofsteps approached some untold number of minutes later, moving right up beside me. Starlight’s voice was soft and pleasant. “Hey.”

“Hey,” I replied, still staring out over the eggs.

She stood beside me, looking through the window with a gentle smile. After a moment, she placed a hoof on my shoulder, giving a gentle rub. “You did it.”

“Yeah,” I quietly replied. Then I drew in a deep breath, and slowly let it out. “Still a lot more to do.”

She nodded. “Yeah.” There was a long, lingering silence as she shared the view with me. Eventually, her attention shifted more toward me. “So, I guess this puts you in charge of your hive, huh?”

“It’s quite the responsibility,” I said, slowly nodding.

“So does that make you the queen, now?”

I flinched, ears flicking back. “No,” I quickly replied. “I’m not a queen.” I emphasized this by gesturing toward the eggs. “One of them will be. Not me.”

She paused, considering me. After a moment, she smiled. “Well, I think you’d make a great queen.”

My first impulse was to argue the point, but I looked to her and that comforting smile, and knew she intended it as a sincere compliment. “Thank you.”

Her smile grew a touch, and she turned to look at the eggs again. “You going to be okay leaving them here?”

“They’re about as safe as they can be,” I said, despite the many fears that lingered in the background. “Nopony knows about this location but us, and it’s far from any settlements. I’ll be locking the labs up again, and I should be able to set a new passcode. They’ll be safe.”

She nodded. “We should probably get on that, then. Dusty wants to move out soon.”

We headed out. Once we’d left the secure labs, I focused on the lock for the giant blast doors, while Dusty led Starlight off to help him break into some vending machine. It only took me a few minutes to figure out how to set a new passcode. I locked the labs up tight and rejoined them, to find Dusty pulling packs of cigarettes from an opened machine.

Starlight was sitting on top of it, her hooves lazily swinging off the edge. She was smirking down at him. “Yeah, no more making fun of me for hoarding snack cakes, Dusty.”

“I didn’t make fun of you,” Dusty quietly replied, steadily shoveling packs into his bag.

“Okay,” Starlight said, and laughed. “No more rolling your eyes silently while ‘not making fun of me’, then.”

Despite his focus, the corner of Dusty’s mouth crept upwards. “Not like I won’t have plenty of other reasons to roll my eyes at you.”

Echo stood back, watching them all with a tight frown, but said nothing.

Dusty noticed my approach as he buckled his bags. “Good timing. We all set to go?”

“I am,” I replied.

“Good,” he said with a nod, then asked, “Where’s Sickle?”

“I don’t know,” Starlight said. “Couldn’t find her.”

“She left.”

They all turned to look at me, blinking in surprise.

“Why?” Dusty asked.

“She was... bored,” I said. “She decided it was time to move on.”

I left it at that. I didn’t feel particularly like elaborating, and I doubted that she would have liked me explaining the conclusions I had drawn.

Dusty stared for a moment before sighing. “Shit. We haven’t even started, and we’re already losing ponies.”

“I can’t believe she just left,” Starlight said. “I mean… hell, I don’t exactly like her, but… shit.”

In the background, Echo had cocked her head to the side, and finally broke her silence. “What are you talking about? She did not leave.” She turned her head, looking towards the front of the facility. “She is currently in the back of your motorwagon, rummaging through the cargo.”

Dusty’s ears perked up as he turned to look that way. I did too, then turned my attention to the E.F.S. and the single contact it reported in that direction.

We made our way out to the entrance and stepped outside once again. Sure enough, Sickle was in the back of the motorwagon, hunched over something.

I walked toward her. “Sickle? What are—”

“Well it took you fuckers long enough,” she grumbled, sitting back and tossing the minigun-armed battle-saddle at my hooves. I heard a sharp inhale from Echo as she stepped forward, catching it at the last moment in her magic.

Sickle was rooting around again. “You want me to stick around? You pull that weak-ass shit off that harness…” She reared back, swinging up one of the massive heavy machine guns and thumping it down on the edge of the cargo bay. “...and mount this motherfucker in its place!”

Echo floated the battle-saddle close to her chest, casting a disapproving glare at Sickle, but after a moment said, “That should be a trivial modification.”

“Those things can put guns on both sides, right?” Sickle asked. “‘Cause I’m thinking of tearing that grenade launcher off this rust-bucket power armor and putting it on the other side.”

“Uh, wait a minute,” Starlight said. “I can’t be the only one worried about giving Sickle a gun, am I?”

“Fuck you, runt.”

“And I thought you were leaving?” Starlight added, looking at me for confirmation. I nodded.

“There’s going to be a good fight, right?” Sickle gave an amused snort. “But hey, if those bugs are going to cheat by flying, I’m going to cheat by bringing a fucking gun.”

Dusty was watching, his expression looking as if he’d bitten into something sour and was trying to hide it. “The idea of you with a gun and grenade launcher is… terrifying,” he said, before adding, “Hopefully in a good way.”

“Good!” Sickle said, grinning savagely. “I like terrifying.”

“I assume you intend to wear this,” Echo said, frowning down at the harness. “It is woefully insufficient for a pony of your girth and length. It will require extensive modification.”

“Well then, you better make yourself fucking useful and get on that, huh?”

Echo scowled. “You could at least have the courtesy to politely ask for my assistance.”

“Yeah,” Sickle said with a derisive chuckle. “And you could have the courtesy to eat me, bitch.”

I stepped forward. “Sickle, there’s no need to be nasty.” Then I turned to Echo. “Would it be possible to make the modifications?”

“It is certainly possible,” Echo said, glaring at Sickle. “I would need to requisition some additional material from some of the unused equipment to enlarge the harness. However, I am not terribly inclined to do any favors for someone so relentlessly rude.”

“I understand,” I said. “Could you please make those modifications?”

Her frown deepened as she looked down at me, then raised her head again to her usual superior pose. “I shall do this task for you.”

“Thank you.”

Sickle snickered, and I immediately turned to her.

“I’m glad you decided to stick around, but if you continue to be rude to Echo when she’s trying to help you, I can always withdraw my request.”

“Yeah, yeah,” Sickle said, waving a hoof dismissively. “Still wouldn’t hurt her to pull the fucking log out of her ass.”

“No more than it would hurt you to ease up on the hostility, especially when she’s doing something for your benefit.”

Sickle just shrugged.

“Have you ever even fired a gun?” Dusty asked, skepticism clear in his expression.

“Sure, a few times,” Sickle replied, kicking back in the bed of the motorwagon and kicking her rear hooves up on the edge of the roof. “Ain’t like it’s hard.”

Dusty raised an eyebrow. “In a fight?”

“Nah.” She lifted a foreleg, wiggling a spiked hoof. “Never needed a gun.”

“Great,” Dusty grumbled. “And how long ago was this?”

“I dunno,” Sickle said. “Five or six years ago? Maybe more?”

“No experience and one of our biggest guns. This will only end well.” Turning his attention to Echo, he asked, “How hard would it be to make it so we can swap out weapons?”

“Trivial,” Echo replied, floating the battle-saddle before her. With a few clicks, the minigun floated free. “These harnesses were explicitly designed to allow the swapping of weapons with a minimal use of tools. The only difficulty will lie in fabricating mounting hardware for new weapons, but that should take mere minutes.”

“Good,” Dusty said with a nod. “In that case, I’ve got a different weapon I’d like you to mount first, just so we can get her some practice shooting.”

He climbed into the motorwagon beside Sickle, who made some quiet and obscene comment that he ignored. A minute later, he climbed out again, holding a rifle. It was another Model 4 rifle, like my own, but it had a thicker, longer barrel, with a bipod mounted beneath it.

“That tiny thing?” Sickle said. “I’d do more damage hitting someone with that than shooting them!”

“We have less than three hundred rounds for the HMG, and we’re not wasting them on training. We’ve got probably a thousand rounds for this gun, we can spare a few.”

He passed it over to Echo, who examined it with a critical eye. “Magazine fed. That will pose some difficulty. The battle-saddle lacks a reloading mechanism. Designing one would take some time, as would adapting the minigun’s feed mechanism to this weapon.”

“No need,” Dusty said. “It’s just for training, so we can make do with manual reloading. Actually, Whisper, I was thinking you might want to consider using this one, once Sickle is done with it.”

I cocked my head, looking at it more closely as I asked, “Why is that?”

“You tend to be a bit heavy on the rate of fire, but you’ve gotten to be a pretty reliable soldier in general. That one’s designed to handle automatic fire better. It’s got a heavier barrel, lets you fire more without overheating it, and it’s a more stable platform. We could load you up with some drums and let you lay out some heavy fire.”

“I guess,” I said, frowning a little as I looked at it. “I don’t know, though. I kind of like this rifle. It’s light. That with a drum mag seems a little awkward.”

“It’ll be heavier and slower, sure,” Dusty said with a nod, though he wore a faint smile; it seems he approved of my observation. “But it’s also much more capable for longer-ranged engagements. If we get you some practice with it, you could swap out depending on the situation. They’re based on the same weapon, so their operation is identical.”

“I suppose that makes sense.”

Meanwhile, Echo had floated out several spare parts and a toolkit from the motorwagon and gotten to work. It took only a couple of minutes before she had the rifle fitted to the right side of the battle-saddle. Another minute was spent alternating between the weapon’s built-in sights and the aiming reticle of the battle-saddle before she was satisfied with its alignment.

After that was several minutes spent rebuilding the frame and replacing straps, and after coaxing a lethargic Sickle from the motorwagon, a few minutes fine-tuning the adjustments to fit snug and secure over her armor.

Sickle did not make it easy.

“Get this shit out of my face,” she grumbled, roughly prodding the arm that held the firing bit and aiming reticle.

“Calm yourself,” Echo replied, standing proudly as her magic did the work of pulling on the straps. “That part is necessary to aim and fire the weapon. You will simply have to deal with it.”

“It’s going to be in the way when I’m kicking the shit out of ponies,” Sickle shot back. “Fuck, I can’t even move my head down all the way!” She demonstrated by smacking her armored muzzle against the firing bit, and followed up by wiggling her head, swinging the long spike atop her helmet. “How the fuck am I supposed to stick ponies with this if I can’t even move my head right?”

“I suppose you will simply have to settle with shooting them.”

“Fuck that,” Sickle replied, swatting the metal arm again, and I’m pretty sure bending it a bit. “You don’t see the fucking Enclave birdies with metal sticks jammed in their faces, do you, bitch?”

Echo’s magic glowed around the protrusion as she held it in place. “That is because they are wearing power armor, and all the systems required for aiming and firing are built into their helmets. They—”

She abruptly stopped, ears perking up. A smile crossed her lips. “I believe I may have a solution to your problem. Give me your helmet.”

Sickle frowned. “What?”

Echo repeated her request more slowly, and Sickle scowled. “I heard you the first time, you stuck-up bitch. I mean, why do you want my helmet?”

“Because if you do not want a rigid bit, I will need to incorporate those mechanisms into your helmet. Now remove your helmet and give it to me.”

Sickle stared at her for several long seconds before answering. “Fine,” she growled, a warning tone to her voice as she sat and unstrapped the helm. “But if you fuck it up, I’m kicking your ass.”

“Hmmph.” Echo took the helm and walked over to the motorwagon, only to stop again. She turned to Starlight, who was relaxing on the hood of the vehicle. “I am uncertain as to who claims ownership over the damaged pegasus power armor, so I shall ask you. May I remove some parts necessary for this project?”

Starlight glanced over to Dusty, who didn’t bother looking up from the drum magazines he was loading. She turned back and shrugged helplessly. “I guess?”

“Good.”

That took a bit longer, as Echo dismantled part of the power armor’s helmet to remove the components she was seeking.

Sickle lay where they had been previously working. She tried to look disinterested, but every now and then she would crane her head a little to try to see what Echo was doing before pretending she didn’t care. A spiked hoof dug at the ground.

I took advantage of the inactivity to move a short distance away and continue my recordings.

Several minutes later, Echo finally straightened again. “It is done.”

“‘Bout fucking time,” Sickle grumbled, pushing herself up to sit again, and snatching the helmet as it was offered to her. She immediately stopped as she looked inside, lips curling back. “What the fuck?”

Despite the remark, she slid the helmet on, then turned her head about, the thick-barred muzzle swinging beneath her chin. “What the fuck did you do to my helmet?”

“I removed the E.F.S. projectors from the pegasus power armor helmet and mounted them in yours, and set an adjustable firing bit inside your helmet’s muzzle. The spark battery compartment I attached at the rear of the helmet provides the power for those devices, and the cable currently dangling from the rear right side of the helmet provides an electrical linkage between the helmet-mounted systems and the battle saddle.” Her nose rose a fraction as she put on a proud smile. “It is a flexible solution that will give you full E.F.S. functionality, including a projected point-of-aim, without compromising your hoof-to-hoof mobility.”

“You really fucking love to listen to yourself talk, don’t you?” Sickle grumbled, still swinging her head around in every direction. “This sparkly color shit is stupid.”

“It is actually quite advanced technology,” Echo said. “The spell matrix involved is—”

“It’s still stupid,” Sickle growled.

Echo frowned. “Yet I am sure you will agree that it is less… ‘stupid’ than the rigid arm you objected to before.”

“Less stupid is still pretty stupid,” Sickle grumbled.

“Oh for fuck’s sake,” Starlight called out. “Say ‘thank you’, you ungrateful bitch!”

“Fuck you, runt,” Sickle replied with a sneer. “Let’s see if this damn gun-thing works before we start thanking anypony.”

Despite her tight frown, Echo took the time to adjust the firing bit to fit Sickle’s mouth. Attaching the rifle itself was completely straight-forward. Finally, she connected the cable to link the helmet to the battle-saddle.

“There,” Echo said with a short nod. “It is complete. When you disable the safety, you should see the aiming pipper. It will show the point of aim. With the necessary data and some time, Whisper should be able to add proper range adjustments to the spell matrix.”

“Yeah, okay,” Sickle muttered as she turned to look out across the open fields nearby. After a moment, she asked, “The fuck is a safety?”

Dusty sighed.

☢

We eventually abandoned our plans to head out that day, once it became clear that proper firearm safety and handling was going to take more than a minutes-long lesson. More than an hour later, Dusty still hadn’t even given her any ammo.

Eventually, he had nearly told her off. “Listen, Sickle! If you want to carry one of the big guns, then you’re going to have to put in some damn work. I ain’t gearing you up with a weapon that’s more likely to kill us than our enemies!”

“I know what way to point a fucking gun, dumbass!” Sickle replied.

“Not giving a shit might work great for running up and kicking someone, but it doesn’t work with guns! If you keep half-assing it like this and not caring about what you’re doing, you’re going to end up shooting one of us on accident.”

Sickle snarled. “At this rate, it wouldn’t be an accident!”

“And that’s not helping,” Dusty said, leveling a hoof at her before sweeping it back in my direction. “And what about Whisper? You seem to like her. If you don’t pay attention to this stuff and treat it seriously, you could accidentally kill her, too. Do you really want that?”

Dusty metaphorically dragged her through the lessons, with Sickle grumbling and arguing the whole way. I hung back, having finished another audio recording, and now sat beside Starlight on the hood of the motorwagon. Echo was nearby; she had decided to not insist on further “research” with me after our previous session, and was instead in the back of the motorwagon, examining the less advanced of the two ruined power armors.

“Do you think this is a good idea?” Starlight asked, watching the so-called training with me.

“Maybe not,” I said, half-distracted by sorting through the contents of my PipBuck. “But it’s still better than the alternative. This is the price of Sickle staying, and as uneasy as I am with some parts of that, it’s unfortunately likely that we’ll need all the advantages we can get.”

“You sound so optimistic,” she grumbled.

“I am,” I said. “With all the factors in play, I think we have a very good chance of achieving our goals.” I gave a shrug, giving up on my PipBuck and lying back beside Starlight. “Still, no reason to not stack everything as far in our favor as possible, not to mention taking precaution against any problems that might come up. Even if I’m optimistic of our chances, there’s still going to be risk.”

Echo spoke up from the cargo bed. “Which is why I hope to get this armor functional. While I am entirely confident in my shields, I would prefer to have redundant safety measures in place for Whisper. Her health is of great value to both of our plans.”

Starlight rolled her eyes. “Gee, glad she’s so useful to you.”

Echo didn’t look up from her work. “Given your strong emotional attachment, I would think you would be pleased by my efforts to protect her.”

“That’s not…” Starlight sighed, closing her eyes and laying her head back against the motorwagon. “Yeah, sure, I’m happy you’re trying to protect her. It’s the ‘why’ that’s dumb.”

“Ah,” Echo said, her magic floating some mechanical part into place on the armor. “You object to my motivations in helping her, not in the help itself.”

“It’s just all clinical, like… I dunno, like she’s a tool to you.”

“Despite my lengthy observations, we have only directly interacted for a little less than twenty four hours,” Echo said, looking up from her work for a moment to meet Starlight’s eyes. “Given the limited interaction, yes, I have not formed any sort of emotional attachment to any of you which would significantly influence my behavior.”

Starlight quietly snorted, and muttered, “Behold, the savior of ponykind: kind of a dick.”

“Well, she’s trying,” I said. “And to be fair to Echo, it took more than twenty four hours for me to start thinking of you as a friend instead of just a traveling companion. I’m not sure exactly where I would put that. When we got to Rust, perhaps?”

Starlight gave another snort, though there was a bit more humor behind it this time. “So, like, two days instead of one?”

“Or thereabouts,” I said, cracking a smile. “Mind, I’d be lying if I said there was no selfish interest in staying with you. You were pretty much my only opportunity for love and survival knowledge prior to Rust, and still my best prospects after it, but that was only part of it. An increasingly small part, at that.”

“Sure, I get all that,” she said. “I mean, it’s still a little weird when I think about, but I guess I don’t really think about it much. Like, I’ve gotten used to it.”

Echo spoke up again. “Whisper is much better at putting on friendly pretenses than I am.”

“I’m sure I am,” I said, “but you’d be mistaken if you think that’s the case here. I don’t generally need to put on pretenses, because I do legitimately care about people, even ponies. I took up my profession to help others. Changelings, yes, but one of the advantages of being an Infiltrator is that it becomes much easier to see the ways we are similar rather than different. I might not have thought of Starlight as a friend right away, but I liked her immediately.”

“Wasn’t I pointing a gun at you?” Starlight said with a smile.

I chuckled. “But after you put the gun down you were all smiles and cheerfulness. Considering how bleak everything seemed, it stood out to me. And you know, even though I had my own problems, spending some time around you made me want to help you with your own. Sure, again, there was a bit of a selfish side to it. I needed food, and, well… seeing you happy gave me hope that good things could still thrive in the Wasteland.”

Her smile steadily grew until she finally gave a soft laugh and thumped me on the shoulder. “Okay, that is ridiculously cheesy, you silly little bug!”

I grinned. “Plus, you have a nice laugh.”

She lay back, still chuckling.

After a moment of enjoying the good humor, I looked back to Echo. “In any case, I think there’s an important point to all this. You and I have certain similarities. We’re both trying to help ponies, and it seems we both have a similarly methodical thought process. I think the difference is, while you’re trying to help ponies as a whole, you seem to overlook the individuals in the process.”

Echo’s head came up again, her work pausing as she considered this. “Hmm. I believe I see what you are trying to say. I… I must admit, most of our lives, our memories, are from our time in Unity. What benefited the whole benefited us. The chaos of individuality is most troubling.”

“It’s certainly more complicated,” I said with a nod. “But the variety makes the world far better for everyone involved, I’ve found.”

Echo hummed again. “I do have to admit, as frustrating and incomprehensible as it seems at times, I am certainly finding the variety to be intriguing.” She returned to her work, floating some mechanical piece into place along the back of the crude power armor. “There was certainly no opportunity to work on such interesting arcane technology when we were together in Unity.” There was a momentary pause in her work, brief enough that I almost missed it. “Nor was there any desire for such, now that I think on it.”

I considered that for a moment. “I take it this Unity wasn’t much for individuality?”

“What need did we have for individuality when we were one?” Echo replied. “We were the whole, and the whole was us. What was good for one was good for all.”

“Wow,” Starlight said. “Yeah, I’m switching my vote on alicornhood from ‘no’ to ‘hell no’.”

“There is no need for you to be concerned about that,” Echo grumbled. “That aspect of our Unity was a gift from our mother. Without her, we are adrift and alone.”

“I don’t mean to diminish your loss,” I said, “and I recognize it’s not quite the same thing, but you’re not entirely alone.”

She scoffed. “It is a meager shadow of what I once knew,” she said in a low tone, keeping her attention focused on her work. Tools and parts floated in purple magic. “Still, I appreciate the gesture, and will strive to make do with what I have. Even I must admit to have found some silver lining to these unfortunate events.”

I nodded. “Discovering your own interests?”

She paused, looking off into space for a moment before resuming her work. “I am uncertain if it is discovering something very old or something very new, but yes.”

The conversation lapsed, and I sat there for a while, thinking, until Starlight’s words brought my attention back to the present. “Oh boy. He’s giving Sickle ammo.”

I looked over just in time to see Dusty finish inserting the drum and chambering a round. The rifle looked ridiculously tiny on her side, even with the suppressor extending the weapon’s length.

“Remember,” Dusty was saying. “Keep the weapon pointed downrange at all times. Safety on unless you’re expecting to shoot. Never point it at anypony unless you’re intending to shoot them.”

“Yeah, yeah,” Sickle grumbled. I had to give Dusty credit for perseverance; he’d apparently worn her down from ‘belligerently hostile’ to ‘irritated but resigned’, and she followed his directions, even if every inch of body language suggested her annoyance.

“Okay,” Dusty said, stepping back before pointing with a hoof at a dead tree some hundred yards away. “Go ahead and disengage the safety, then line up the sights on the target.”

“Uh-huh,” Sickle muttered around the bit. I saw her jaw shift slightly as she worked the safety latch, then her head twitched upwards. She adjusted her stance, first lowering her chest a bit, then sticking her rump up, and finally arching her back. “Well this is awkward as shit. How the fuck am I supposed to aim this?”

“Practice, mostly,” Dusty replied. “I’d say it took the average soldier a good week of combat drills and a few hundred rounds of ammunition to become acceptably proficient with battle-saddle mounts, and specialists put in many times that. You’re getting the crash-course version.”

“Lucky me,” Sickle grumbled. “No wonder Rattle couldn’t hit shit.” She bit down, and a single sharp crack echoed across the shallow basin. I could see Sickle frown, then she bit down again, and again. The weapon fired a few more times, then stopped.

“What the fuck?” Sickle snapped, standing upright again and turning to glare at the weapon. “Did this shit break? I know they hold more shots than that!”

“They do,” Dusty said. “But I only loaded five rounds into the mag.”

“Well give me a full one!” Sickle shot back. “And why was it only firing one at a time? This shit’s supposed to be full-auto, right?”

“It can be,” he said, removing the drum from her weapon. “I just wanted to make sure you have the basics of weapon handling down before you get to playing around too much. I’ll give you a few more rounds, you can get some practice in using the weapon. Once you’re doing well enough, we’ll step you up.”

Sickle groaned. “Leave it to you to make guns even more boring.”

“Trust me,” Dusty said as he slowly loaded a few more rounds into the magazine. “When it comes to guns, boring is good. Exciting means something’s gone wrong.”

“And this is why I kick things instead of shooting them,” Sickle grumbled.

Dusty gave a chuckle. “So far, you aren’t shooting things because your aim is horrible. You didn’t even come close to the tree.”

“Oh, fuck off,” Sickle replied. “I had that circle-cross thingy right over the tree. Not my fault the fucking sights are off.”

“Getting the sights aligned is part of why we’re doing this.” He slid the partially loaded drum into place again, racked the bolt, and gave her a pat on the side. “You’re loaded. Keep the aim-point at the center of the tree, right where it splits into two branches. Fire three rounds, I’ll adjust, we repeat. Got it?”

With little else to do, I watched the brief training session. There were several cycles of firing and adjusting, with Sickle grumpily following Dusty’s directions. Eventually he switched the rifle to full-auto, letting her fire a few bursts that peppered the tree with bullets. With the weapon securely mounted to her side, I was hardly surprised at how easily she could control the recoil, and with the aid of the aiming device Echo had rigged up for her, she was even reasonably accurate.

On the other hoof, it still took her a good five seconds to line up a shot.

It was getting late when he finally decided she was ready.

The heavy-barrel rifle came off, and Dusty hefted the heavy machine gun in its place. The mounting bracket Echo had rigged up attached easily, and after a minute, the weapon was set. Next came the ammunition. The can holding the ammo fit into a bracket Echo had attached across the back of the harness, with the belt feeding down through a simple chute and into the weapon itself.

Dusty racked back the charging handle, chambering a round. “Okay, weapon’s hot. Now remember, we don’t have much ammo for this. If you spend this belt, you might have to do without for a while. We’ll try to make sure you have some ammo, but if you want more, you’ll have to spend some of your share of the caps… so try not to waste too many rounds.”

“Yeah, okay,” Sickle said with a resigned sigh.

“I’ve got it set to single-shot right now to check the aim,” he said, stepping back and sitting to put his hooves over his ears. “Put one round into the tree, same point.”

Sickle’s jaw tightened, and the monstrous gun thundered, kicking out a small wake of dust and echoing across the landscape. Fragments of dry wood flew from where the top of the dead tree had been moments earlier. For the first time in a few hours, Sickle cracked a smile. “Yeah, that’s more fucking like it.”

“Looks like the sight is aligned,” Dusty said, lowering his hooves. “Okay, it’s yours, now. It’s an expensive piece of hardware, so if you want to keep using it, I expect you to take care of it.” He turned to his saddlebags and pulled out a bundle. “Which means it’s time to teach you how to clean it.”

Sickle’s smile vanished. “Aaand we’re back to boring.”

☢

We spent the night there, enjoying the relative comfort of the abandoned facility. Sure, the air was a little musty due to the lack of maintenance in the air system, and everything was coated in a fine layer of dust, but the beds were more comfortable than anything I’d had since leaving my chrysalis.

When we returned to the motorwagon that morning, we found Echo slumped over the power armor she had been working on, with several disassembled pieces of scientific equipment all neatly arrayed around her. She was snoring softly.

There was an amused silence as we looked over the scene, until Starlight spoke up with deliberate loudness. “She looks so cute when she’s not being so arrogant.”

Echo’s head jerked up and she slid back to a sitting position, blinking several times before the scene and words finally registered. “I am not arrogant,” she said, and wobbled a little before bracing herself. “...What time is it?”

Starlight was grinning. “You’re wearing a PipBuck.”

Echo frowned and looked down at the device, wobbling a little as she lifted her hoof. “Right.”

Dusty climbed up to the motorwagon’s window, sitting on the edge for the moment. “Did you stay up all night working on that?”

“Of course not,” Echo said, shuffling her wings before raising her head, taking up her usual prim and proper pose, though she remained sitting. “I obviously slept, and for a perfectly reasonable time. I simply overslept is all.”

Starlight snickered. “Uh-huh. Who’s got a problem about honesty now?”

Echo’s expression tightened, eyes widening and ears standing alert. Her mouth hung open for a moment before she formulated a response. “I… suppose ‘reasonable’ is a very subjective term that we might not exactly agree on, so I am not technically being dishonest.”

“Ah, yes,” I said. “Technically true, the best kind of true.” Then I smiled. “Mostly because it’s also the best kind of lie.”

She scowled, raising a hoof to rub at her eyes, but catching herself halfway there and quickly setting her hoof down again. “It is much too early to have someone twisting my words around over something so unimportant.” She pointedly turned to look at Dusty. “I assume from this gathering that you intend to depart?”

“Yep,” he replied. “How’s the armor doing?”

“It is taking me longer than I had hoped,” Echo replied with a hint of a grumble. “The brute caused a considerable amount of damage when she disabled it, particularly in the torso. Unfortunately, the torso articulation is the most complicated of the entire armor. I have made great progress, but it will require several more hours to fabricate the necessary replacement parts from what I have.”

“Several hours, got it.” Dusty nodded. “Well, it’ll have to wait. We’ve got a long ride to Trotsen, but since we’re setting out early, we might make it today.”

“That will be a lengthy journey,” Echo noted, and her magic reached out to grab the various parts gathered around her. “Very well. I shall continue my work once we have arrived there.”

In moments, all of the various parts were tucked neatly away, and the power armor was once again laid out on its side at the back. Echo stood atop the motorwagon, spreading her wings. “Again, I shall follow you from above.”

With that final statement, she beat her wings, rising up into the sky.

“Bitch talks way too much,” Sickle said as she climbed up into the rear of the motorwagon, the vehicle creaking under her weight. My attention again turned to the massive barrel sticking out past her chest. Sickle was menacing enough on her own, but I had gotten used to her presence. The addition of the huge gun changed that, and I found myself regularly glancing over at it.

I tried to shake off the nervous feeling, reasoning that I would eventually get used to it, just as I had with the leg blades, spear-like horn, and general demeanor. I climbed into the rear of the motorwagon, stowing my bags and gear beside me.

That gear included the new rifle, along with a pair of pouches holding loaded drums. Dusty had me put a drum through it in steady bursts, and I had to admit, it controlled nicely, especially when I was lying down with the bipod out. It might be clunky compared to my regular rifle, but when I was putting tight bursts into a dead tree probably three hundred yards away, I could appreciate its advantages. It was more light machine gun than rifle.

Still, it would probably live there in the motorwagon, except for the occasions where I needed to use it.

“Open up your map,” Dusty said to Starlight as he climbed in, setting his own rifle beside him. “Scroll up north, about thirty miles.”

Starlight did so, and Dusty gave a few corrections before finding the right place. “There. That’s an old road, goes all the way to Trotsen. You’ll make your way north until we hit that, then follow it west all the way to the city. Good?”

“You got it,” Starlight said, scrolling the map again. “Terrain’s a little rough between here and there, but I think we can do it, and it’ll all be smooth sailing from there.”

“Good,” Dusty said with a nod. “Let’s move out.”

☢

It took us almost two hours to wind our way through some particularly rocky terrain, but we eventually found our way to the road. It wasn’t much of a road, mind you. It certainly wasn’t the paved street or highways you might see in some cities. It was an old dirt road, unmaintained for two centuries. Still, it was a level path across the Wasteland, and almost entirely free of debris.

“Trotsen convoys make the trip on this road,” Dusty had said. “I’m sure they make sure it stays clear. We heard that a few raider gangs tried taking them on, but none of them were up to fighting a convoy of heavily armed motorwagons. Most just steer clear.”

He turned to give us a serious look. “But we aren’t a convoy, so keep your eyes out.”

So, while I spent a good portion of the journey adding to my recordings, and hoping the background noise wouldn’t be overwhelming, I kept an eye out.

☢

A rapid cacophony of impacts broke the monotony of driving, accompanied by the chatter and crack of automatic fire.

“Shit!” Starlight blurted as the motorwagon swerved sharply, throwing me against the edge of the window I was looking out, then back into the seat as she corrected. I quickly pushed myself back up. I had been watching out our left, and now turned my attention right. Dusty was grabbing his rifle, shouting out at the same time. “Step on it! Contact close right, high-ground!”

I slid across the seat as the motorwagon roared, snatching my rifle up in my magic and sticking it out the window. There was a small bluff less than a hundred yards away. Dusty was firing rapidly, peppering me with shell casings and kicking up plumes of dirt and dust from the ridge. At our speed, I couldn’t see any ponies. I was still searching when another series of snaps and cracks made me duck, with a couple rounds pinging off the side armor.

I came up firing, putting rounds out in the general direction of the low cliffs. I didn’t stop until the magazine ran empty, the cliffs already falling behind us.

That’s when we saw the twin plumes of dust kicking up from the low-ground nearby, their sources obscured by a low rise. I had just finished reloading when a pair of motorwagons came surging over that rise, tearing across the open ground between us.

“Whisper!” Dusty called out. “Get on the gun!”

I set my rifle down and scrambled over the back of my seat to climb up behind the machine gun. It was a bit cramped with Sickle there, but she didn’t complain about me taking the gun; she had her own, now, and was already turning to face the incoming vehicles, a grin on her face.

The attacking motorwagons had split up, with one swinging towards the road behind us, and the other speeding across the field to our side, running parallel to us. I focused on the one at our side. It was smaller than our motorwagon, but covered in heavy plates, and several long poles were topped by pony skulls. I swung the machine gun around, bracing against the wild bumps and lurches of the rough road, and hit the trigger.

I fired a short burst, just a few rounds, but I knew as I fired that I had missed. I fought against the bumping and swaying of the wagon to get my aim on-target. There was movement in the back of the other motorwagon, and something long pointed in our direction. I hit the trigger again, laying out another short burst. I couldn’t tell if I had hit, but the motorwagon immediately swerved away.

I looked behind us, where the second motorwagon had just pulled onto the road, swerving as it plunged into the trail of dust we were kicking up. This motorwagon was similar in size to our own vehicle, but taller, and featuring a massive wedge of metal welded to the front like a giant, murderous plow. Through the dust, I could just make out a pair of ponies riding in the back, clutching spears in their mouths and wearing thick metal armor.

Getting the gun pointed behind us was difficult, and I had to press one rear hoof against Sickle’s side to push myself halfway onto the roof, awkwardly wedging myself alongside the gun as I got it turned around.

The driver of the other vehicle saw what I was doing, and swerved off the road again on our left. Behind it, a great plume of dirt and smoke burst from the receding cliffs, and a purple, winged form arced up into the sky. Echo had joined the fray.

Despite driving off the road, the close motorwagon was still gaining on us. I dropped down again before swinging the gun all the way around, but I hadn’t even started climbing up again before the other vehicle swung over, plunging through our dust-trail to the other side of the road.

As I got down again, Sickle reared up in the back of our vehicle, pointing a bladed hoof. “Fuck off, you little shits, or I’m coming over there and kicking your asses!”

I doubt they heard her. I could barely hear her over the clatter and roar. Still, if I had seen Sickle pointing and yelling at me, I would have reconsidered what I was doing.

Instead, the attacking vehicle centered on the road, rapidly closing on us.

“Sickle!” I shouted out as loud as I could over the cacophonous noise. “Shoot them!”

“Fuck that!” she shouted back, planting her hooves on the edges of the cargo bay.

I cast a quick glance off to the side. The other vehicle was driving straight away from us, perhaps deciding we were too dangerous of a target. Black smoke mixed with the plume of dust behind them. I’d evidently hit something. In any case, they were not currently a threat, especially as I saw Echo swooping into a steep dive toward them.

I gave up on the machine gun, snatching my rifle from the back seat. A bullet cracked by my head. Another smacked loudly against Sickle’s armor. She roared in reply.

The other vehicle was pushing up beside us as I floated my rifle around. It was almost impossible to aim, but it was a point-blank shot. I switched it to automatic and held down the trigger, trying to aim for the windows.

As the front end of the attacking vehicle got beside us, it swerved. Sickle leaped. The other vehicle slammed into the rear corner of ours with a tremendous thud, throwing me to the side. My helmet hit the side armor. Dust flooded over everything. Our motorwagon swerved again, shuddering hard and bouncing off the road. All the cargo slid around violently as the world spun.

I leaped for safety, wings beating to lift me clear of the chaos. The entire road turned to dust as I surged upwards, still reeling from the blow to the head. I caught a glimpse of the other motorwagon, with Sickle clinging to the hood and kicking at the window, before it disappeared into the cloud of dust kicked up by our own wagon’s uncontrolled skid.

Sickle came flying out of the cloud, completely airborne, followed a moment later by the tumbling motorwagon. Our own wagon shuddered as it slid and skipped sideways across the ground, my heart lurching as it tipped, but it finally came to a rest upright. The cloud of dust it had kicked up washed over everything.

I shook myself from gawking and turned, wings beating as I swooped down toward the hostile motorwagon, changing magazines as I closed in. Through the dust, I could see it had landed on its side. My E.F.S. showed at least one hostile being within.

Sickle was nearby, slowly pushing herself up and shaking her head. “...Motherfucker!”

Something vaguely pony-shaped moved in the back of the motorwagon. I back-winged, drawing short, and put out a long burst. I couldn’t tell if I hit, but whatever it was retreated into the shelter of the vehicle.

Sickle was already trotting toward the vehicle, favoring a foreleg. I swung wide behind her, following her in.

She just went right up to the rear of the vehicle, a cargo bed much like on our own, and stuck her head in.

There was a shout, then gunshots. Sickle jerked back, then roared again, wedging her upper body in through the rear window. There was cursing and a few more gunshots, and Sickle pulled back, dragging out a dirt-caked and bleeding pony, still clutching a pistol in his mouth.

Despite the broken leg dangling uselessly at his side, the pony twisted his head around, firing another round into the only part he could currently aim at, Sickle’s side. It did as little as you might expect against her thick armor, and Sickle responded by rearing up, gripping the pony in both forelegs, and bashing him against the rear of the wagon.

The fight seemed to go out of the pony, but after a moment to recover, he turned his head and fired several more times into her armored shoulder. Sickle responded by smashing the pony against the motorwagon again and again and again.

I landed on the upturned side, blinking against the dust that stung at my eyes. My heart hammered as I peeked through the side window, rifle floating beside my head. I saw movement, hastily aimed, then stopped. It was the rear leg of a pony, kicking in slow, weak spasms at the far side of the interior. The rest of her body had been sticking out of the window, and was now crushed under several tons of motorwagon.

I pushed out my magic, casting a bright green glow through the dust-choked interior and checking that there were no more ponies. My E.F.S. confirmed it.

At the rear of the wagon, Sickle finally ceased her banging, tossing aside the limp and excessively dead pony.

Two cracks sounded from somewhere nearby, and I quickly scanned around, but the slowly settling dust still hung thick in the air. A moment later, my earbud crackled with Dusty’s voice. “Whisper, check in.”

“Here!” I said into the broadcaster, still looking around. “I’m at the other motorwagon. They’re dead.”

“Is Sickle there?”

“Yes. She’s fine.”

“Good,” he said. “I’ve got another contact due south of my position, obscured by dust. Get airborne and get eyes on them.”

“On it!”

I shot upwards, clear of the cloud of dust. My E.F.S. was showing a single contact, and I turned to face it. Through the haze of dust, I spotted the silhouette of a pony, low to the ground. I slowed to a hover, leveled my rifle, and kicked on S.A.T.S. Two bursts kicked up several sprays of dirt, and while the form barely moved, the contact marker winked out.

“They’re down,” I reported over the broadcaster.

“Copy. Get a good three-sixty scan, then get back down here.”

I looked around, taking in the area. Another body lay a short distance from the motorwagon, close enough that I could see the ragged wound across her side. My E.F.S. showed no signs of life. There were no other ponies nearby. Looking further, I could see that the other motorwagon was continuing on, still trailing smoke, while Echo flew swiftly in our direction.

I dove down again, back-winging in time to land atop our motorwagon. Dusty was in the rear, perched on an uneven pile of jumbled gear. His rifle was up, and his eyes glanced my way as I landed.

“I didn’t see anyone else around,” I said, then pointed out in the direction of the fleeing vehicle. “The other motorwagon is running away, and smoking pretty badly.”

“Good,” he said, relaxing slightly. “That… could have gone a lot worse.”

“The hell was that?” Starlight said, perching on the edge of the window, and dabbing a hoof at the corner of her mouth, wiping away a tiny bit of blood. “Since when do raiders have motorwagons?”

“Motorwagons are supposed to be more common around Trotsen,” Dusty said as he climbed up on the roof for a better view; the dust was finally settling. “It’s where they were made, originally. I don’t know if these were raiders, exactly, but I guess it’s not too surprising other ponies would get their hooves on some motorwagons. We’ve seen raiders sporting some impressive hardware, after all.”

Meanwhile, I had dropped off the edge of the roof to hover beside Starlight. “Are you okay?”

“Yeah,” she said, wiping at her mouth again, then smiling. “Face-planted into the steering wheel when we spun out. Just split my lip is all. I’ve gotten worse just playing around.”

“When your ‘playing around’ is climbing and jumping all over ruined buildings, I’m hardly surprised.” Still, I eyed the injury warily, as if I might discern something that her PipBuck hadn’t already told her.

A burst of wind made me flinch back, and I looked up to see Echo directly above us, looking down with wide eyes. Her voice was surprisingly loud. “Is everyone okay?”

“We’re fine!” Dusty called out, then gestured with his PipBuck-clad hoof. “We need to get you fixed up with a broadcaster so we can communicate with you.”

“Yes, of course,” she replied, her voice back to a conversational volume as she landed lightly on the rear of the motorwagon. “And the attacking ponies?”

“Dead or driven off,” he said, gesturing in the direction of the other motorwagon. The dust had cleared enough for me to see Sickle rooting around inside it.

“Well, that is good,” she said with a sharp nod, and followed it up with a frown as she looked down into the cargo bed. “We really must find a better way for you to secure your cargo.” Her magic enveloped the contents, rapidly placing them back in their respective places.

Starlight hopped down and trotted over to the other motorwagon, and I followed.

Our own vehicle sported only a shallow dent and some scrapes on the rear corner. The other motorwagon had not fared nearly so well. One of the front wheels was bent almost entirely sideways, and the body itself was visibly twisted from the crash. Everything was coated in dirt.

Sickle was sitting beside the wagon, checking over the pony she had killed. It looked as if his fashion choice had been much like hers, though his metal armor was both thinner and less complete in its coverage. Several spikes were welded across his back, most of which were now bent from Sickle’s assault.

If these ponies weren’t raiders, they were certainly taking to the raider aesthetic.

Starlight paused, watching Sickle for a moment before speaking. “Okay, I’ve got to admit, ending a motorwagon chase by jumping over and kicking the other wagon to death? That was pretty cool.”

“Fuck yeah it was!” Sickle said, grinning behind her muzzle. “Think I cracked some ribs. Oh, that looks good.” She pulled something away from the body—a pill, I think—and slapped it between the bars of her muzzle to swallow it.

Starlight started looking over the motorwagon, joined moments later by Echo.

“Well, the front axle is toast, obviously,” Starlight noted. “Must have landed right on it. Look at how cleanly the struts sheared!”

“The vehicle’s chassis was deformed by the collision,” Echo said, leaning in close to examine the underside of the vehicle. “It has much lighter armor than your vehicle. I assume that and the lighter cargo load explains its superior speed.”

“Probably,” Starlight agreed. “Think we could fix it up?”

Echo gave a sharp nod. “Undoubtedly. My only concern is whether the motor or transmission has been damaged.”

I moved to the passenger compartment, looking around for anything we should take, while they continued their conversation. I did my best to ignore the now-still legs sticking through the window, and rooted around.

There were a few soft thumps from the undercarriage, followed by Starlight’s voice. “I’m not seeing any external damage on them.”

Dusty joined us. “Find anything?”

“Not yet,” I said.

Starlight called out, rather happily, “I think we can fix it!”

“Fix it?” Dusty asked, as if the thought hadn’t occurred to him until that moment. “How long will that take?”

“A few hours,” Echo said. “A day at most.”

“More delays,” Dusty said. “And in territory where we’ve already been attacked once. I know we’ve got a lot of firepower, but I don’t like tempting fate. We should move on before we attract any more attention.”

Sickle called out from somewhere more distant. “Fuck that, I like the attention!”

“Seems like a shame to just leave it,” Starlight said, climbing up atop the upturned vehicle to peer in the side window, and smiled when she saw me there.

“We don’t really need a second motorwagon,” Dusty noted.

“Well, maybe Echo wouldn’t have to fly everywhere?”

“I am perfectly content with flying,” Echo said. “Still, I suppose it would be more relaxing.”

“You can always perch on the roof,” Dusty said.

“I suppose.” From her tone, I could picture the frown she must have been wearing.

“Well, what about selling it?” Starlight asked. “A working motorwagon is worth a small fortune if you can sell it, and Trotsen seems like the place that would buy them, right?”

“They probably have enough already,” Dusty said, though his tone had turned more thoughtful. “Still… would be a shame to pass up something that valuable. Hmm. Tell you what. If you two can get this thing mobile in, say, thirty minutes, we’ll take it with us. You can finish repairs once we get to Trotsen, or we can find somepony to buy it. Sound good?”

“You bet!” Starlight said, immediately galloping for our motorwagon and the tools she had there.

Echo flew after her. “I do not think we can repair the axle in time, but perhaps we could arrange a way to tow the vehicle…”

A half-hour later, the damaged motorwagon had been righted, its front end lifted and secured to the rear of our own by a quickly kludged-together hitch. It was an awkward-looking arrangement, but it sufficed to move.

Looting had come up light. There was a pistol and a rifle, both pipe weapons, and a small supply of ammunition for each. There was a five-gallon canister about half-full of water, a few cans of food, and a few drugs that Sickle had quickly snatched up. A small set of tools were scattered around the cab, and while they looked brand new, we already had more than enough of our own.

Still, we gathered it up. Every piece was something we could trade for caps. The only things we left were the armors they had been wearing, despite Sickle’s suggestion that Starlight could use some better armor.

Starlight declined, naturally. “I’m not wearing raider armor.”

She did, however, snatch the goggles one of the ponies had been wearing. On seeing it, I immediately started looking for a second set for myself. The closest I found was a gas mask. I declined to take it.

We piled in once more and continued on our way, a little slower as we towed the second vehicle, while Echo flew close overhead.

☢

“Trotsen is pretty much the industrial center of the region,” Dusty said as I finished unloading the machine gun. “So I guess that much hasn’t changed.”

I floated the ammo can back, setting it in the bed of the vehicle before leaning in under the gun itself. “Probably about the only thing that hasn’t, then.”

“True,” Dusty said. “The stripes hit the place with some sort of seismic megaspell. Tore the ground right up. Not sure why they did that instead of balefire. Maybe they figured it’d wreck factories better or something.”

I pulled out the thick pin holding the mount in place, then struggled to lift the gun. Dusty had asked me to take down the gun; if raiders were driving around in motorwagons, he wanted us to do everything we could to not look hostile. “How bad is it?”

“Not sure,” Dusty said. “I’ve never been here, before. Way I hear it, the ground split open in some places, and shot hundreds of feet into the sky in others. Ah, there we are.”

The vehicle rattled as we rounded another rocky hillside, and I finally got the gun down, placing it in the cargo bed. I climbed back into the rear seat, and through the front windows, past the jagged rock formations that hemmed in the rocky road, I could see massive iron gates spanning between two cliff faces. They were overlooked by battlements, with a wild variety of ancient signs, strips of canvas, and other seemingly random adornments arrayed around the tops.
I settled into my seat, gathering my belongings. My armor was already hidden with my disguised form, but I took the time to remove most of the combat-related equipment from my walking-around gear. The pistol should be more than enough.

I was almost done when Starlight gave a quiet gasp. “Oh shit.”

Looking forward, I didn’t immediately see what drew that reaction. It wasn’t until I noticed she was looking upwards that I leaned my head out of the window to see what she had seen.

What I found sent a chill through me.

Above the massive gate, suspended by her neck, hung the corpse of a changeling.

Chapter Thirty Seven: Casualties

A long, thin line of dust cut through the Wasteland.

At least two dozen motorwagons tore down the bare dirt trail. It was the same trail the Trotsen caravans had used for years, but this time, it bore a different cargo. Two hundred ponies, maybe more, were tucked into every available space. They carried weapons of all sorts, from spears to machine guns, with expressions both angry and eager.

At their head rumbled Sandstorm’s Beast, a relic of an earlier age. A mighty war machine, eager to return to the role it had been built for centuries ago. It roared like its namesake, a warcry echoed by those who followed.

And I was following right behind it, surrounded by ponies looking for a fight.

I had turned these ponies loose on the Wasteland. Now, I could only hope I could nudge them in the right direction.

☢

The great convoy had halted for the evening, parked in a chaotic cluster of vehicles. Even with our speed limited to that of the slowest of the vehicles, we had already covered half the distance to Mareford, and we could expect to arrive the next afternoon. While several eager mechanics had already detached our second vehicle to work on fixing it up—without even bothering to ask us—I made my way to where Sandstorm consulted with her riders. Echo and Sickle followed on my flanks, like a pair of large and terrifying bodyguards.

Sandstorm was standing beside a folding table, along with a small group of ponies. Axle was at her side, speaking while she looked at the map spread across the table. “Gangrene and Howler caught up with us, but there’s still no word of Shaft, Buckeye, or Clanger’s patrol. I don’t know if they’ll have time to catch up before we get to this ‘Serenity’ place.”

I was almost to them when a pony stepped in front of me. “Turn around,” she said, magic glowing around the grip of her shotgun. “Riders only.”

Sandstorm looked up. She was dusty from the day of travel, and her eyes were still reddened, but her expression looked as hard and determined as ever. That expression darkened the moment she saw me. “Let her through.”

The guard frowned, but stepped aside, eying me suspiciously.

I continued forward, giving an appreciative nod to Sandstorm. “Thank you.”

She ignored me, turning back to Axle. “What were you saying?”

“The patrols,” he said, casting repeated wary glances my way. “Gangrene and—”

“Right,” Sandstorm said, nodding. “Nothing to worry about. They’ll have plenty of time to catch up. They’ll be faster, and they can go direct while we swing by Mareford.”

“Wait,” Axle said, his ears shooting up, and casting me another quick glance. “We’re really going to Mareford?”

Sandstorm’s eyes narrowed ever so slightly, a look that seemed particularly dangerous to me. “I want more guns and ammo,” she said. “Everything we can get, and those Mareford fucks are going to give us a damn good deal on them if they know what’s good for them. Hell, won’t hurt to spread word about these damn bugs. Maybe if they see their own head on the chopping block, they might get off their fat asses and do something for a change.”

She was going to Mareford, spreading information, and giving them the opportunity to join in, all while keeping a position of power by not explicitly going there for help. I didn’t have the time to fully consider the stance before she turned to me and quite bluntly asked, “What the fuck do you want?”

I blinked, but quickly recovered. “I was hoping to find out what the plan was.”

One of the other riders, a mare with spiked armor, cut in. “Who the hell is this? Sandy, what’s going on?”

Sandstorm scowled as she turned on the rider. “What’s going on is this dipshit has a pair of motorwagons and some hired guns. She’s willing to go along with the whole ‘stomp the bugs’ plan, so she gets to play at being a rider.”

The mare glanced warily between us. “Just like that? She could be a changeling!”

“Of course she could be a fucking changeling,” Sandstorm said, an edge creeping into her voice. “Hell, so could you, or any of the rest. That’s the problem, ain’t it?” She lifted a hoof, gesturing to me. “Right now, she’s helping us, so we’ll let her help us. If she decides she’s not going to help us any more, well, we’ll just have to make a new arrangement…”

She trailed off with a warning glare at me.

The other mare grumbled, but begrudgingly backed down, casting her own glare my way. “Fine.”

A nearby stallion with a spiky red mane grumbled. “I don’t like this.”

Sandstorm’s jaw clenched. She turned to him with a dangerous purpose to her movements. “You going to bitch to me about not liking the situation?” She took a very deliberate step towards him. “You really want to go down that fucking road with me right now?”

He wisely backed down. “No, ma’am. Sorry.”

“Good,” she growled, and turned back to the table. “Then let’s stop whining about all this stupid shit and start focusing on the real problem.” Her hoof came up, jabbing at the map. It landed right on a penciled-in mark: Serenity.

One of the other riders, a silver-maned mare, quickly stepped forward to help shift the subject back. “We’re slower than the usual convoy, but we’ll still make Mareford by mid-day. Best time from there to this ‘Serenity’ place would probably be around six hours, depending on what the old roads are like in that area. That’d put us there around nightfall, maybe a bit after, but that doesn’t give us any time at Mareford.”

“And I don’t like the idea of showing up at night,” Sandstorm said. “So mid-day, day after tomorrow. Longer than I’d like, but it’ll have to do.”

“We’d be there tomorrow evening if we just go straight there,” Axle pointed out, but Sandstorm gave a dismissive wave of her hoof.

“We could split up,” another rider suggested. “Take the fastest wagons and best riders out to Mareford, while the Beast and other wagons go direct. We’ll have to gun it, but it’ll give us some time to work out a deal and still meet with you well before dark.”

The first rider grunted. “I dunno. I mean, hell, neither group would be an easy target, but you know how bad the raiders have gotten lately. Something’s up with them.”

My ears perked. “You’ve been having raider problems?”

The looks from most of the ponies was predictably icy at my intrusion. Sandstorm came to my defense, whether intentional or not. “Motorwagons,” she said. “Sure, raiders get their hooves on a working motorwagon every now and then. It happens. Either they dig one up and get it running, or take out an inexperienced crew and steal theirs. Usually, they don’t last long before we take ‘em out, but lately they’ve been flush with ‘em. We’re up to, what, eight new wagons this last month?”

She looked around until Axle gave a nod, and gestured to me. “Nine, including the one she captured.”

“Nine,” Sandstorm echoed. “I figure they must have turned up some old wagon yard or something. They ain’t done much with ‘em yet, ‘cept lose the one that tried hitting our convoy, but they’re being more of a pest than usual. If it weren’t for the fucking bugs stirring shit up, I’d have my riders out putting those raiders down and finding out where they got their rides. We can always use some more wagons.”

“A sudden upswing in raider activity and equipment,” I noted, frowning. “It seems like that’s been happening a lot, lately. This might be Serenity’s doing.”

A couple of the cold looks had been replaced by questioning ones, so I explained myself. “They’ve used raiders before. Pass on equipment or information, and let the expendable raiders do their dirty work. And Serenity has motorwagons.” I inclined my head towards where my companions had set camp. “We swiped our first wagon from them, and they had several more.”

There were a few murmurs at the news—whether that of Serenity’s involvement with raiders or my mention of previous contact with them—but Sandstorm cut them short by speaking up. “Doesn’t matter, anyway,” she said with another wave of her hoof. “We’re not splitting up. I want a show of force when we roll up on Mareford. We’re going to let those sedentary morons know we mean business.”

I nodded, glad she’d made that call, even if her intent was a bit more aggressive than I would have liked.

“So,” she said, looking over the gathered riders. “On to Mareford in the morning. We set camp there, get a good deal on all the guns and ammo we can carry, maybe convince a few of their so-called Militia to get off their asses and actually help ponies for a fucking change.”

One of the riders snorted. “Ain’t like we need their help.”

I spoke up. “Against Serenity, I think we can use all the friends we—”

The spiky-haired stallion cut me off. “There ain’t no fucking ‘we’, bitch. You ain’t one of us. I don’t think you’re even—”

“Hey!” Sandstorm’s shout cut across the group, instantly silencing the stallion. She leveled a hoof at him. “She’s our guest, so watch your fucking mouth you disrespectful cunt.”

As he cringed back, she turned to look at me. “Well? Keep talking, bitch.”

There were a few snickers from the gathered riders, as well as a look of silent annoyance from the stallion. I wasn’t surprised that Sickle snickered as well.

I ignored that and continued. “What I was saying was that we could use all the friends we can get, and I think I have some friends that might help out.”

She frowned, pausing for a moment before speaking. “Don’t think we need any ‘friends’ here, but hell, I ain’t turning away anypony who wants to squash some bugs. They want to tag along, fine. Who are they?”

“Enclave Loyalists,” I said. “About fifty or sixty soldiers, maybe more.”

In my defense, calling them “friends” was more of an exaggeration rather than an outright lie. Echo didn’t directly call me out on the claim, but I’d still like to get that down for the record.

Several of the ponies looked at me with perked ears and looks of surprise at my unusual claim, and I clarified. “They’re the ‘good guy’ side of the civil war going on up there. They’ve been trying to help ponies down here, and they’ve got good reason to dislike Serenity. We’ve met with them before. If they see hundreds of ponies gathering to fight Serenity, they’ll want to pitch in and make sure we win.”

Sandstorm’s expression had soured. “I trust the birdies about as much as I trust the bugs,” she said with distaste, before her expression mellowed. “Still, be nice to have some more fliers, since it looks like changelings can fly. Fuck it, why not?” She lifted a hoof, tapping the edge of the map. “Where are they?”

I quickly consulted my PipBuck, comparing locations for a moment before reaching out to tap at the map a short ways east of Rust. “They were camped here last we saw them, but they had been moving regularly. They probably won’t be there, but we should come across one of their patrols easily enough.”

Axle grunted. “That’s way out of the way! That’d add a whole day to our trip!”

“At least ten hours,” another pony said, leaning over the map. “Maybe twelve. Terrain is a bit rough there.”

“And that’s if we stumble across them right away,” Sandstorm noted, and shook her head. “Sorry, not happening. I’m not giving these bugs any more time to prepare.”

My ears flicked back. “But we could use their help, and it’s only a small delay.”

“I said it ain’t happening,” she said, and gestured a hoof around. “This ride ain’t stopping. Be glad we’re even swinging by Mareford. You want to bring in these Enclave pricks, you can haul your tail over there and tell ‘em yourself. Put a hustle on it and you can catch up with us at Mareford.”

I frowned, looking at the map. It’d probably be doable, assuming the Loyalists hadn’t moved camp or we found them quickly enough, but there was little room for complications. “That might work,” I said, reluctant. “Though my wagon is a bit heavily loaded. We’d make better time if we could offload some of our cargo to one of your wagons.”

There were a few grumbles from the riders, including a few who spoke up. “We’re not your mules.”

“Consider it collateral, then,” I said, “for our good behavior. If we don’t show up again, you get to keep it.”

“I won’t turn down free shit,” Sandstorm said, “especially since most of it is weapons. The hauler won’t even notice the load, and it’s still faster than the tank. Deal.” She held out her hoof, and I shook it, as she added, “Feel free to not come back.”

“I’ll meet you at Mareford,” I said evenly, gave a parting nod, and walked off.

As I left, I heard Axle speak up. “You’re just letting her go?”

Sandstorm’s groan brought a smile to my face. “Seriously, you bitches whine that she’s here, now you’re whining that she’s leaving. Buck up, already. We’ve got a fight to look forward to.”

The rest of the conversation faded into the background as the distance grew.

☢

We set off early in the morning, before the sky had fully brightened.

It was easy to forget just how much of an arsenal we had accumulated from the mercenaries and raiders we had fought. It wasn’t until we started unloading our motorwagon that the truly excessive scale of it became apparent. Dozens of grenades and mines. Multiple heavy weapons. Two sets of damaged power armor. Roughly a hundred pounds of explosives. Enough small arms to outfit an entire squad of ponies, with enough ammunition that it would have been easier to measure it by weight instead of by round, if only we had scales. And that wasn’t even counting the two drums of water, the large stash of canned and packaged food, an extensive variety of spare parts and mechanisms Starlight had picked out as valuable, or the assortment of barely-used camping gear we had forgotten beneath all the other stuff.

Almost all of it was unloaded. When we left, we were stripped down to a bare combat load: our personal gear, some spare ammo, and three days’ worth of food and water. All told, we probably offloaded a literal ton of equipment, and I could see that the wagon sat noticeably higher on its suspension.

We carefully inventoried everything, and persuaded the increasingly impatient rider taking the cargo to verify the count. Then we climbed into our lightened vehicle and set off, rattling and bouncing across the Wasteland with renewed speed.

☢

Starlight made exceptional time. It was a rough ride, as she drove the motorwagon across the uneven terrain at speeds she wouldn’t have risked—or possibly even been able to reach—with all our cargo.

It was exhausting, and it was exhilarating. We tore across the dry Wasteland at speeds I would normally only experience when flying. Starlight was exuberant, with a huge grin, eyes narrowed in excitement behind her goggles. Sickle stood tall in the rear, her hooves braced against the vehicle frame, giving the occasional enthusiastic yell.

I managed to hold out for almost half an hour, my mind occupied by concerns over current events, before their enthusiasm seeped into me and planted its hooks.

By the time we neared the Enclave camp, my squishy pony body felt sore and bruised from the journey, but I was grinning just as much as Starlight was.

The good mood quickly faded as we drove up to the camp at a more sedate speed. Sure enough, the Loyalists had moved on. The camp was abandoned, the tents removed. The few bits that did remain were clearly worse for wear.

Dusty ordered me onto the gun as we approached. I slid out over the back of the seat, and reared up to grip the machine gun. I pivoted it around as I scanned over the remains of the camp, keeping the barrel elevated in case any friendly ponies were out there.

The signs of magical energy weapon strikes were clear on the abandoned earthworks. The rearmost tower had collapsed. A few tattered tents had been left behind, and several craters peppered the interior of the camp. There had been a serious fight here, but there was no sign of either side.

“This looks bad,” Dusty said, already turned to look out from the camp. I turned the gun around to do the same. “Serenity must have hit them before they moved out,” he continued. “Hard to say how the fight turned out, and there’s no telling where they went.”

“So, what now?” Starlight asked. “Drive around looking for a patrol? That could take hours.”

“We don’t even know if they’re patrolling this area any more,” Dusty said. “If Serenity hit their camp, that means they either evaded their patrols or hit too hard and fast for Aurora’s forces to hold them off. Either way, it means Serenity has the upper hoof in this area. She may not risk sending patrols around here.”

I mulled over that for a moment, while Echo spiraled down, landing in the midst of the camp and slowly searching it. I watched for a bit before ducking down, looking under the roof at Dusty. “Okay, you’re the military pony. Say you were in charge of these Loyalists. You’re in unfriendly territory, and just got driven back by a superior force from Serenity. What would you do, and where would you go?”

He frowned around the bit of his rifle, considering it for several long moments. “Depends on how poorly it went. I’d certainly want to pull back and establish a better position. Ideally one Serenity doesn’t know of or will have a hard time locating. Even better, fall back to friendly positions. Biggest problem with that is ‘friendly positions’ means up in the clouds, and last we heard, they hadn’t been able to locate other Loyalists.”

“Okay,” I said, nodding along. “Let’s assume going above the clouds isn’t an option, because if they’ve gone up there, we wouldn’t be able to find them anyway. What does that leave them with?”

“Short term, they could stay on the move,” he said. “They’re mobile. Keep scouts out for early warning, keep moving any time hostile forces are detected.” He frowned. “Except they would have been doing the same thing for defending this camp, and that clearly didn’t work. Plus, staying mobile is exhausting, especially if they have to move casualties. On the other hoof, digging in means getting crushed by superior numbers. There’s not much of a good play, here.”

“It’s a bad situation,” I agreed. “So, given that, what would you do?”

He slowly scanned across the barren terrain as he mulled over the question. “Honestly? I’d either keep retreating at speed until it was clear there was no pursuit, or until I found friendly forces that could help mount an effective defense. ‘Cept they don’t have any friendly forces.” He gave a quiet snort, and after a moment, added, “Myself, I’d go for Mareford. Good, strong defenses, and probably the safest place in the Wasteland. Granted, that’s ‘cause I lived there, so I know what it’s like. Don’t know if Aurora would consider that a valid option or not.”

“It’s a possibility,” I said. “Would be awfully convenient.”

Dusty snorted. “Yeah. Too convenient to hope for.”

“Maybe.”

“Hmm. You know…” Dusty lowered his rifle, looking back to me. “Aurora said she’d been sending patrols by Gemstone regularly. It’s about the only place we know they might go by, and if they took any serious casualties, they’ll need to rest somewhere. If Aurora doesn’t consider Mareford viable, she might try sheltering there, at least temporarily. It’s not a good position, but it might be the best she has. Even if she isn’t there, she might still be in contact.”

“Might be worth checking out,” I said.

“Yeah,” he said, though his tone didn’t sound convinced. Still, he shored up his expression and gave a decisive nod. “Let’s do it.”

☢

The drive to Gemstone was less exuberant, but just as swift. I spent most of it in my natural form, with my armor, to protect against the banging and jostling of the wagon.

We were five miles out when Dusty called out, “Two fliers inbound, south-east high! Looks like Enclave.”

I quickly retook my disguise while Dusty brought out his binoculars. By the time I was ponified once more and on the gun, Dusty had them in sight. “Blue and rainbows. Looks like Loyalists.”

I grunted at how he said that. “Looks.”

“Yeah,” he said. “Keep an eye on them in case they attack. Hopefully they’re friendly, but I don’t want to take the chance.”

“Yeah,” I said. “I assume they’ve seen us?”

“Oh yeah,” Dusty replied. “They’re diving towards us, and one of ‘em pointed. Hey, give them a wave. If these are really Loyalists, we want to look friendly.”

I did so, giving an exaggerated wave to ensure they could see it. When I finished, my hooves returned to the gun, and I gave a dry snort. “You know, I appreciate the irony of me saying this, but sometimes I really hate dealing with changelings.

Sickle chuckled and gave me a heavy, spiky-hoofed pat on the back. “Yeah, we all do.”

“Thanks,” I grumbled, rolling my shoulder; the cloak had given enough padding to keep the spikes from drawing blood, but only just.

Echo had swooped down to fly just above us. As the flying ponies drew nearer, they veered to come in at an angle, the ominous gems of their weapons no longer pointing directly at us. I took that as a good sign, and gave another wave. One of the ponies returned the gesture, and soon were banking around, circling us as they bled off the last of their altitude. Two pips popped up on my E.F.S. as they swooped in beside us: non-hostile.

“Hey!” the lead mare called out in greeting as she slipped in, matching speed to fly just beside our motorwagon. “You heading in to Gemstone?”

“Yeah,” I called back. “We were looking for you guys, too. We need to talk.”

She held up a hoof, then turned her head away. I could barely hear her words over the wind and rattling of the wagon. “Yeah, it’s that changeling and her friends. Yeah, the same one. Says she’s looking for us.” There was a long pause. “You got it.”

Lowering her hoof, she looked back to us. “Okay, you’re cleared into town. Just don’t go pointing that thing at anypony!”

She immediately banked, wings pumping as she veered away, her partner mirroring her actions perfectly. Moments later they were both climbing up into the sky.

“Well that wasn’t the warmest welcome ever,” Starlight said from below.

“Warmer than getting shot,” Dusty said. “Seeing as they probably got in a big fight with Serenity, I imagine they’re going to be a bit wary.” There was a pause as he thumped his hoof against the roof. “Hey, Whisper?”

I slid down to peer in over the back seat. “Yeah?”

He’d turned to look back at me. “You sure you want to do this?” he asked. “These ponies know you’re a changeling, and if they’ve had trouble, they might not look too kindly on the fact. This could be dangerous for you.”

I frowned. He was right, after all. “Could be,” I said, slowly nodding, but I quickly hid the frown to put on a show of determination. “But I’m not sure there is any place that isn’t dangerous for me, right now. At least here we have the chance of improving our situation.”

“Fair enough,” he said with a nod, and turned back.

Minutes later, we came into sight of Gemstone. As we rolled over the tracks and up the path to the small town, we could see several figures atop the walls. One was a bright blue pony, while four more were clad in Enclave armor, the menacing black broken up by the Loyalist colors. The trio of magical energy weapons atop the wall swiveled to us; my heartbeat ratcheted up, but they simply tracked us, waiting in case we became a threat.

We came to a halt in front of the gate, waiting under the eyes of the Loyalist soldiers as the gate slowly swung open. Once it had, we rolled slowly through the opening.

There were a few more Loyalist soldiers beyond the gate, two of which were trotting our way, and further in I could see a few town ponies. One of the wall-top pegasi took wing, and once we were beyond the gate, flew in to hover before us, a hoof held up in a clear command to halt. The wagon ground to a halt once more, as black-armored pegasi surrounded us.

I started to worry that we had made a horrible mistake.

“Okay!” the lead pegasus called out. “Exit the vehicle, and leave all your weapons behind. You can have them back when you leave, but you’re not carrying them in town.”

The bright blue pony atop the wall was a unicorn stallion, and he reacted with surprise at that declaration. “What are you talking about?” he called out. “We don’t disarm our guests.”

“You don’t,” the pegasus replied, his attention focused on us. I couldn’t help but imagine him glaring behind those eyepieces. “But we do, especially for these ponies.”

“Now hold on a minute!” the stallion said, trotting down the stairs to approach the Loyalist soldier, while we remained carefully still and quiet in our motorwagon. “These ponies are our guests, and besides, this ain’t the first time they’ve been here. Well, ‘cept the big purple one, but I figure if they vouch for her, she must be all right.”

“They aren’t all ponies,” the pegasus replied, his gaze unwavering. “The gray one’s a changeling. Maybe the others, too.”

“Hey!” Starlight called out, thumping a hoof against the steering wheel. “Come on, really? Why don’t you shout it a little louder? There might be ponies in Mareford that didn’t hear you!”

I winced a little. I appreciated Starlight leaping to my defense, but I couldn’t see it helping us.

A mare’s voice cut across the argument. “What the hay is going on out here?”

I recognized that voice, ears perking up as I looked out the window. Sure enough, the Enclave Loyalist trotting up to the scene was Sergeant Hail Burst. The mask that would cover her muzzle hung at her side, letting everyone see that she looked thoroughly unhappy, a look only furthered by the pocked and charred surface of her armor. It seemed someone had unloaded a magical energy weapon into her side.

“I ordered these ponies to disarm,” the first pegasus said, gesturing our way before inclining his head to the unicorn guard. “Blueberry objected.”

Hail Burst turned to the approaching guard. “You understand that at least one of these individuals is a changeling, and that we can’t verify whether or not they work with the group that we have been fighting?”

The unicorn halted, casting a glance our way, frowning. “Can’t say I know anything about that,” he said, a cautious tone to his voice, but it vanished as he followed up. “Can’t say it makes any difference to me, either. We ain’t in the habit of assuming the worst of our guests, if you remember.”

Hail Burst had immediately turned back to the other pegasus. “Snowfall, your orders are to assist the locals in guarding the settlement, not to take over its operation. Unless they ask you to do something that directly violates your orders or our laws, you are to follow their direction. They can keep their equipment.” She then turned to look pointedly at us. “But keep a close eye on them, all the same.”

While she was saying that, I had climbed over the back of the seat, and pulled myself up onto the roof where I was more open and visible. “I appreciate that my kind doesn’t have the best reputation at the moment,” I said, hoping the openness might defuse some of the tension, “but we came here looking for you because there are events underway that you need to know about.”

There was a tension in Hail Burst’s jaw, the only part of her face I could actually see. Despite that, she replied evenly. “What kind of events?”

“There’s an army gathering,” I said. “The ponies of the Wasteland are preparing to hit Serenity. We’ve got one chance to stop Serenity before it’s too late for hundreds, if not thousands, of people. We’ve met you before, so they sent us to see if we could convince you to join the fight.”

She frowned.

It was the guard, Blueberry, who spoke up. “What do you mean, an army?”

“Trotsen mobilized every vehicle they have. They’ve got a few hundred soldiers, dozens of motorwagons, and even a tank. Right now, they’re making their way to Mareford, which has the best fighting force in this part of the Wasteland and is the largest producer of weapons and ammunition. We’re also reaching out to any others who are willing to join the fight. Every extra person we can get pushes the odds a little more in our favor, and we’re only going to get one shot at this.”

There was a moment of silence. Hail Storm stood there, as if thinking hard on what I had said. Blueberry gave her a critical look. Behind them, a few more ponies were looking on from porches or storefronts.

Then Blueberry turned back to me. “Fuck it. I’ll go.”

Hail Storm’s head whipped around to look at him.

I opened my mouth, about to say that it wasn’t necessary, but I realized just how hypocritical that would be. Instead, I nodded. “I appreciate it.”

Some of the onlookers were approaching, and a couple of the other Gemstone guards were trotting up to Blueberry. “What’s going on?”

“They’re gathering an army,” Blueberry replied. “Taking on the group that wiped out Rust.”

As they fell into a hushed conversation, Hail Storm watched, her expression difficult to read behind those amber eye lenses. Finally, she turned to me, her tone a bit softer than it had been. “We should speak with Commander Aurora.”

The pegasus guard, Snowfall, stepped up. “Commander—”

He fell silent as she held up a hoof. She lowered it again, looking to me. “Come with me.”

I hopped down from the wagon, with Echo landing beside me. From behind the wheel, Starlight called out, “I’m going to park the wagon, then I’ll join you!”

I gave her a nod, then turned to follow Hail Burst to Emerald’s store.

Not Emerald’s store. Not any more. I hesitated a moment at the thought, then huffed a deep breath and pushed on.

I felt like an intruder as I stepped into the store. It was as if it had somehow become some alien place, even though almost everything was just as I remembered it. Only one thing had changed: Emerald was gone. A different pony was behind the counter.

Dazzle was slumped across the counter, head resting on her forelegs, and lifting wearily as we entered. There were the faintest of bags forming under her eyes, hinting at fatigue, and her well-groomed mane had just a couple of hairs sticking out of place. For anypony else, it wouldn’t have looked unusual. For Dazzle, it looked like she was completely run-down.

Despite that, her expression slowly brightened as she recognized me. “Hello again,” she said, her voice soft. It was friendly, if not enthusiastic; the events surrounding our last meeting still hung over us. “Wasn’t sure if you’d be coming back.”

Hail Burst snorted. “Who says ‘she’ has? This is a changeling.”

I winced, then gave Hail Burst a pointed look. “The same changeling you had no problem with just a few days ago.”

“Things change,” Hail Burst said.

“Wait,” Dazzle said, looking between us in confusion and perhaps a touch of alarm. Her eyes settled on me. “You’re a changeling?”

I sighed. At this rate, the entire Wasteland would know before nightfall. “Yes,” I said. “I always was, and—”

Her eyes suddenly widened, ears perking high, and she pointed an accusing hoof at me. “That’s why your coat and mane were so immaculate! You… you… cheater!”

“I’m sorry, I—”

My mouth snapped shut as she started laughing, her hoof returning to the counter. “Holy crap,” she said, and I stared in momentary confusion at her broad grin. “Okay. I’ve got to admit, I’m a little envious!”

I’m not used to stumbling over my words, but after a few aborted attempts at a reply, all I managed was, “Oh.”

She gave another laugh. “Oh, goddesses, that would be the best thing ever. So you can really look like anything you want? Like, not just cosmetic changes, but anything?”

“Uh…” I glanced at Hail Burst, who was frowning again. I looked back to Dazzle’s excited grin. “...More or less. Bigger changes take more out of me, but anything pony-sized is fairly easy.”

Hail Burst coughed. “Yes, well, that’s all great, but you’re going to have to wait on… whatever this is. Our little changeling friend here is going upstairs to talk with Commander Aurora.”

“Oh,” Dazzle said with a subtle wince, her smile halving in intensity. “I hope we can catch up afterwards?”

I hesitated, still a little surprised by her reaction, but after a moment I relaxed, smiling back. “I’d like that.”

We parted as I followed Hail Burst up the stairs. Her armored tail flicked faintly, an agitated expression. Her behavior was clear enough to me; she was not at all pleased with how amiable my encounter with Dazzle had been. Given how bluntly she had outed me, I imagine she had hoped it to sour any existing relationship, instead of being a new source of interest. Between everything I had seen and heard, the conclusion was increasingly obvious: they had encountered Serenity, and that encounter had gone poorly.

It wasn’t until I saw Commander Aurora that I knew just how poorly it had gone.

I hadn’t heard a reply when Hail Burst knocked, and when I followed her in, I saw why. Commander Aurora wasn’t in her armor. Instead, she was in a bed, slowly and agonizingly pushing herself up to a sitting position with her remaining foreleg. There was no sign of the other leg, only a thorough canvas of bandages wrapped around her chest, covering the misshapen place where the shoulder should have been. I couldn’t tell if her wing was hidden under those bandages, but from the contours of her body, I suspected it was missing as well. More bandages wrapped around her neck and up to her face, even over her right eye. Glimpses of badly burnt and partially healed flesh showed at the edges of the cloth.

She wheezed slow, ragged breaths as she finished sitting, and turned to look at me with her one good eye. Despite the tremendous pain I’m sure she must have been in, her eye was hard and unflinching.

When she spoke, it was in short fragments, and her voice was wholly changed; the hints of scratchiness had become raspy, gravelly tones that almost overtook the words themselves. “If I thought… you had anything… to do with what happened…” She paused, taking a few more rasping breaths before continuing. “I’d have you taken out back… and shot.”

It was simultaneously concerning and reassuring.

“I hope it doesn’t come across as making light of the situation,” I carefully replied, “but I’m glad you’re not doing that.”

“I’m not… stupid…”

She abruptly broke out into rough coughing, her body shaking with its violence. She almost fell over as she fumbled for a glass of water on a stand beside her bed, and Hail Burst trotted over to help her.

While they were occupied, I glanced around the room. It was furnished nicely enough, particularly given how everything had to be scavenged. There were some maps and other papers on one of the tables, as well as a terminal. The other table held an array of medical supplies, and soiled bandages filled a small trashcan beside it. There were even two empty potion bottles set in front of a large trauma kit; Aurora had likely been given at least two healing potions while here, and who knows how many before arriving in Gemstone, and was still in such bad shape.

There was a quiet murmur as Aurora waved off Hail Burst, her eye meeting me again. Her voice was a little clearer. “The supply team didn’t expect us. We caught them by surprise. No warning.” She paused for another short coughing fit, but it passed easily. “Their response force chased scouts. Hunted for us. They didn’t come straight for our camp. It gave us time… so either they wasted an opportunity to wipe us out… just to make it look like you didn’t tell them anything… or you didn’t tell them anything.”

I just nodded. There was little I could add.

“Which doesn’t mean you aren’t trying to play us,” she rasped. “Just that you aren’t doing it for Serenity.” Her head turned, as if signifying the end of the conversation, and she faced Hail Burst. “Why did you bring her here?”

Hail Burst cleared her throat. “Because she brought some information and a… proposal… and I thought you should make the call on what we do about it.”

Aurora sighed slightly, the sound grating and unpleasant. “You’re the acting commander… that means you—”

“With all due respect,” Hail Burst said, her voice firm, “this is significantly bigger than organizing camp defenses and sending out a few patrols while you recover.”

There was a long pause as Aurora stared back at her, but finally, reluctantly, she looked back to me. “Okay... What is it?”

“We’re gathering an army,” I said, and gave her a brief overview of the forces involved. Once I had laid out the situation, I added, “And we could use your help. I can see that things haven’t gone well for you, but I imagine this has also shown just how dangerous Serenity can be when you’re on your own. This fight is inevitable. They’re going to come after us until there are no more threats to them. The one choice we have is whether we face it together or all alone.”

Aurora had broken her hard stare, looking down with a more thoughtful expression, and eventually followed up with a slow shake of her head. “We’re not a fighting force any more,” she rasped. “When those changelings caught up with us, there must have been more than a hundred of them. We took more than fifty percent casualties. Eight confirmed dead, twelve missing. Many of the wounded will never recover. We lost Lifeline and most of the medical supplies. We have barely enough hooves to man the walls and do local patrols.”

“Mareford has doctors and supplies that could tend to your wounded,” I offered, hoping I remembered correctly. “And they have a much more defensible position, with a large fighting force. I’m sure they’ll be willing to help you if you’re willing to help them. Your wounded get the best treatment available in the Wasteland, while your able-bodied soldiers get the help of an entire army to strike back at the people who attacked you and killed their comrades. An army that can help you take back the Cumulonimbus before Serenity can turn it on the settlements around here.”

Her eye looked up again, fixing me with a hard stare, as if she could see the juicy carrot I was dangling in front of her. Still, she remained silent for a few moments as she mulled it over. Her reply was a change of tactics. “And why are you so interested in getting us into the fight?”

“I’m interested in getting everyone into the fight,” I said. “Heck, one of the guards here already volunteered to join in when he overheard us.” I raised a hoof, gesturing to Aurora. “As for your group, specifically, I may not be all that versed in tactics, but I’ve been in enough fights to appreciate the value of a hard-hitting force to break the odds. You’re a group of trained soldiers in heavy armor, carrying heavy firepower, and with excellent mobility. We’ve got an army to engage Serenity’s forces on even terms, but the more mobile and aggressive forces we have, the better we’re able to hit them where we want, when we want. Your ponies could be the difference between victory or defeat, and the stakes are far too high for all of us to not push things as heavily in our favor as we can arrange.”

She watched me warily, even as she carefully considered what I said. “Could be,” she rasped, giving a little not, but then added, “but it could also be that your army doesn’t stand a chance, and my ponies are better off withdrawing. Once our war is done, then we can come back and deal with them properly.”

“After hundreds or thousands of ponies have died!” I said, and quickly softened my tone again. “At least come to Mareford. See the people who are gathering to fight. You can judge for yourself whether they have any chance of pulling this off, but at least meet with them.”

Another long pause. “I have eighteen wounded soldiers. Will Mareford have the capacity to care for them?”

“Yes,” I said; even if they didn’t have enough medical facilities, I’m sure something could be arranged. “They’re a much larger settlement than Gemstone.”

She grunted weakly, followed by a few suppressed coughs. It took her a moment to recover and speak again. “And what if these changelings move into Gemstone when we leave?”

I frowned, alarmed at the possibility, but I quickly shook it off. “I would imagine they’d put a priority on dealing with the gathering army rather than hitting a small settlement. That said, and I hope you don’t take offense at this, but given how your previous encounter with Serenity turned out, I think it’s unlikely that your presence here would change the outcome.”

She grunted again, grimacing slightly, but the expression faded away over the next few seconds. Finally, she gave a slow nod. “Okay. We’ll meet with your army. I think we can do that little.” She turned her head to look at Hail Burst again. “Make it happen.”

Hail Burst gave a sharp nod. “Yes ma’am.” She then turned, giving a jerk of the head that made it clear I was to follow her.

We exited the room. I’d barely stepped into the hall and shut the door before Hail Burst abruptly turned to face me, muzzle close to mine. I drew to a halt, expecting some hostile gesture.

Instead, she immediately got down to business. “This army we’re meeting. When will it arrive in Mareford, and how long do we have to get there before it leaves?”

Regaining my composure, I answered. “They should be arriving sometime this evening, probably in the next few hours. As for when they set out for Serenity, I’m not sure, but they’re eager to start the attack and doubt that you’ll show up. I doubt they’ll stay any longer than necessary, which might mean setting out at first light.”

My response was met with a snort. “You sure don’t like giving a lot of time, do you? You expect us to displace all our wounded and equipment just like that?”

“Less ‘expect’, more ‘hope’,” I replied.

“Wonderful,” she dryly replied. “Go talk to your friends. I’ve got a lot of preparations to organize and a short time to do it, so the last thing I need is some changeling getting in my mane.”

She turned and walked briskly to the stairs, her mouth clenched in a tight frown.

“I’m sorry for what’s happened to you,” I said, trying to ease some of the tension. “I know you’ve had bad experiences with changelings, but I’m not your enemy. I’m trying—”

“I know,” she replied, the words coming out in a clenched-teeth growl. She looked back over her shoulder. “And for the record, this isn’t me treating you like an enemy. I shoot my enemies. This is me treating you as a bad reminder of just how hard we got fucked. So you just go hang out with your friends. Stay out of my way. Give us the time to go meet this army, get a feel for what’s going on, and let this crap…” She raised a hoof, gesturing back and forth between us. “...settle down and sort itself out, ‘cause nopony’s going to just take your word about anything right now.”

I paused, and finally nodded without saying anything else.

“Good,” she said, turned, and headed down the stairs.

I gave her a few moments to gain some distance before heading downstairs myself. When I stepped into the main room again, she was just stepping out the front door. Starlight and Dusty were at the counter, along with Dazzle and the gate guard, Blueberry. Starlight had been watching Hail Burst’s exit, and turned to me with a worried look. “What’s wrong?”

“They’ve had a hard time,” I said with a shake of my head. “But they’re going to go to Mareford, so they may be on board. I guess we’ll find out when—”

I halted; Dazzle had stepped out from behind the counter, grinning expectantly. The moment my mouth shut, she said, “Well, come on! I want to see what you look like!” Blueberry looked over with curiosity, while Starlight’s ears had perked up with alarm, looking anxiously around the gathering.

I opened my mouth to reply, but stopped and sighed. There really wasn’t any point in arguing it. I called up my magic, and after taking a moment to slip out of my cloak and saddlebags, stood before her in nothing but my chitin.

Dazzle walked up, no smiles now, just staring intensely. She moved to the side, eyes tracing over every inch of me. “That’s so weird,” she murmured before her lips twitched upwards with a hint of a smile. “You’re all glossy and shiny.”

“Thank you.”

Her eyes hesitated at my legs. “What’s with the holes?”

I shrugged. “Nothing’s really ‘with’ them. That’s just how changelings are.”

“That’s so weird,” she repeated, though she was smiling openly again. “I like it. It’s exotic!”

I could hear Starlight’s hoof meeting her face. “Oh goddesses no.”

Dazzle laughed loudly, taking a step back and raising a hoof. “Hey, relax. I’m not going to get between you two lovers. I learned my lesson.”

“We’re not lovers,” Starlight groaned.

The front door swung open, and Sickle stuck her head in, grinning beneath her muzzle. “Hey, is someone making the runt squirm without me?”

Starlight abruptly set her hoof down, glaring at Sickle. “Go away!”

“Fuck you,” Sickle said, still grinning as she entered. “Oh, wait, I forgot. That’s Whisper’s job.”

Starlight groaned. “Why are you even in here? Don’t you have anything better to do?”

“I know when I’m needed,” Sickle smugly replied. “Also, no.”

Starlight grumbled and turned away from her. “Anyway, didn’t we have some actual business to deal with?”

“You mean other than admiring your exotic marefriend?” Dazzle said with a light, teasing tone, then blinked. She turned to me, head craning a little, with a questioning look at my flanks. “Wait, are you actually a mare?”

I resisted the abrupt urge to tuck my tail in close and protective. “I am female,” I replied as evenly as possible. Dazzle just smiled, giving a little chuckle. I added, “I do have to say, it’s a nice change to have ponies react with curiosity instead of fear or revulsion.”

“Well, we try to be friendly,” Dazzle said with a shrug, and leaned against the counter. “That’s what Gemstone’s all about. You’re a good… well, not-pony, I guess, but you know what I mean. You’ve been nice and friendly, and you’ve helped us out before. What you look like isn’t going to change that, even if some other changelings are causing problems. I think Emerald taught us better than that.”

That name sucked any humor out of the conversation. Starlight looked away, and despite the difference in species, it was apparent that my own discomfort was clear. “Hey, hey,” Dazzle said, raising her forehooves. “I didn’t mean to kill the mood. I know, it hurts that she’s gone, but… look, she always tried to cheer up ponies, right? I don’t think she’d like her name making them sad.”

I swallowed. “It’s… not that.”

Starlight eyed me.

Dazzle’s expression was still restrained, but curious. “Then what?”

I just stood there, silent, while my mind raced, bouncing from one piece of information to another, weaving it together, sorting out the benefits and risks.

There is one particularly dangerous side to secrets: the damage they cause can depend heavily on how the come to light.

I took a deep breath, gave a silent apology, and spoke. “Okay. Emerald made me promise not to tell you this, but—”

“Woah, woah,” Dazzle said, raising a hoof. “If she made you promise, that’s that. She must have had good reason to—”

“She did,” I said. “But the situation’s changed, and I’m certain that if she were still here, she’d want you to know.” I hesitated before adding, “And you’re going to figure it out soon, anyway. Better you learn all of the details now instead of having to make assumptions.”

Concern had etched itself into Dazzle’s expression. “...What are you talking about?”

“Emerald was a changeling.”

Both Dazzle and Blueberry stared at me, blinking. Dazzle spoke first, and with an uncharacteristic crudeness. “Brahminshit.”

I shook my head and pushed on. “Did she ever tell you where she came from?

Dazzle stared open-mouthed at me for a few seconds before replying. “She never really talked about her past, but that doesn’t mean she was a changeling!”

“But she did talk a little about it,” I said. “She even mentioned it to us, vaguely, on one of our visits. Do you remember the name of the place she grew up at?”

“Why is that so important?” Dazzle demanded. Her body was tense.

“Please,” I said, keeping my tone gentle.

She glared silently at me for several seconds before replying. “Like I said, she didn’t really talk much about her past. Yeah, I remember her saying something about it, but… I don’t know, I can’t quite remember the name of the place. It’s just…”

“Serenity.”

Blueberry’s ears went up, his expression tightening.

“That’s the place,” Dazzle said, thumping a hoof lightly on the counter before noticing the change in Blueberry’s expression. “What?”

“That’s the group the pegasi were talking about,” he said, his eyes fixed on me. “The one that hit them so hard. The one that wiped out Rust.” A hoof came up, pointing at me. “And she was talking about leading an army there.”

“Emerald was born there,” I said. “Her hive taught that ponies were just monsters, responsible for everything wrong with the world. That the only thing you were good for was food. Then she got here, and found out that wasn’t true at all. She found out just how nice ponies could be. She couldn’t go on helping her hive hurt ponies, so she… she left.” I looked over Dazzle and Blueberry. “I don’t know if I can convey how significant that is to a changeling. To a changeling, turning away from your hive is… it’s like a pony cutting off their own cutie mark.”

Dazzle and Blueberry both winced at that imagery.

“I want to make it clear,” I said, my voice gentle. “She was still the same person you knew. She wasn’t trying to deceive you, and it tore her up that she had to keep it secret. And I know you’re going to think it, but no, it wasn’t because she didn’t trust you. I think she knew you’d understand. She didn’t tell you because it would be dangerous for you.”

Dazzle looked to me with damp eyes. “Dangerous?”

“Serenity,” I said. “At the time, they were mostly passive, hiding, but they guarded their secrecy. If they found out some ponies had information that pointed even slightly in their direction, they’d see it as a threat, and they’d be ruthless in removing it. If she told you, and Serenity ever caught word of it, they’d see every pony in Gemstone as a risk. They’d have done the same thing here that they did to Rust.”

Dazzle didn’t reply. She simply stared, her gaze lowered to the ground, as if unable to fully process everything that was said.

“That’s why she insisted on going on that job,” I said. “She knew who Amber was. She knew Amber was another agent of Serenity, and that if she slipped up in even the slightest way, she’d be discovered. She also knew that if Serenity had any reason to suspect that she told you anything, all of Gemstone would be in danger. That’s why she planned on going out and faking her own death, to keep you safe.”

“Fake?” Dazzle said, her eyes rising once more. “Is she still alive?”

That little glimmer of hope hurt. “I’m sorry. Amber must have caught on that something was up. Serenity killed her.”

She deflated ever so slightly.

“But it’s only because of Emerald that we even know Serenity is a thing.” I raised my PipBuck-clad hoof. “Because of her, we know where they are. Because of her, we were able to discover that Serenity isn’t just hiding any more. Their queen wants to put every pony under her hoof. They’ve been arming raiders and have already wiped out one settlement. We’ve turned up agents infiltrating both Trotsen and Mareford. Serenity is gearing up to make a big move, but Emerald has given us a chance to fight back.”

Dazzle slowly nodded, silent.

“These other changelings,” Blueberry said. “What happens if they aren’t stopped?”

“It wouldn’t be just taking over,” I said. “The only value they put on ponies is food. Most likely, they’ll wipe out any groups that could be a threat, like Mareford or Trotsen, as well as what’s left of my hive. They’ll probably kill most ponies and keep just enough to be harvested for love, with a small breeding population, all kept under heavy guard.”

Dazzle’s expression had turned uneasy. “What do you mean, harvested?”

“Changelings feed on love,” I said. “Serenity has dozens of ponies held prisoner in suspended animation, and they drain them of love to feed the hive.”

The look of unease grew, with a touch of fear. “That’s how you guys feed?”

“That’s how they feed,” I replied sharply, eyes narrowing for a moment before I relaxed again. “My hive survives by making friends, to earn willing affection, even if we can’t always be open about it.”

I might have gone on, but Blueberry had abruptly turned and walked off toward the door, his expression grim. I might have said more to him, but Dazzle asked how the whole love-feeding thing worked, so I settled in to give her a brief answer. That led into discussing Queen Chrysalis the Sixth and the Serenity hive, and the differences between those and my own queen and hive, which of course necessitated explaining more details of our history.

And yes, there was certainly a large part of me that was anxious about sharing so much information. At the same time, there was something almost cathartic about it. It was almost like unloading, like a weight had been lifted, if only temporarily. It also seemed to help Dazzle. She started out tense and uneasy, but steadily relaxed until she sat beside me, fascinated by this new and unknown subject.

We must have talked for half an hour. It finally came to an end when several Enclave Loyalists entered, bearing a stretcher, with Hail Burst in the lead. She approached me. The rest continued on to the stairs, though their helmets turned to track me, expressions unreadable behind the amber lenses.

“We’re about ready to go,” Hail Burst said as she came to a halt. “We’re loading the last of the wounded right now. Dust-off is in ten minutes.”

I stood. “I guess we should get ready to go.”

“Right,” Dazzle said, quickly rising to her hooves. While she trotted to the back of the store, I called up my magic, restoring my disguise. Hail Burst’s frown tightened slightly, but she said nothing, simply turning to leave.

“Wait!” Starlight said, and Hail Burst looked back at her. “What about Singe? Is she okay?”

“The civilian?” Hail Burst asked. “She’s stable. We’ve already loaded her up.”

Starlight relaxed, smiling at the good news. “Thank you.”

Hail Burst nodded, turned, and left.

Dusty spoke for the first time since I came downstairs. “Let’s get back to the wagon,” he said. “Where’d you park?”

We followed Starlight out the back door of the store, and I almost ran into her back as she abruptly halted.

Some forty ponies had gathered there. Some were guards clad in varying degrees of heavy armor. Others wore lighter barding, or even none at all. Almost all were armed with the Wasteland-made energy weapons Gemstone was known for. Arclight was there, too, with a small wagon of his goods, and was in the midst of passing out his creations to the few ponies not already armed.

Echo sat in the back of the wagon, warily watching all the ponies gathered around her.

I saw Blueberry near the front of the pack, and still grim-faced as he helped tighten the straps of another pony’s armor. At the sight of our appearance, he turned to face us.

Starlight, being in front of us, spoke first. “Uh, what’s going on?”

“We’re all going, too,” Blueberry said, backed by several sounds of affirmation from the ponies around him.

I have to admit, I was a little concerned. These were just regular ponies. Good ponies, certainly, but not soldiers. Some were part-time guards, but most weren’t even that. Given Dusty’s glance my way, eyebrow raised, he was thinking the same thing.

I stepped around Starlight. “I don’t want to turn away anyone who wants to help, but are you sure you know what you’re getting into?”

“We know,” Blueberry said, while a few other ponies nodded along. “Hell, we saw what they did to these pegasi when they arrived.”

“It’s going to be even worse than that,” I said. “This isn’t going to be like fighting raiders, even if it was the biggest band of raiders to ever exist. The changeling hive we’re going to be facing has professional soldiers with extensive training and the best equipment available, and that’s the least scary thing about them.” I looked around, wondering how far the word of my nature had spread. After a moment, I decided it didn’t really matter anymore. “I may not know all that much about combat tactics, but I do know changeling infiltration tactics. We can expect anything from impersonating friendly or neutral forces, or embedded Infiltrators passing on information, or even replacing or assassinating leadership, and chances are good we won’t even know it’s happening until ponies start dying.”

There were a few looks of concern among the crowd. I could see Blueberry considering what I said, but his look of grim determination returned a moment later. “We all know it’s going to be bad, but that’s why we’re going. Hell, I had friends in Rust, and now we find out they’re the ones that killed Emerald? People like that need to be stopped. But then you say they’re holding a bunch of ponies hostage? Yeah, I ain’t going to sit around all safe and pretty when I could be helping. Far as I see it, it can’t be any worse for us than it already is for them.”

I hesitated, looking over the group of ponies. “Like I said, I’m not going to turn away any pony that could help, but… but the world is already short enough on good ponies.”

“It’ll be a lot shorter on ‘em if we weren’t willing to help,” Blueberry said. “Emerald was right about that. Gemstone isn’t just hollow talk from behind a wall of turrets. We’re about doing what’s right, even if it costs us, because that’s what the Wasteland needs.”

There were murmurs of agreement as looks of unease faded. Some of the ponies stood a little taller, a few smiles starting to overtake grim expressions.

The door behind me thudded open, immediately followed by Dazzle’s voice. “Okay, I grabbed all the—woah…”

I looked back. She had donned her heavy barding, and had slung two bulging and hastily packed saddlebags across her back, while her magical energy rifle hung from its sling around her neck. The look of surprise on her face lasted only a moment before melting into a pleased smile. “...Well, all right. We’re all going?”

Several ponies called out in the affirmative, and her smile grew as she approached the rest of the group. She only paused when she saw Arclight. “You too?”

He looked up from the wagon of weapons. “Somepony’s got to maintain the weapons and do repairs. I’ll be more useful with you ponies than I will sitting in my workshop.”

“Well we’ll be glad to have you along,” she replied.

Dusty and I exchanged glances before he stepped forward. “Okay, I’m not going to complain about having a few more hooves, but we’re on a tight time-table. We need to get to Mareford as quickly as possible, and we don’t have enough room to carry everypony.”

“The pegasi have sky-wagons!” some pony in the crowd called out.

“They have two,” Dazzle said, “and they’re probably full-up with wounded.” She then gestured to our motorwagon. “How much can that pull? Can it pull a wagon?”

Dusty frowned. “Our motorwagon’s up to it, but I wouldn’t trust a normal wagon to hold up to that kind of speed.”

It was Arclight who spoke up next. “We’ve got a couple of wagons that should be up to the trip. They wouldn’t hold up to full-speed driving, probably, but they’ll hold up to a modest pace so long as we stay to the old caravan road.”

Dusty considered that for a moment, clearly still having some concerns, but finally nodded. “Okay, but it’ll have to be quick. The Loyalists are taking off in about five minutes. Echo, Starlight, could you help them?”

“Should be easy enough,” Starlight said, already trotting towards the motorwagon. “We still have the rig we welded on to tow the other motorwagon, shouldn’t take much to modify it.”

What followed was a frantic scramble. Dusty and I helped load a few ponies and their supplies into our motorwagon, giving up our own seats to join Sickle in the cargo bed. Six ponies crammed into the cab. Dazzle climbed up to sit straddled across the side-armor of the cargo bay, and a few other ponies followed her example, clinging to the vehicle. Our wagon sagged once more under the load of ponies.

Behind us, a pair of wagons were brought in, one of which already carried two of the gate’s magical energy cannons. Echo and Starlight got to work hooking them up end-to-end, cutting, welding, and just plain hammering scrap metal parts to serve their purposes, all with impressive haste. Echo’s magic, particularly the ability to levitate several hundred pounds and hold it steady, seemed to help a lot.

They had just finished getting the wagons connected when a Loyalist soldier swooped in, backwinging to come to a hover beside us. “We’re lifting now. Hail Burst wants to know if you’re setting out now, or if we’re meeting in Mareford.”

“We’re ready to move,” Dusty replied. “We won’t be making the best of time, but we should still make Mareford by nightfall. If she wants to travel together for mutual security, we’d certainly appreciate it.”

“I’ll let her know,” the soldier replied, and zipped off.

Dusty gave one last look back at the pair of wagons behind us, linked end-to-end and packed with ponies, then turned to rap a hoof against the roof of the wagon’s cab. “Okay, Starlight. Take us out.”

The motor hummed, dirt crunching softly under the tires as we started to roll. New squeaks and groans joined the usual soft cacophony of sounds, and as we built up to the speed of a brisk trot, the wagons behind us rattled along.

We wound our way out from behind the store and toward the town gate. The heavy gate itself was already open, and several of the town’s ponies were gathered on either side or atop the walls. Ponies called out cheerfully, waving to each other, though I caught an undercurrent of worry in the occasional damp eye or wavering smile.

As we rolled through the gate, I looked back at the trailing wagons and their cargo. The ponies there waved back happily to the ponies they were leaving behind. Their grins were sure and proud. They were good ponies, following me in the hopes that they could do the right thing and help others who couldn’t help themselves.

I only hoped I wasn’t leading them to their deaths.

☢

It was dark when we rolled up to Mareford.

The old dirt road was level enough to make decent speed without destroying the towed wagons, though it had been a rough ride for the passengers. Several times, the ponies in the wagons had started looking distinctly miserable. Each time, some pony made a comment we couldn’t make out, and was answered by laughs and grins. Despite the unpleasant ride, it seemed their spirits were high.

The Loyalists descended as we neared our destination, flying alongside us at a relaxed pace, with the two military sky-wagons trailing at the rear. I’m not sure if they counted as sky-tanks when they didn’t carry weapons, but they were still armored flying vehicles. I’d noticed Dusty looking at them several times during our trip, no doubt contemplating ways to make use of such hardware.

Lights danced and flickered from campfires set outside the gate, illuminating the Trotsen motorwagons and the ponies milling around them. The Gemstone ponies started murmuring amongst each other, craning to get a good look as we slowly drew closer. The Loyalists, in turn, drew back at Hail Burst’s barked order, and formed into neat columns behind us.

Sandstorm’s ‘Beast’ was easy to find, still at the head of the pack, its cannon pointed squarely at the gate. Under Dusty’s direction, Starlight drove us up to the tank, and with a slow, rattling groan, our wagons finally came to a halt.

It was Axle who popped up from the tank at Dusty’s call. He stared out at us for a second before snorting. “Didn’t think you’d actually make it,” he said, casting a glance back at the Loyalist forces, who had landed neatly behind us.

“We told you we’d be here,” Dusty replied evenly. “Is Sandstorm up?”

“Yeah,” Axle said, pointing off to the gate. “She’s still in town, talking with their mayor.”

“Guess we’d better get in there, too,” Dusty said.

Starlight stuck her head out the window, twisting to look back at us. “Uh, Dusty, you sure that’s a good—”

“It’s fine,” Dusty quickly said, cutting her off, and ignoring the questioning look Starlight gave him. Instead, he turned to address Hail Burst. “You should probably make introductions, too.”

“Of course,” she replied, her head turning to look at the gathered Trotsen force before looking back to Dusty. “Will Mareford be making accommodations for my ponies, or will we be camping outside of the walls?”

Dusty shrugged. “I suppose that depends on how our meeting goes.”

“I see.” Hail Burst turned and called out. “Cyclone! You’re in charge while I’m gone. Get everypony settled in case we’re staying in the field, and set pickets. Downdraft, you’re with me.”

Dazzle nudged Dusty’s shoulder. “Should we stay out here, too?”

“You should make your introductions, too,” he replied. “Besides, they better not be turning away Gemstone ponies at the gate. We can at least get all of you some decent beds for the night.”

“Sounds good to me,” Dazzle replied with a smile.

The motor hummed again as we slowly rattled our way up to the gate, with Hail Burst and Downdraft hovering alongside us, all under the eyes of the guards at the gate.

There must have been at least twenty militia gathered atop the walls and by the gate itself, many half-hidden in the shadows. Rifles were slung in easy reach. Light machine guns rested atop the walls, ready to pour out a hail of fire. In the recesses of the half-collapsed upper floor of some office building, the firelight flickered in a lens, the shadows almost entirely concealing the barrel of a monstrous rifle.

Three ponies stood by the gate itself, clad in the sandy-brown barding of the Mareford Militia. The two flanking the gate gripped the bits of their rifles, holding them ready, while the third stood her ground in the middle of the path, her own rifle slung across her chest. As we drew closer, she held up a hoof. “Hold up there!”

We ground to a halt once more, and she set her hoof down again. “We told you, you’ll have to wait until the mayor is done talking with your boss. Until then, you’re staying outside.”

Dusty placed his forehooves on the roof and pulled himself up so he could be seen. “Hey, Rose. We’re not Trotsen. We’re bringing in representatives from Gemstone and the Enclave Loyalists. They’re looking to join the fight.”

“The fight? What—” The mare halted, blinking as she peered out in the dim light. Her voice sounded a little strained as she spoke again. “Dusty Trails?”

His tail flicked beside me. Even when faced with destruction, it seemed we were still wanted. “Yeah, it’s me.”

There was a moment of silence. Dusty didn’t elaborate further, while I wondered if it was the wise choice or a missed opportunity to explain his position. The guard mare, Rose, stood silently for a moment, obviously thinking over the situation. Finally, she took a slow step back and to the side; the adrenaline spiked as I noted it was a move entirely consistent with getting out of the line of fire, until she spoke. “Maybe you’d better come in, then. I think Mayor Hardwood’s going to want to talk with you.”

Dusty’s expression immediately brightened. “Hardwood’s mayor again?”

“He is,” she replied, raising a hoof and giving a circular motion. A moment later, the gate groaned and creaked open. “I don’t know if he’ll be so happy to see you, but I expect he wants an explanation. And Dusty? You and yours better be on your best behavior, understand?”

“Of course,” Dusty replied, nodding. I resisted the urge to look questioningly at Sickle. She’d just see it as encouragement.

We were waved through the gate. On the other side, a squad of militia ponies waited to escort us through town. I couldn’t blame them for the show of caution, considering we were supposedly wanted ponies with several dozen armed ponies following us, but it didn’t make me feel any more comfortable about the situation.

Even restricted to a walking pace, it took only a couple of minutes to arrive at the town hall. I was pleased to see it was apparently intact, with no signs of fire damage.

Sandstorm was coming out as we pulled up. She was frowning. Not a great sign.

The motorwagon came to a halt, and we dismounted, several dozen ponies climbing down and stretching their legs. I hopped down from the wagon and slipped past the other ponies to approach her. “How’d it go in there?”

She snorted, continuing to walk right past me. “Fucker likes to talk as much as you do.”

I followed along. “Did he agree to help?”

Her tail flicked in irritation. “Only thing he decided was that it was getting late, and we should talk more in the morning.”

“And will you?”

“Fuck off,” she grumbled, pointedly not looking my way, but following up with, “Yeah, I’ll be there.”

I came to a halt, letting her walk off on her own, and turned to rejoin the rest of my group. A pair of soldiers parted from the others to head inside. Dusty informed me that they had asked us to stay put while they went to see if the mayor would see us.

Echo landed unannounced, drawing several startled reactions from both the Gemstone ponies and the militia soldiers, and neatly tucked her wings in at her side and stood calm and proud, as if nothing was unusual about her abrupt appearance. “Do you suppose they will try to kill us?” she casually asked.

“Hah!” was Sickle’s immediate reply as she hopped down from the motorwagon with a solid thump and rattle of armor. “I’d like to see ‘em try. Seriously. I could use a good fight.”

“Settle down,” Dusty said, earning a crude gesture from Sickle.

I heard the soft clomping of Hail Burst’s power armor behind me, and turned to see her frown. “I take it there’s a problem with your little army?”

“No problem, just a delay,” I said, hoping it was true. “It’s a bit late for a big meeting.”

She gave a quiet snort. “It’s a waste of time. It isn’t like our enemies just stop as soon as night falls.”

“He’s a mayor,” I said, “not a general. I imagine he’s used to a more civilian schedule.”

“Hopefully whoever leads the ‘soldiers’ around here is a little more disciplined.”

“They are,” Dusty replied.

It was a couple of minutes before the soldiers returned. The stallion leading them approached us and spoke up clearly for everyone to hear. “Dusty Trails. Hardwood will see you and your companions. As for the rest of you, there will be a meeting in the morning at oh-eight-hundred—eight o’clock—to discuss possible arrangements. Until then: Gemstone ponies, that building across the way—” He lifted a hoof to point to an old and mostly-intact apartment building. “—serves as a shelter and inn. There should be enough room for all of you. As for the rest, we have to ask that all military forces remain outside of the city until an agreement has been reached.”

“Wonderful,” Hail Burst grumbled, while the Gemstone ponies started unloading their gear.

Starlight called out to the soldiers. “Uh, can you guys watch over our wagon while we’re in there? We don’t want anypony stealing it.”

The soldier in charge eyed her, but said, “Yeah, we’ll keep an eye on it.”

We parted ways. Hail Burst and Downdraft took off to return to their camp, while Dazzle and the other Gemstone ponies made their way to their accommodations. As for Dusty and the rest of us, we entered the impressive town hall building, escorted by a squad of soldiers.

I would say it seemed excessive, but the barrel of Sickle’s heavy machine gun was bobbing right next to my head as we walked, and a living pseudo-goddess followed close on my flanks. If anything, it was insufficient.

I hoped these soldiers hadn’t come to the same conclusion. It would be an unnerving recognition, and fearful ponies are dangerous ponies.

There were some distinctly uncomfortable looks from the few ponies in the lobby as we entered. They certainly had good reason to be concerned. It was distinctly unusual, enough that I had to consider the implications. If they considered us a threat, allowing us all to enter a room with their mayor would be a significant risk. Either they were making a risky decision, or one of those two conditions weren’t true.

Which meant either that they were leading us somewhere else, or whoever was in charge didn’t think we were a risk.

So it was just a little reassuring when they led us up the stairs and down the hall to the same office I remembered from my previous visits.

What was much less reassuring was the signs of recent repairs: small patches of plaster on the walls, consistent with patched bullet holes, fresh chips and gouges in the banister, and a few places where no amount of cleaning had been able to remove the bloodstains.

A new pony sat behind the large desk where I had once seen Big Gun. He was just as old, though a bit rounder and softer in appearance. He sat back in his chair as we entered, eying us carefully, though his expression struck me as less critical, more concerned.

Dusty naturally took a place at the front of us, giving a deferential nod to the mayor. “Hardwood.”

“Dusty,” Hardwood replied, his voice soft and tired. He remained silent for a couple of seconds before sighing, slowly leaning forward to rest his forelegs on his desk. “Been a lot of strange stories turning up, lately. If you’d shown up a month ago, you’d be telling me your story in cuffs. But now… ever since Gun died, things have been turned upside down. Ponies keep turning up more shady shit he might have been involved in, Silverline’s been up in arms about him murdering her husband and how you were framed, hell, I’ve got a herd of zebras that showed up out of nowhere singing your praises. Then we’ve got Militia soldiers trying to stage a coup—” Dusty’s ears perked in alarm. “—Gun’s mercs turning bandit, all this nonsense about these so-called ‘changelings’. Now you show up in the middle of it all, and…” He drew to a halt, silent for a moment before slowly shaking his head. “Hell. What’s going on, Dusty? What happened to you? I knew you. You were a Ranger. I have a hard time buying that you’d turn on your own, but we had a bunch of dead ponies and no answers. Just for once, I want a simple, no brahminshit story.”

“Simple story?” Dusty said. “Okay. I didn’t turn on them. They turned on us. They set an ambush for us, tried to kill us, all on Big Gun’s orders. He’s the one that set those raiders on the water caravan, and we knew. He wanted to silence us for good.”

Hardwood was slowly shaking his head, only to be interrupted at the soft thump of a small notebook landing atop his desk. Both he and Dusty looked back to me as I rebuckled the flap of my saddlebag. “The notebook belonged to a raider boss named Gutrip,” I said. “He’s the one who led the attack on the caravan, and took Silverline and Quicksilver. Check the last page. They were told exactly where the caravan would be, and more significantly, that the guards would leave them unprotected there.”

Hardwood reached out, taking the dingy notebook, and slowly flipped through the pages until he reached the end. He stared at it long and hard, without visible reaction, before finally giving a slow, long sigh and setting it down. “I heard some traders saying the same thing. Hell, I wanted to believe you, but it just seemed so absurd to believe that some of the Militia—some of the Rangers, even!—would be involved in something so… so…” He raised a hoof, giving a weak gesture as he tried to come up with the right word, and finally gave up. “Then some of the Militia officers, ponies I’d known for years, tried to take over.”

Dusty stepped in close to the desk. “What happened?”

“The day after Big Gun and Wild Runner were murdered, it was chaos. Ponies were scared, and even more so when they looked through some of Big Gun’s records. Some of the staff asked me to come in and help out, just to reassure ponies until we figured out what happened and had a new mayor elected.” He shook his head again. “I was here when some Rangers and Big Gun’s mercs came in, said they were taking charge until things settled down. We all said we had it handled, and then they tried to arrest us all, saying we’d murdered Gun and Runner. Guess they must have expected the rest of the Militia to go along with it, but the ponies standing guard there refused. Next thing I know, everyone’s shooting.

“I spent four hours, bleeding from the leg, while Rambler held me and the others at gunpoint. Rambler! I shared drinks with him every month! I’d been friends with his wife since we could hardly walk! I’d helped take care of his kids! And he was holding a gun on me, ready to kill me like he’d killed Marionberry.” He was trembling faintly, and he took a moment to draw a deep breath, calming down.

Dusty’s ears flicked back. “They killed ponies?”

“Some,” Hardwood said, his voice quiet. “She tried to run when they herded us into the office. Only one of the soldiers guarding the place lived, and she lost a hoof. A Ranger died when they stormed the place, too.” He gave a quiet sigh. “It was a bad day.”

Dusty murmured something quietly, slowly shaking his head.

Hardwood looked up again. “So they turned on you?”

“They did.”

Hardwood stared for a moment before slowly nodding. His eyes slowly drifted away, looking over the rest of us. “Interesting company you keep these days.”

“It’s been an interesting couple of months,” Dusty replied. “You know why we’re here.”

“Yes,” Hardwood said with a tired sigh. “The supposed ‘changelings’.”

“There’s nothing supposed about them,” Dusty said. “I’ve seen them.”

Hardwood raised an eyebrow. “You have?”

“Yes, sir.”

Another short pause. “And how bad is it?”

“To be blunt? They scare the shit out of me.”

Hardwood fell silent again, thinking for a good while before finally shaking his head once more. “This whole thing is a mess. Has been for months.” He slowly slipped out of his chair, walking around the desk with a pronounced limp. He came to a halt in front of Dusty, and raised a hoof.

Dusty lifted his own hoof, and they shook.

“I never really bought what they said,” Hardwood said. “I know some called you a traitor for leaving, but I know why you left, and it just doesn’t jive with you being some murderer. I knew there had to be more to it.” He lowered his hoof again, looking past Dusty to one of the nearby soldiers. “They’re free to go.”

The soldier nodded.

“Thank you,” Dusty said, and Hardwood gave a weak smile, nodding in reply.

“I get the feeling it’s going to be more chaos heaped on all the crap we’ve already got, but it’s good to see you again, Dusty. I… also want to hear all the details of what happened. There’s still a lot of unanswered questions.” He groaned slightly as he leaned against the table, taking some weight off one of his rear legs. “But that can wait for tomorrow. It’s too late to be getting into all of that.”

“Of course,” Dusty said, offering a smile. “We’ll talk in the morning?”

“If I have any time with all the other talking I’m going to be doing,” Hardwood said, weakly mirroring the smile, though it quickly faded.

“Well, we’ll get out of your mane, then. Goodnight, Hardwood.”

Hardwood nodded, and Dusty turned, heading for the door. We followed, while the soldiers slowly dispersed as word was passed, casting only a couple of wary glances our way. The four watching over our motorwagon were a bit more wary, but another soldier came trotting up, passing on the news, and they let us pass.

Starlight parked the motorwagon beside the makeshift inn, and we made our way in. Dusty handled getting the rooms, but was otherwise tight-lipped.

He remained so until we had gone upstairs to a vacant common room, with the doors into our rooms, and well away from any prying ears.

“A coup,” Dusty said as we came to a halt by one of the room's doors. “Shit like that’s exactly what I was worried would happen if Big Gun was killed. A bunch of ponies died because of it.”

I gave a quiet sigh. “I know.”

“Yeah, you know,” he grumbled.

“I know it’s not always the most persuasive of arguments,” I said, “but it’s likely it saved far more ponies.”

He snorted irritably.

“I don’t like what happened, either,” I said, stepping forward to look him a little more squarely in the face. “I don’t like people dying as a result of my actions, but I still think we made the right call in a difficult situation.”

“Oh, shut up,” he grumbled. “I don’t care. Fuck, I’m not even disagreeing with you. I’m just pissed.” He waved a hoof off to the side. “That’s your room.” Then he walked across the common room to another door.

I frowned, contemplating whether I should say more, but decided against it. These events were a little close to home for him, even in a more literal sense. I figured he could use some time alone.

Though with the way Sickle followed him, I doubt she intended to give him that opportunity.

Instead, I turned, entering the room Starlight and I would share for the night.

☢

I woke at exactly six, having made use of the PipBuck’s alarm-clock function for the first time since I had acquired it.

I stretched, rose, and took care of the usual morning prep. Dusty was waiting in the common room, with a couple plates loaded with cooked antique boxed mush. He gave a little nod to us and gestured to the plate he wasn’t eating from, which seemed to say to me that he didn’t particularly want to talk, but wasn’t holding a grudge.

We settled in to our mediocre breakfast, joined several minutes later by a very lethargic and possibly hungover Sickle. She flopped noisily onto a couch that was a little too small for her, and sprawled out on her back with a quiet groan.

When he finished eating, Dusty started bringing out all his weapons, unloading and stripping them down. “There’s going to be fighting, soon,” he said quietly, not looking up from his rifle as he removed the bolt. “You should tend to your weapons. You too, Sickle.”

She grumbled something unintelligible, and didn’t budge.

As for myself, I agreed with Dusty, and started pulling out my own weapons.

Starlight sat beside me. “Guess I should maintain my weapons, too.” She then sat there silently for a second. “Oh, look, I’m done.”

Dusty snorted softly. “Magical energy weapons need maintenance, too.”

“Sure,” Starlight said. “Keep the dirt out of the case, make sure things don’t get knocked out of alignment, maybe clean the lens. It takes a couple of seconds, tops.”

“Well, if you’re not cleaning your weapons, how about you help Echo looking over the motorwagon. We drove it pretty hard, I’d rather not have it break down to something we could catch early.”

Starlight’s expression brightened. “Okay, that sounds more like it.” She quickly snatched up her saddlebags. “Don’t take too long!” she called out as she trotted off down the stairs.

“Guess that answers where Echo is,” I said as I opened up my rifle, while hoping the offer of casual conversation might break the ice.

To my relief, Dusty took the offered gesture. “She’s been anxious about it being left alone,” he said, though his attention was focused on the bolt of his rifle. “Something about all that advanced pre-war tech just lying out there in the open.”

“I suppose that makes sense,” I said, then paused as a thought occurred to me. “Shouldn’t that be wartime tech, though?”

Dusty looked up, blinking in surprise as he thought on that. “Huh. Everypony says pre-war, but I guess most of this stuff isn’t from before the war. Never really thought of it before. I wonder why that is.”

“I guess because it’s less of a mouthful than ‘pre-megaspell-apocalypse’,” I offered, and he snorted in amusement.

He fell into silence again, but I was satisfied that things were good between us. Being an experienced soldier, I imagine he might be familiar with the idea of even good decisions having hard costs. I know the idea of a commander making a decision that will kill some of his soldiers in order to save far more is a common cliche, but it’s one that always struck me as having a solid basis in fact.

After a moment, he addressed Sickle again. “Seriously, though, you should look over your weapon. It won’t take long.”

She groaned a little louder, a hind-leg lazily kicking in the air. “Fuuu… It’s too goddesses-fucking early for that shit.” She cracked a smile, lazily flopping a forehoof across her crotch. “Tell you what: you come over here and fuck me ‘till I’m good and awake.”

He rolled his eyes, returning to his weapons. “Not happening.”

“Aww,” Sickle said in mock disappointment. “That’s not what you said last night.”

Dusty’s jaw tensed, but he didn’t reply.

As we lapsed into silence, I focused on the task at hoof. For a relatively mundane task, there was something satisfying about working on that rifle. It was an intricate and complicated machine, where so many parts worked together to produce a single result. It wasn’t quite as satisfying as coding, but there was certainly a degree of puzzle-ness to the procedure.

The similarity kind of fell apart when I pulled the pin from the bolt and started brushing it clean. Carbon build-up is hard to map to a coding analogy, though I did crack a smile when I considered that perhaps my rifle just had horrible memory management.

I had just started reassembling the bolt group when Starlight returned, walking up to where I sat. “Hey, Whisper?”

The firing pin slid neatly through the bolt, holding the rotating cam in place, and I carefully picked up the retaining pin; it was a bit awkward with just my mouth and hooves to work with, but having an earth pony as my standard disguise had given me enough practice to manage it. “Hmm?”

“Yeah, I just thought of something I should probably ask you about,” she said. There was a pause while I slid the retaining pin into place and gave a gentle tug on the rear of the firing pin to confirm it. Then Starlight spoke again. “Um… in private?”

I looked up to see her awkward half-smile.

Before I could say anything, Sickle chuckled. “Soooomepony’s getting their morning fucks.”

I sighed, but didn’t bother shooting her an irritated glance. She’d just find it amusing. Starlight didn’t, either, though her ears flicked back for a moment. “Sure,” I said, looking at the reassembled bolt. It’d take only a couple of seconds to put it back in and close up the rifle, but I still hadn’t gone over the barrel or gas system. “Dusty, could you watch my stuff?”

“Of course,” he said, in the midst of checking over his magazines.

“Thanks,” I said, setting the bolt assembly down and rising to my hooves. Sickle just lay there, watching us as we left.

Starlight followed me into the room. She looked concerned, and absently left the door open as she entered. I stepped back, shutting it behind her.

Outside, I heard Sickle finally getting up, her armored hooves thumping heavily on the floor.

Now, I’m going to have to digress slightly.

People have a certain psychological need for control in their lives. It can manifest in all manner of strange and even unforeseen ways, but it’s there.

This is a danger to Infiltrators for two reasons.

First, we have to recognize that there are many situations where we do not have control. We might be able to stack the odds more in our favor, but in the end, our fate is often completely out of our hooves. A mistake by someone else, compromised information networks, even completely baseless or unreasonable assumptions made by someone else might lead to an Infiltrator’s capture or death. Recognizing that lack of control can be terrifying, and it’s one of the hardest things that an Infiltrator must overcome.

But equally dangerous are the situations where we do have control. When you act in secrecy, arranging things behind the scenes, there are times when you set something in motion that your target, whether a person or an organization, has absolutely no chance to prevent. A good scheme, properly executed, is like a work of art. It’s a remarkably pleasant sensation, that feeling of power, where for a fleeting moment, you’re the one pulling the strings. For that moment, you hold the fate of a project, a life, a country, in your hooves.

In a life where we normally have so little control over our fate, there is a natural desire to hang onto that fleeting sensation for as long as possible. To drag it out just a little bit, to savor the feeling. To show your target that, for just that moment, you have absolute power over them. It’s one of the psychological factors addressed in our training. No matter how tempting or satisfying it is, a good Infiltrator can’t indulge in such dangerous pleasures. A good Infiltrator doesn’t taunt their defeated foe. They don’t give clever one-liners. They don’t monologue and explain their masterstroke like some Con Mane or Daring Do villain.

A good Infiltrator lures their target into a false sense of security, and then shoots them in the back without a word.

I never heard the shot.

Chapter Thirty Eight: Damage

Out of the abyss of nothingness, a hint of light was the first thing that I can consciously remember. It didn’t mean anything. It simply was. It was all that was. Nothing else existed, even thought, but that little hint of gray in the dark stirred something. It grew, and as it grew, I slowly became aware. A thought slowly bubbled to the surface, and I knew where I was: the entrance of my hive, looking out the entrance tunnel at the light outside.

I heard sound. I couldn’t discern any details, any meaning to the sound, but I knew it must be my sisters, walking the tunnel with me.

I ached. My body felt oddly tight. I realized I was on my back. I wasn’t looking down the tunnel. I was… underwater? The light of day filtered down to me, cloudy and indistinct. The sound I heard was… a voice? Echoing faintly through the water to my ears. I couldn’t breathe, but I was still breathing. Somehow that made sense. I must have transformed into a fish.

It continued to make sense until it didn’t, and new scenarios floated to the surface. My brain struggled slowly up to speed, picking out fragments of memories and imagination to piece together and make sense of the jumbled and incomplete signals that reached it.

What finally pierced the haze of slowly dawning confusion was pain. The aching tightness I felt steadily grew in intensity, a focal point that my consciousness steadily crystallized around. As the pain grew, so did the hazy light. The gentle touch of affection teased at the edge of my senses, and I reflexively fed on it. Somewhere, muffled yet increasingly clear, I could hear Starlight’s calm, gentle voice.

My eyes opened, lids slow and heavy, and immediately shut once more against the searing light. Starlight’s voice was still there, soft and coaxing, then distant and loud, then soft once more. Again, I struggled to open my eyes, the blinding light slowly fading.

Starlight was still talking. I tried to answer. I think I managed a moan.

Something cool was pressed to my mouth, and something wet spilled across my tongue. Thirst suddenly flared up, and I weakly tried to grip the object with my mouth, struggling to drink as much as I could. I tried to grab at it, as well, but I don’t think my hooves were listening to me.

A warmth flooded through me as I drank greedily on what my brain insisted must have been at least half a gallon of fluid, yet it did almost nothing to alleviate my thirst. The world steadily focused. The pain seemed to both fade and grow more focused, in a way my half-awake brain couldn’t quite comprehend. My head and chest both felt like they were in a vice.

A dim silhouette steadily resolved into the soft, smiling face of Starlight, an empty healing potion floating beside her. The previously blinding light was nothing more than the glow of cloud-filtered sunlight through the thick curtains beside her.

She spoke again, and finally, I was able to make out the words. “That’s better. You all awake now?”

I opened my mouth to reply, only to wince in pain. Something was wrong with my jaw. It felt as if the carapace along my cheek might have been cracked. That thought led to noting the sharp teeth my tongue had touched. I was in my natural form.

Why was I in my natural form? And why did I ache? I tried to dig up the memories, but my memory was a morass at the time. I vaguely remembered something about working on my weapons and Starlight talking to me. I became very concerned that I had accidentally shot myself.

I must have missed several seconds, as Starlight was bringing a cup to my mouth. “...need your fluids. You’ve been out a while. If you wake up a bit more, we can get you some painkillers, too.”

Dusty had entered at some point without me noticing. He stood opposite Starlight, though I couldn’t make sense of his expression.

I tried to drink greedily from the cup, but Starlight took it slowly, a hoof gently supporting my head. When it was done, she let it down again, and I sank into the pillow, panting. Even in my degraded mental state, that stood out as alarming. I was winded from taking a drink.

All sorts of questions immediately leaped to mind. What happened? Where was I? Why was I injured? How bad was it?

What I managed to croak out was simply, “...What…”

Starlight leaned in close, gently looping a foreleg around my shoulders. She didn’t squeeze, though the touch still called up a twinge of pain from my side. “You’re okay,” she said, her face close enough to be comforting without being so close as to seem uncomfortable or intimate, and I’m not entirely sure why that evaluation immediately came to mind.

The thought lasted only a moment before I managed a weak smile. Starlight was there. Starlight was good. That meant everything was good.

It was several more seconds before the questions started teasing at my senses again. It was around then that I registered the E.F.S. indicators in my vision. While it didn’t give me a lot of details, it did indicate that I was in poor shape, just in case the pain wasn’t making that clear.

“W-why,” I croaked, then paused, swallowing, and trying again. “...Why am I hurt?” My voice was off, my words tumbling around in my mouth and coming out all wrong. My jaw didn’t move right.

“It doesn’t matter right now,” Starlight said, her smile faltering for a moment before returning. “Right now, let’s just focus on you getting better, okay?”

I found myself mirroring her smile, my head sinking a little deeper into the pillow, and savoring the gentle feeling of her affection. That lasted only a moment before the concerns surfaced once more. I was starting to recognize how impaired I was, how slow and muddled my thoughts were. Something was very wrong. Naturally, I had to figure out what was wrong and how to fix it. “But… what happened?”

Starlight’s hoof gently touched my chest, which I finally recognized was covered by a blanket. I was in a bed. “Don’t worry about that,” she said, voice soft and soothing. “You need to rest, okay?”

The sound of her voice was so gentle and pleasant. I focused on the sound. A moment later I twitched, fighting off the lull of sleep; I could feel myself shutting down, dozing off, but I couldn’t do that yet. I had responsibilities, and no time for sleep.

“Details,” I asked. Even just that much made my chest ache. I needed to wake up, clear my mind, focus, and evaluate my situation. Maybe I could transform into something that handled the pain or injuries better, but I didn’t even know how hurt I was.

They had exchanged looks, silent for a moment, until Dusty finally spoke. “You were shot.”

I remember thinking that didn’t seem right at all. Being shot seems like one of those things you should remember. I had a hard time articulating the thought, so I simply repeated myself. “Details.”

He frowned, but finally replied, “A changeling tried to assassinate you. She shot you in the back.”

I actually had to stop and think on why a changeling would be trying to kill me. When I finally connected the thought, the memory of Serenity brought a spike of adrenaline. I was their enemy, and they were targeting me specifically.

Most times, I find adrenaline a nuisance, between the narrowing of senses and tendency towards jitteriness, but it beats the heck out of coffee for waking up. I can’t complain about the painkilling effect, either.

“How… how bad am I?” I wheezed, fighting off the sudden urge to cough. I rolled my head to the side, spotting the cup floating in Starlight’s magic. She must have recognized where I was looking, as she filled it again before floating it over. This time I was able to lift a foreleg to gently guide it, ignoring the twinge of pain at the motion.

Dusty waited until I had finished drinking to answer. “Bad enough that you’ve had four healing potions and surgery, and you’ve been unconscious for about thirty hours.”

Thirty hours. That was too long. What had I missed? Had the Trotsen forces already left? Had I slept through the entire fight? Too many questions came all at once, but as I slowly fell back into my training, I shelved them. I had to deal with my current situation before I could adequately handle anything more grand.

I tried to lift my PipBuck-clad leg, but I only managed to lift it an inch before the hot stab of pain made me set it down again. I was breathing faster just from that little effort. I repeated myself. “Details.”

“You need to rest.”

I looked at Dusty, doing everything in my ability to keep my voice firm and even, even as the world skewed strangely around my head; I was pretty sure I was observing the late effects of a concussion. “Dusty,” I said, pausing a moment to catch my breath. “I need details.”

He continued to frown down at me, staring right into my eyes. I held his gaze, putting all my focus into maintaining a steady stare. I must have managed it, as he gave a little nod and spoke.

“She had a weapon just like yours. A standard Equestrian Army pistol with suppressor, firing subsonic hollow-points.” He gestured to my side. “She hit you from just off your flank, two rounds into the back right side of your chest. Two perforations of the right lung, one perforation of the left lung, laceration of the trachea and esophagus, serious damage to the diaphragm, and heavy blood loss. One of the rounds lodged against your heart. Your… shell, or whatever you’d call it, was shattered in one spot. We’re guessing one of the rounds broke a rib before you transformed.”

I realized Starlight had averted her eyes, her expression tight and fragile.

Dusty continued. “She followed up with two rounds to the back of your head, but you got lucky. The first shots must have knocked out your shapeshifting, so you had your armor. One hit low and to the side, slipped past the helmet, shattered your lower jaw, and lodged in your nasal passage. The other one struck the back of your helmet. That stopped it, but it still caused a minor fracture across the back of your skull.”

I lay there numbly for a few seconds, piecing everything together. It seemed so unnatural. “That’s… a lot. How…?”

“Immediate treatment with healing potions,” Dusty said. “And she didn’t have the time to finish the job. I forget how freakishly fast Sickle can be. Shit, she was up and moving before I even heard the shots. Busted through the door, took down the assassin, and I got a healing potion in you to stop the bleeding.”

“That’s… still a lot.”

“Blood loss was the biggest danger, and healing potions handle that very well. A bigger problem was getting the bullets out of you to do more serious healing. There aren’t many ponies around that can do surgery and wouldn’t freak out at you being a changeling. It took us hours to get Soaring Heart to come help you.”

I groaned softly, letting my head sink back. “...Great. I bet Echo loved my secrets biting me in the flank.” I winced, closing my eyes, and quickly added. “Sorry. That’s… not fair.”

I heard Dusty’s grunt, followed by a stretch of silence before he finally spoke again. “There’s more.”

My eyes cracked open again, blinking a few times against the blurriness. He met my gaze before continuing.

“She wasn’t the only changeling,” he said. “Serenity hit back.”

The fading tingle of adrenaline picked up again. “...How bad?”

“Bad,” Dusty said. This time, he didn’t wait for me to insist on details. “Hardwood is dead. Aurora is dead. Sightline, the Militia commander, is dead. Hail Burst was badly injured. One of Sandstorm’s riders died stopping an assassination attempt on her, and Axle’s still in bad shape. Then there’s the sabotage. They planted demolitions. Destroyed three motorwagons, damaged another two and one of the skywagons. Killed about a dozen Trotsen ponies and one of the Loyalist soldiers, plus some miscellaneous casualties.”

I felt like sinking into the bed and never coming out. This was bad. We hadn’t even gotten to the fight, and already Serenity had hit us hard. “What… what happened since then?”

“A whole lot of nothing,” Dusty said, a distinct grumble to his tone. “Mareford’s a mess, sorting out leadership. The Militia is doing well enough, but the town itself is all chaos. Sandstorm’s pissed beyond all belief and growing impatient. She wants Mareford to pitch in, but the ponies running the mayor’s office are scared of getting involved now. Hail Burst isn’t impressed by any of this, and is talking about getting her ponies to safety. Gemstone’s still in, mostly thanks to Dazzle, but they’re pretty much the only ponies still on-board with the plan. It’s a shit show. You’d think being hit like this would make ponies more likely to work together.”

I listened, taking it in, digesting it.

Then I rolled weakly to my side, grit my teeth against the pain, and started pushing myself up.

Dusty was there in an instant, his hooves moving to my shoulders. “Oh, no. You need to rest and recover.”

I’d like to say I fought back, but that might imply that my feeble resistance had any chance of success. I found myself on my back again, with his hooves resting gently atop my chest. “Just rest,” he said.

“No,” I wheezed. Breathing was surprisingly difficult. I weakly raised my hooves, clutching at his forelegs. I focused all my energy into focusing on him and speaking in a hard, firm tone, though I imagine the effect was less than I imagined it to be. “Dusty, listen to me. There isn’t time for rest. If this falls apart, we’re all done. Serenity wins. I need—”

I coughed, pain lancing through my side with the sudden convulsion and leading to several more pained coughs. I clutched Dusty’s leg tighter, focusing on the pain for a moment, eyes clenching shut. When they opened again, I fixed him with a glare. “I need… to do… what I can.” I weakly shook my head, the world twisting strangely with the movement. “I know I’m in bad shape, but… but I can still talk. That’s what I’m good at. If I can help keep things from falling apart, then I need to do so, before it’s too late for all of us.”

He had that tight frown again. That frown where he really disliked what I was saying even though he knew I was right. His hooves didn’t move. “Whisper, you can’t even stand up right now.”

“Then help me stand.”

He stared silently for several seconds before replying. “You’re not going to stay put no matter what I say, are you?”

“No,” I said, letting my hooves slide back down to my sides. “You’d have to tie me down, and I’d just shapeshift out of that.”

He gave a quiet snort, and after a moment, looked up to Starlight. “Get some painkillers.”

A minute later, Starlight passed a couple of pills to Dusty, who had produced another healing potion. He leaned over to give me the pills. I weakly raised a hoof, blocking his. “Only one,” I said, already breathing a bit harder from the sudden movement. “I’ve had those before. Too strong. I… I need my head clear. I need to think.”

“You sure?” he asked. “It won’t do much good if you can’t think past the pain.”

“Can handle that,” I replied, eyes half-shut. “Can… change. Relieve some injury.”

Starlight finally spoke again. “You can heal by shapeshifting?”

“Not heal,” I said, head lolling to the side as I looked to her. “Relieve. It’s… complicated. Rewiring nerves is hard, but… but I can work around the injuries.”

It was a bit of a simplification, and possibly over-selling my ability, but it was reasonably accurate.

“Okay, then,” Dusty said, removing one of the pills. “We can always give you more if you need it later.”

“Yeah,” I said. “That healing potion should help, too.”

“We’re running low on these,” he said. “But you’re right. We need ponies sticking together. Stocking up on healing potions won’t matter if Serenity wins.”

My hooves wavered as I reached up and gently clutched the healing potion. The pill I risked taking in my magic, receiving only a faint throbbing sensation along the back of my head for the effort. The small exertion also left me well aware of how depleted my magic was. I’d burned through a lot of it just healing up.

Starlight’s affection was still there, and I continued to cautiously feed on it.

I downed the pill and slowly drank the potion. The magic took hold immediately, the pounding headache and searing pain in my side fading a touch. I laid my head back, waiting for the painkillers to kick in, and bracing myself for what was coming.

☢

In the next half-hour or so, I managed two significant accomplishments: I assumed a fully upright sitting position with only minimal help from Starlight, and transformed into my standard disguise without complicating my injuries.

The healing potions had mended my skeletal structure—carapace at first, bones after my transformation—to the point where nothing was shifting and tearing at my soft inner bits, but I still had significant soft tissue damage, as my PipBuck happily informed me via its medical screen. The painkillers were doing their job, which was both good and bad at the same time. The pain was much less immediate, but my head felt stuffy and muddled. I didn’t like it.

I’d also restructured and rewired several parts of my disguise as best I could, despite my temporary impairment. I think it worked, though with how much the pain and drugs were obscuring things, I couldn’t be sure. I left the minor outward physical signs of injury, however; not only would it be more consistent with my impaired behavior, it might be something I could play for sympathy.

Before those alterations, I had felt weaker than when I had emerged from that chrysalis two months earlier, starving and atrophied. Even after, I still felt weakened, but functional.

After a few minutes to recover from the effort and catch my breath, I finally felt ready to move on. “Okay. Dusty, what’s the situation? How do we get these ponies talking again?

“Oh, they’re talking,” Dusty said with a grimace. “At least, as long as you count arguing and bitching as talking.”

When I prompted him for details, he clarified. “Hardwood had made plans to have organized talks with all the foreign representatives and key members of Mareford. So far everypony’s holding to that, even Sandstorm, though she seems to be losing her patience for the whole thing. She’s getting the last of the weapons she ‘traded’ for tonight, so I wouldn’t be surprised if she takes off in the morning. She’s certainly threatened to.”

I slowly nodded, a hoof placed firmly on the bed beside me to keep my balance as the whole world wobbled. “Okay. So we need to make sure that doesn’t happen. Are they having any of these meetings before then?”

“Just one,” Dusty said. “Right now. It’s supposed to go for a few more hours, but like I said, Sandstorm’s getting impatient.”

“So we need to do this now,” I said, heaving another sigh. “Okay. Let’s… let’s do this.”

The first step, of course, was getting to my hooves. I turned slightly to the side, sliding slowly off the edge of the bed. Starlight moved to help support me, but I weakly waved her off with a hoof. “No, let me… let me try first.”

She hesitated, obviously wanting to help, but let me try on my own.

I got one hoof down to the floor, and slowly slid until I dropped onto all fours. A thin line of pain ran across my side, along the partially mended rib, but I grit my teeth and bore it. I had to stay leaning against the bed for several seconds, but after another stabilizing breath, I gently pushed myself away. I wavered, spreading my hooves a little wider. My sense of balance seemed delayed, as if it took a second for the sensation of ‘down’ to make its way through my muddled brain, but I managed to keep my balance. My side felt sore, but not pained. I could do this.

“So far, so good.” I heaved another deep breath and took a tentative step forward. It was slow and awkward, and the motion made my side ache horribly, but I retained my balance. My right foreleg trembled slightly, but held. “Okay. So… the meeting.”

Dusty led the way out of the room, while Starlight remained close on my flanks, ready to step in at a moment’s notice. I limped slowly along at a slow, shuffling pace. Not my best showing.

Both Sickle and Echo were waiting for us in the next room. Sickle watched me for a moment before cracking a smile and standing. “Well, shit, it’s about time you got up.”

Starlight snorted in sudden irritation. “Shut up, Sickle. She was shot.”

“And I don’t hear her bitching about it,” she replied, casually walking up to me. She paused, eying me for a moment before giving a chuckle. “Well, it might not have been a minigun or big fucking rifle, but hey, not bad.” Then she gave me a bone-jarring pat on the back. I grit my teeth against the pain that lanced through my side, a quiet hiss of pain escaping my lips past all my efforts.

Echo had stood as well, and now moved briskly to interpose herself between us. “Will you please stop trying to aggravate her wounds?”

“Oh, fuck off,” Sickle said. “She took a couple shots to the head and got back up. A pat on the back ain’t going to kill her.”

“From you, it might,” Echo replied. With her standing between us, I couldn’t see her expression, but I’m sure she was glaring.

By then I was able to breathe normally again, the pain in my side steadily receding to a deep ache. “Everyone… please, we have more important matters to deal with.” I paused, then added, “And Sickle?”

She looked to me, her smile fading away to her more typical, vaguely irritated look.

“...Thank you for saving me.”

Her head tilted slightly, apparently surprised at where I went. Then she shrugged. “Shit, I got to stomp a bug. That’s good enough for me.”

“Well I still appreciate it.”

She just shrugged again.

I paused to look around our gathered group. “As for the meeting… we should remain alert. If Serenity still has any agents in Mareford, we could be walking into danger.”

Echo gave a snort. “They had best not attempt anything. I will not permit them to harm you again.”

“Heh, I hope they try something,” Sickle said, grinning. “I could do with squishing some more bugs.”

I paused, and though I was fairly certain, I had to ask. “The assassin. I assume she didn’t survive?”

Sickle laughed. “Fuck no. Shit, it’s too bad you were out. You should have seen the splatter she made.”

I grimaced. “I thought so. Still… if another changeling shows up, it might be advantageous to capture her alive, if possible.”

“Eh, we’ll see,” Sickle said. “How many limbs can one of you bugs lose before dying?”

“Not many,” I said. I really didn’t have the energy to spar with her. “Let’s go.”

We headed out. While the meeting was being held at the town hall, just across the street, it still took an agonizingly long time to get there. The worst part was the stairs down from our rooms, which I had to take sideways, slowly moving one hoof at a time until I stood on a single step, before starting on the next. I distracted myself from the discomfort by listening to Dusty’s description of the situation and ponies I would be meeting. It mostly worked.

By the time we had climbed the stairs in the Town Hall and approached the old conference room, I had a tentative plan formed.

We entered with Dusty and myself in the lead. Ponies were talking, and while the conversation didn’t halt at our entrance, many ponies looked over to us. Reactions were distinctly mixed. Sandstorm and Hail Burst both frowned as they looked at me. Many of the Mareford ponies eyed Dusty, their expressions wary. Dazzle, who was looking a little worn down, brightened again upon seeing me.

At one end of the table sat the Mareford mayoral staff Dusty had told me about. Holly, Brushfire, and Mulberry all looked at us before returning to the conversation without missing a beat. Sitting beside them was Two Bits who, due to losses, had inherited command of the Militia, at least temporarily. He gave us a careful look, though he finished up with a small nod directed to Dusty. Finally, on the opposite side of the mayoral staff, sat Seroon. It was a little surprising to see him there, but Dusty had told me Seroon had quickly impressed Hardwood, to the point that the staff still consulted with him. He certainly seemed to have taken well to the role, and looked relatively relaxed compared to the ponies around him, even giving a soft smile our way. A touch of appreciative affection touched at my senses, and I thankfully drew on the energy he and Dazzle offered me.

There were other ponies, too, enough to make the fairly spacious room feel a little cramped. Sandstorm had a half-dozen of her riders behind her. Even more Mareford ponies were gathered around their end of the table, including a couple of more military-looking ponies and another of Seroon’s tribe. Hail Burst was relatively light, with only a single soldier at her side, although the power armor—menacing even with the blue and rainbow detailing—made their presence much more pronounced. Only Dazzle had shown up alone, it seemed.

“We heard you the first fifteen times,” Holly was saying, her impatience clear in her tone. “But right now, the only army I see is the one you’ve camped outside our gates in an attempt to extort us.”

Clearly, negotiations were not going well.

Sandstorm stopped glaring at me to shoot back a reply. “Well if you’d pull your head out of your flank for half a second, maybe you wouldn’t need other ponies to tell you what’s going on. Fuck, a bunch of their spies just bent you over the table, and you still don’t see it!”

“Funny how they only became a problem when you showed up,” Holly replied.

That seemed like a perfect time for me to step forward and interject. “Excuse me.”

And I was ignored. “Oh, right,” Sandstorm said with clear disgust. “I forgot. It doesn’t matter if shit’s going wrong, so long as it only happens outside your walls.”

“Excuse me,” I said again, ribs protesting as I tried to bring my voice up to something more than a quiet conversational tone.

Holly snorted in irritation, while Mulberry took the opportunity to reply. “I would like to help, but we have to look to the safety of our citizens first.”

“Excuse me.” I even managed to speak loudly enough that most of the table might have heard that I had said something, even if they likely couldn’t make out precisely what I had said past the loud conversation.

“Oh, I’d love to hear you explain that one to the ponies in Stinkpit and Hayseed. Let me guess, you had to protect your citizen’s right to steal from them?”

Dazzle cut in. “Perhaps we should listen to what Whisper has to—”

“We did no such thing!” Brushfire shouted. “Those towns attacked our ponies!”

Mulberry quickly added, “And even if it’s true that Big Shot had set things up to fake it, we still—”

“Shut the fuck up!”

I cringed as Sickle’s powerful bellow pounded at my ears in the enclosed space, ratcheting up the headache a notch. In the stunned silence, she pointed a bladed hoof at me, her teeth bared in a snarl. “Whisper’s talking.”

And with that, every eye in the room was on me.

I carefully straightened up, taking a quick breath before speaking. “I’m… sorry about that interruption,” I said, even as Sickle snorted. “Also, I apologize if I’m a little hard to hear. I still haven’t recovered fully from my injuries, and I’m afraid I can’t manage much volume.”

No harm in playing for a bit of sympathy right off the bat.

It was Seroon who spoke first. “I hope I speak for all of us when I say that I am happy to see you are still with us, and to wish you a swift recovery from your injuries.”

I smiled, softly. “Thank you. I should probably still be in bed recovering, but with everything that’s happened, I felt I had to be here.” I turned to the mayoral staff. “I understand that you have to look after your own citizens. I won’t even try to argue that you should not, but you need to understand the threat you’re facing to do so. Queen Chrysalis, the Serenity hive, they’re coming. They’ve already wiped out one settlement. This gathering army is the best chance to stop them. If it fails, you’ll still have to face them, only you’ll do it alone.”

“So ponies keep saying,” Holly said, “but we haven’t had any problems before this army arrived at our gates.”

“Your government had been infiltrated, possibly for months,” I said. “Wild Runner had been replaced by a changeling. I’m not certain exactly how long it had been, but every indication suggests it was for quite some time.” Or at least, that was the scenario that made the most sense.

They shared a look of surprise, which thankfully gave me the opportunity to catch my breath again. “And how do you claim to know this?” Brushfire asked.

“Because I’ve made a point of learning all I could about Serenity’s activities. I know more about the capabilities of changelings and the threat Serenity’s assassins pose than any pony in this room.”

Behind me, I heard Hail Burst give a quiet snort at my wording.

I continued to press the point, even as the ache in my side started to grow again. “And more than that, they’ve attacked you directly. You might argue over why they did so, but it should make it clear that they hold no good intentions for you and have no problem killing anyone to get what they want. All it took for them to start killing ponies here was the mere possibility that you might be a problem to them.”

The trio looked to each other, with Holly murmuring quietly.

Before they came to a consensus, Two Bits cleared his throat to draw their attention. When they looked his way, he spoke. “It’s clear they have hostile intentions. Striking back with multiple allies gives us a stronger force and lets us control the circumstances of the conflict. It’s the reasonable response to being attacked, and gives us the greatest advantage.”

I was pleased to see that he was on the side of the allied effort. That meant more pressure we could make use of.

Holly shook her head. “We don’t even know if there will be a conflict.”

“They’ve killed our people,” Two Bits replied. “They drew blood. If they want peace, they can come out and say so, but until then, I’m under the opinion that these changelings just declared war on us.”

Mulberry shifted in her seat, ears drooping. “I agree it’s a… hostile act, but ‘war’ just seems a little…” She gestured vaguely with a hoof, as if searching for an appropriate word, but ended up leaving it unsaid.

Seroon slowly and gently put a hoof on the table, and immediately, the Mareford ponies stopped and looked at him in anticipation. I wasn’t sure if I should be impressed or concerned. In just a week, he’d impressed the ponies of Mareford enough that they were listening seriously to him. The only question I had was whether this was due to insight or personality on his part, or simply a sign of how desperate the ponies of Mareford were.

“If I might interject,” he said, his voice soft, but perfectly clear over the now-quiet room. “I know my kind has certain reputations. One of those reputations is for the use of assassins. It’s true. My tribe may be descended from soldiers, but we have carried the history of our people with us. Assassins were a respected profession, and while our ancestors did not possess those skills to pass down, they did pass down our understanding of them as a part of our culture.” He placed his other forehoof on the table beside the first, leaning gently on the surface. “You see, soldiers and assassins served similar goals.”

One hoof raised slightly. “A soldier is the sword, able to hew flesh or deflect a hostile blade.” He set that hoof down, and raised the other. “But the assassin is a scalpel. It makes the tiniest of incisions, but wielded with skill and restraint, it can cut out infection and save the whole body… or it can sever an artery and kill it.”

His hooves returned to the table. “But it’s a delicate thing. A fine blade. If you attempt to use it for every problem, it becomes dull, brittle. You risk breaking it. You can not hack wildly away with it, like a foal clearing brush with a machete. Neither can you make the aggressive slices and thrusts you can with a sword. You have to use patience, a delicate touch, and most of all, discretion.”

He looked squarely at the trio of mayoral staff. “This Serenity they speak of has sent its assassins into this city. They see Mareford as a threat, one great enough that they have spent the lives of two of their assassins, and an untold amount of effort and resources, simply to strike at us. They have marked us all as their enemy, and they must intend us harm.”

Brushfire looked uneasy as he replied. “We don’t really know any of that, though. All we know is that the assassins were changelings, but we don’t know anything about what’s really going on. Sending out the Militia all on the word of some strangers is inviting a worse attack.”

“There is more,” Seroon said, and slowly swept a hoof around the room. “Consider: who did they attack?” He gave them a moment before answering himself. “They attacked settlement leaders. Military commanders. They destroyed equipment that was to be used against them.” Then he lifted his hoof once more, slowly turning it to point straight at me. “And they attacked Whisper. They lost one of their assassins trying to kill this mare. That act stood out to me, and the message it delivers is clear.” He calmly crossed his hooves on the table. “This Serenity sees her as a threat on par with the leaders of the most powerful cities in the Wasteland, and we should listen to her words with the utmost attention.”

I absolutely love that he was able to put so much weight behind my words, but as an Infiltrator, that was an alarming number of eyes suddenly scrutinizing me.

Holly was the first to speak the question that must have immediately come to everyone’s mind: “Why?”

Seroon simply gave me a little smile, and left me to answer.

I felt increasingly exhausted under the weight of all their attention. I took a deep breath, steadying myself, and spoke. “Because I know how they work. I know what changeling Infiltrators are capable of, the tactics they use, and the best ways to defend against them. I know Serenity’s strengths and weaknesses, and I’ve been spreading that information. Serenity’s greatest advantage was that nopony knew that they even existed. Now they’ve lost that advantage. Ponies know that they’re a threat, and more importantly, they know where to find them.”

Dazzle pitched in as well. “Whisper’s the reason we’re all here in this room. She’s been spreading the word and bringing in as many ponies as she could to help stop Serenity. Of course Serenity is scared of her. She’s the only reason we can even fight back.”

She finished by quite blatantly turning to look at the mayoral staff.

Holly shook her head, but the motion was slow and hesitant, ending with a glance to Two Bits before speaking. “Even if that’s all true, sending out the Militia is a risk. It means leaving the city unprotected. It means leaving our defenses and fighting out in the open. The Militia can hold the walls against any threat, but if this is some sort of trap and we lose them…”

Two Bits frowned. “We’d have a better shot hitting them first.”

“Soldiers and walls might be good against raiders and other armed forces,” I said, “but they’re useless against assassins that can look like anyone. You can’t defend against this. If you fortify your position and don’t strike back, you give them all the time in the world to take care of any other settlements that are fighting back, and then they can take their time infiltrating and slowly picking you apart.”

Holly snorted in irritation. “They won’t find us to be such an easy target,” she said. “They might have landed a sucker-punch, but they blew their surprise. Now we know what to look for.”

Hail Burst gave another, louder snort.

Myself, I stared at her in silent disbelief. A small part of me—possibly made louder by the lingering pain and drugs—wanted to shout at her for being too stupid, but that wouldn’t be productive.

Fortunately, I still had another card to play. So, instead of trying to beat her down with my words, I instead spoke gently. “Holly, when I say that your walls and soldiers can’t stop a determined changeling from getting into Mareford, or even getting up close to important ponies, it’s not speculation. If you had any hope of doing so, you would have known that I’m a changeling.”

She had opened her mouth to reply before fully processing what I had said, and ended up stumbling on her words. Surprised mixed with apprehension and doubt.

“Yes, it’s true,” I said. “Many of the ponies in this room already know. I’m also a changeling that has access to a sizable arsenal, including multiple balefire eggs. If I were aligned with Serenity, I could have leveled this building and killed everyone within it, and there wouldn’t have been anything anyone could have done to stop it.” The risk of me not surviving the attack was enough that I wouldn’t want to attempt it even if I had been inclined to do so, but that wasn’t important right then. “That’s the kind of danger we’re all facing with Serenity, and that’s why we need to work together to stop them. The longer they’re allowed to operate in the background, the more people die.”

Murmurs were rippling around the room among the ponies who hadn’t already known, and Echo had stepped up protectively to my side, glaring down her muzzle at the assembled ponies. Somewhere behind Sandstorm, I heard one of the riders speaking to another. “I fucking told you she was brown before!”

Mulberry was the first of the trio to find her words again. “That’s… why you know what they can do? Because you are one?”

I nodded, despite the way it made my head swim. “Yes. And I know exactly how changeling Infiltrators train and operate. The more time we give them, the more they’ll pick us apart. We can’t defend long against them, but we can strike back and stop them at the source.”

Brushfire looked dazed, while Holly was shaking her head. Her expression wavered back and forth, as if torn between talking to me or ordering my arrest. Her voice shook when she finally spoke. “No. For all I know, you’re just like those other changelings, and you’re trying to talk us into a trap! The Militia isn’t going anywhere!”

She turned to Two Bits, but jumped as Seroon placed a hoof lightly on her foreleg. “She is trying to help. Trust her.”

“Trust her?” Holly replied with an incredulous look. “Why the hell should we trust her? You know what she is!”

“I’ve known what she is since the day we first met,” Seroon said with a calm, placid smile, and turned his gaze to me. “She is an individual who stepped aside from her own quest to help some strangers she had just met. Someone who put herself in danger to protect my kin, with no more reward than the satisfaction of having done the right thing. One who mourned over our fallen, and who ensured that the rest of my tribe would have a future. That is far more important than whether she is a pony or not.”

There was a momentary pause before his smile widened a hair. “Though I did notice that she was no longer a pegasus.”

My ears flicked back instinctively, and despite the embarrassment of that little detail being called out, I couldn’t help a weak smile. “I’ve been getting a little more relaxed with my disguises as more ponies know what I am.” Or possibly careless, but ‘relaxed’ sounded better.

Mulberry looked anxiously around at the ponies and the zebra, and cautiously spoke up. “I think Seroon might be right.”

Holly shot her a look, then turned to look at me again. I made a point to keep my expression as soft and non-threatening as possible. I don’t think it helped much. “...I don’t trust her,” she said. “Even if she did all those things, what, she’s just turning on her own kind? I don’t buy it.”

“Serenity isn’t ‘my kind’,” I said, without showing any of the distaste I felt at the idea. “They see ponies as nothing more than food. My hive might have stayed hidden, but we always tried to work with ponies, not against them.”

Holly’s eyes narrowed ever so slightly. “You’re from a different... hive?”

“I am,” I replied with a small nod. “And Serenity has no more love for my hive than it does for your ponies.”

Her eyes darted to Echo’s glowering visage, then the rest of my companions, and finally returned to me. “And are they changelings, too?”

“No. They’re ponies.”

She slowly nodded, mulling it over, and her expression grew harder by the moment. “So your hive wants us to go to war with this other hive… and you’re all that they send to help us.”

“My hive doesn’t have any more to send.”

“Oh, of course,” she said with a snort. “A whole hive, and they can’t spare more than one single changeling. Why would they, when they can just send you, and you can get the ponies to do all the fighting and dying?”

Mulberry blanched, nudging her. “Holly…”

It seemed Mulberry had swung our way. Brushfire still looked dazed. We were close. We just needed a little push to tilt things fully into our favor.

Maybe it was the drugs addling my mind. Maybe it was the desperation of the situation and the absolute need for these talks to be a success. Maybe, just maybe, it was something else. Whatever the reason, an option presented itself to my mind. One that wouldn’t just give that final nudge, but might flip the scales entirely.

“I’m not ‘just’ a changeling.”

I focused on the magic of my disguise, but I didn’t unwind it. Instead, I steadily poured more magic into it. More, far more, than my usual transformations. I closed my eyes as the magic flames steadily flowed over me, slowly, as I carefully poured my meager magic into crafting the new form. The ache in my side grew in intensity for a moment, then rapidly diminished. I did my best to hide it, holding myself in a firm, confident stance.

Seconds later, it was done. I opened my eyes again to see the world had turned purple. Several ponies had started to pull weapons, but had halted as the shield bubble had snapped into place. Beside me, in the shield, Echo took a step forward, drawing even with me. She scanned over the ponies for a moment before looking to me with a satisfied expression.

More specifically, she looked up to me.

The shield vanished a moment later. I took one slow, steadying breath, before speaking in a softly resonant voice. “My name is Queen Whisper, and I am the last surviving adult of my hive.” I slowly turned my head to look across all the gathered ponies, and the tip of my great notched horn nearly scraped at the ceiling. “If my family is to have a future, it will be side-by-side with ponies, and I intend that to start here and now. I will fight alongside you, and do everything in my power to ensure we overcome the threat Serenity poses.”

Ponies continued to stare at me in shock, and I started to worry that I might have gone too far. I remained still, as non-threatening as my enormous form would allow, my heart pounding in my ears and sending throbs of pain through the back of my head. It was a few ponies murmuring in the background that finally broke the spell. Weapons lowered, tensions relaxing, as the giant insectoid creature before them refrained from attacking. While Hail Burst looked just as annoyed as before, many of the Mareford ponies looked awed, if a bit apprehensive.

Mulberry finally broke the silence with a simple question. “You’ll… help us?”

I gave a slow, serious nod. “To the best of my ability.”

Brushfire had finally come out of his daze. “Will that be enough?”

I gave a soft smile, careful to not show off too many of my sharp teeth. “Between the forces we have gathered here, I am confident that we can defeat Serenity. I will do what I can to make sure that victory comes at as small a price as possible. I may not be the greatest combatant, but I will offer every ounce of experience I have.”

“And that’s a lot?”

I paused a moment to consider how I wanted to answer that. “...I learned the art of espionage in Equestria, during the height of the great war. We had to avoid the attention of the Ministry of Morale and the scrutiny of an increasingly xenophobic population just to get the love we needed to survive. We did this, and turned over zebra spies and smugglers, and combated hostile changeling Infiltrators from other hives. I don’t want to overstate my ability, but I am experienced.”

I felt like I was imitating Echo, if just a bit.

Two Bits spoke over the growing murmurs. “And you can tell us about these other changelings?”

I nodded, giving me another moment to just breathe before speaking again. “I can tell you the approximate strength, equipment, and training of their forces, the capabilities of changelings, their strengths and weaknesses, and the mentality of their leader. I do not have any experience leading a military force or orchestrating military tactics, but I can offer my knowledge of these changelings to help you do so.”

The ache in my head grew, my heart pounding harder still. I couldn’t properly catch my breath; rapid breathing is a common sign of stress and tends to make you less believable. I wanted to project certainty and honesty, so I kept my breathing slow and steady, even as my body protested. Passing out would be preferable to appearing dishonest.

Two Bits slowly nodded as he considered what I had said, then turned to Dusty. “Is this all true?”

Dusty nodded grimly. “All of it. I’ve seen Serenity. It scares the hell out of me.”

Two Bits grimaced, and cast a glance back to the mayoral staff. “I say we take it. Hit back before they hit us worse.”

“I agree,” Brushfire said, looking to Holly.

She continued to look at me with wide eyes. “I… I don’t trust her.”

Mulberry placed a hoof on her side. “Holly…”

“I don’t,” Holly said again. “But… if you’re all convinced it’s the right call, then… okay.”

Mulberry smiled.

“About fucking time,” Sandstorm said, rising to her hooves. She looked to Two Bits. “We’re rolling out in the morning. If you and your ponies are coming to the party, you better be ready. We’ve already given these fuckers enough time to get ready for us.”

“We’ll be ready to move out,” Two Bits said in reply, standing as well. “I’ll pass the word and get everypony ready to move.” He looked to me. “When I’m done, I need to talk with you. We need a good idea of what we’re going to be facing.”

“Of course,” I said, dipping my head slightly, allowing myself to breathe a little more freely. As he turned to leave, I looked to Hail Burst. “Will you be joining us?”

“For now,” she said, her tone irritable. “You didn’t say anything about being a queen.”

“It’s a recent development,” I said. “Also one that might make me more of a target, but seeing as Serenity is already sending assassins after me, there isn’t much reason to keep it secret.”

“Yeah, sure,” she said, rising to her hooves and walking away. “Just don’t keep too many secrets from your allies.”

She left, and several other ponies milled around, discussing what had just happened. Some, naturally, approached me with varying degrees of nervousness and curiosity.

“I’m sorry,” I told them when they asked to speak. “I’m afraid I need to excuse myself and get some rest while I can. I’ll be happy to answer any questions you have once I’ve recovered a little more.”

The town hall was already more busy as we departed, with ponies hurrying around and talking rapidly. Soldiers had gathered, with commanders giving directions to their subordinates. Despite the activity, every eye turned my way as we passed.

I kept walking, putting on the look of calm confidence, with only a subtle slowness and favoring of one leg hinting at the extent of my injuries. By the time we reached the inn, the limp had grown. The stairs sent tendrils of pain through my side.

Finally, we reached the door to the room. I entered, took two more steps, and finally collapsed to the floor. My magic flickered out as I reverted to my natural form, groaning.

Starlight scurried up to my side. “Whisper!”

“I’m okay,” I weakly replied, wincing in pain as I rolled to my side. “I’m just… exhausted.”

Dusty stepped up. “Let’s get her back in bed before she hurts herself worse.”

The world abruptly turned purple as the weight lifted from my body, and I floated in Echo’s magic. It took me a few moments to fully connect that thought past the pounding headache. “I… didn’t hurt myself. I just… burned through a lot of magic.”

“Well, you did what you were aiming to do,” Dusty said. “Now you’re on bed rest until we leave. No arguing this time.”

“No arguing,” I murmured. I wouldn’t have argued even if I had the energy to. Moments later I was lowered gently into the bed once more. In that moment, it was the most wonderfully luxurious bed I had ever experienced. I slowly relaxed, weariness descending over me.

Echo was still standing over me with a thin frown. “...I can’t say I approve of the dishonesty,” she said, before begrudgingly adding, “but it did have a certain dramatic flair.”

“Not dishonest,” I murmured, closing my eyes.

I felt the bed shift as Starlight sat beside me. “What do you mean?”

“I mean… I’m the only one left in my hive. I’m basically playing the role already. Might as well call it what it is… at least for now.”

Dusty made some unhappy grunt, but didn’t say anything.

“Well I think it was pretty cool,” Starlight said, and I could tell she was smiling just from the tone of her voice. “You looked… you looked cool.”

I gave a soft chuckle. The conversation faded away, but Starlight remained there beside me, sharing her company and affection.

☢

I felt a bit better by the time morning came around.

I’d spent almost all the time sleeping, interrupted only for a couple of hours to receive visitors. I had been gently stirred awake sometime that evening to meet with Two Bits. I’d wanted to get up to meet him more equally, but Dusty insisted that I stayed in bed.

We spent at least an hour discussing Serenity, their equipment and forces, the disposition of Queen Chrysalis the Sixth, and the capabilities of changelings. A good deal of time was spent with him inquiring about changeling psychology, as we collaboratively pooled our knowledge to get a better tactical picture of what we faced.

It was a very interesting conversation. I wish I had been coherent enough to remember the details.

At least I was clear-minded enough to explain my diminished size as an effort to conserve magical energy. That much was technically true. While assuming the form of a proper queen wasn’t as exhausting as mimicking Echo, it was certainly among the more difficult and draining forms I had ever taken.

The extra drain on my magic from my healing simply compounded the issue. Fortunately, I was well supplied on that front. I had brief visits from Dazzle and Seroon to wish me well, and I fed on some of the affection and appreciation they held for me. Dazzle even insisted on giving me another healing potion from her personal stash, which helped ease the returning pain in my side.

It was Starlight that provided the bulk of the magical energy I needed, of course. I hadn’t even realized how much I was draining her until I saw her wobbling a little, her eyes slightly unfocused.

“I’m okay,” she had said, her ears perking up and expression growling livelier for a moment, before slowly slipping back to slack weariness. When I apologized, she refused it. “It’s okay,” she insisted. “You need it more than I do. Besides, at least this way I’m doing something useful.”

I insisted that I was fine, and that she didn’t have to worry about me now, but from the fragile smile, I could tell she didn’t believe me.

I tried to fill some of my little waking time being productive and making more of these recordings. I went over them a couple of days later and deleted the whole thing. It was rambling and semi-coherent, skimping on important details while repeating inconsequential ones. The whole thing was a complete and utter wreck and made me seriously question how sound-of-mind I had been at the time.

Still, I was feeling better when Dusty roused us. Only the faintest hint of light crept in around the edges of the curtains. Starlight groaned weakly beside me while I slowly pushed myself up to sitting once more. My side was still sore, but there were no more stabs of pain. The cracks in my carapace were fully mended, though the shell was still discolored in thin lines where it had split. More importantly, my head felt clearer, with only a faint ache lingering in the back of it. My jaw still felt tight and slightly lopsided, but not enough to impede my speech. I wasn’t up to normal, but at least I didn’t have that splitting headache any more.

Despite spending more than half a day in bed, I still felt exhausted. I slid from bed and onto my hooves, and while I wobbled a little from lethargy, my sense of balance had returned. Once Dusty had finally roused a grumbling and half-asleep Starlight, I staggered out into the common room. Echo and Sickle were already there, with the latter sprawled out and on the large couch, mumbling some incoherent greeting. Dusty guided us to chairs at the small table, and surprised us by pushing mugs of coffee into our hooves.

I started to decline, but after a moment’s pause to think, changed my mind. “I don’t normally care for stimulants, but I think I might have to make an exception.”

Sickle gave a weak chuckle, her voice thick with sleep. “Yeahhh, you call that weak-ass shit a stimulant. Heh.”

“I guess you won’t be wanting any, then,” Dusty said.

Sickle grumbled a little. “Eh, whatever. I’ve got plenty of Dash left. You want some, Your Highness?”

I winced slightly at that. “No thank you,” I said, and followed up with a sip of the coffee. The taste was just as strong and off-putting as I remembered, but that wasn’t the point.

Sickle shrugged. “Yeah, a lightweight like you’d probably just get all jittery with the good stuff.” She slowly stretched, letting out a drawn-out yawn as I took another sip before adding, “Maybe some Buck. That’s good for getting back on your hooves when you’re beat to shit.”

“I’ll pass.” Another sip. “But thank you.”

A thump and clatter drew my attention to the side, where Dusty had just deposited a bag. “Your armor,” he said. “Figured you’d want it back.”

I slowly nodded. “Probably a good idea.” It had already saved my life once already, and I couldn’t imagine things would be getting any safer until Serenity was dealt with.

I finished my coffee and started pulling out armor pieces. Donning it was awkward. Though I felt a good deal better, I was still stiff and sore, which made the process neither swift nor pleasant. Straps squeezed my carapace in ways it really wasn’t comfortable being squeezed just yet, and I was still reluctant to use my magic when I didn’t need to, just in case.

The final piece was the helmet. I paused, turning it over in my hooves to examine it. All I found was a tiny nick in the back, slightly off-center. It seemed like far too small of a thing to have hurt the way it did. I slipped it on, carefully buckling it in place. “...Okay. Guess I’m as ready as I’ll get.”

“There’s one more thing,” Dusty said. When I looked at him, he continued. “You made a big showy display of being a queen, yesterday. Are you planning on keeping that up, or going disguised?”

I stared silently for a moment before slowly, quietly groaning, and sinking down against the table. “Urgh. I shouldn’t have done that.”

“Well, it’s a little late for second thoughts,” Dusty said, frowning a little. “Still, it worked. You got everypony onboard, but you also got everypony talking. I’ve been trying to think on it, and I’m still not sure if ponies would be more concerned seeing a giant queen-bug walking around, or a pony they know isn’t actually a pony, or a bug that isn’t the bug they’re expecting.”

I groaned again as I considered all of those. “Past-me was stupid,” I mumbled, and finally, wearily, pushed myself upright once more. “As much as I don’t like it, I decided to take up the title, so I might as well live up to expectations. Anything else would be dishonest.”

Echo gave a soft snort, and I couldn’t tell if it was amusement or annoyance. “I am starting to lose track of what is honest, anymore.”

“I suppose it’s complicated,” I said. I closed my eyes, focusing my magic once more.

The change came easier. There was less damage to work around, no drugs or pain muddling my mind, and I had much more love and affection stored up than I had the day before. Additionally, I wasn’t fabricating a new form. I was retaking one I had already created. It was still an impressive amount of energy devoted to the change, but it was more like slipping on a comfortable old sweater than knitting a new one from scratch.

The change completed, I steadied myself, slowly looking over my form. I was so much like Queen Ephema, but another changeling would see the differences. They’d probably even recognize that it was me. The holes in my limbs were still my own, patterned the same as before. My mane was different from Ephema’s, with a more silvery teal color, lush and sleek, as opposed to her slightly shorter and straighter mane. Even the notches in my impressively sized horn were different, though only subtly. I couldn’t see my eyes, of course, but I knew they would be just like hers, vibrant green and expressive.

I could feel my throat tighten as I made the comparisons. Part of it felt like sacrilege, as if I were usurping her position, disrespecting her memory. I tried to shake those feelings off. Someling was going to have to take responsibility for leading the hive. For now, that was me.

I looked back to Echo, speaking in my new yet still familiar voice. “The best I can say is that I will do what I can to make this honest. If I am taking on the title of queen, I will do what I can to live up to that responsibility.”

She frowned in contemplation for a few moments before finally nodding. “I suppose that will do.”

“Well I think you make a great queen!” Starlight said, grinning sleepily as she looked up at me. I couldn’t help smiling back. “You look so cool!”

Sickle shrugged. “Eh, I’ve seen better.” She took a long swig from a beer before adding, “Now you add a dick to that, then maybe we’re talking.”

Starlight grimaced. “Damnit, Sickle! Do you have to make everything perverted?”

“Yep.” Another swig. “Shit, you know you’d love it. You’d jump right on that dick.”

Starlight rolled her eyes, and I stood to bail her out. “If you’re quite done trying to make Starlight squirm, I believe we have an army expecting us?”

“Yes we do,” Dusty said, rising to his hooves as well.

The next few minutes were spent gathering our belongings. In my case, that was simple, as my possessions had already been packed while I was resting. Dusty brought them out for me. Included among them were my rifle and pistol, resting atop the saddle bags. “I finished cleaning them for you,” he said quite simply.

“Thank you,” I replied. I hadn’t even thought of them until that moment.

When we left, I took the straps in my mouth, carrying my bags that way, rather than using my limited magic on the task. I’d considered adjusting the straps to fit this new form, but I lacked the drive to do so at the time. Besides, I reasoned, my armor only fit in my natural form, so if there was any fighting to be done, I’d probably revert to that.

As we started to leave, Dusty started giving directions to everyone other than myself. The intention was rapidly obvious. Sickle on one flank, Echo on the other, Starlight bringing up the rear, and Dusty himself at the head. They were guarding me.

It was probably for the best. As you might expect, I drew attention. Every eye turned our way as we emerged into the main lobby of the building. Most of the ponies there were from Gemstone, and they looked on with curiosity, with only a few nervous gazes. Dazzle was there, and softened much of the effect by waving and calling out a clear “Good morning!”

I replied with a soft smile and a nod. A few other ponies followed Dazzle’s lead, though generally with a bit more hesitation.

That tone changed as we stepped outside.

The town was still shrouded in the dim blue haze of the pre-dawn twilight. A pair of militia soldiers were stationed near the front of the building, rifles slung across their chests. Two Bits had evidently spread word about me, as there were no looks of alarm or leaps to action. Instead, they watched me warily, scrutinizing my every step. I gave them the same soft smile and nod I had given to Dazzle. They didn’t react at all.

They also didn’t seem to pay Dusty any attention, so I suppose my big reveal accomplished some good.

It was only a short trip to our parked motorwagon. More ponies passed on the street, and the reaction there was decidedly more mixed. While some still looked curious, many flinched back upon seeing me. Considering I was standing between a vicious-looking over-armored beast of a mare and an ethereal-maned pseudo-goddess, that said quite a bit about the impression I was making.

Echo stood guard while we clambered into the wagon. I climbed into the cargo bay and peered into the passenger compartment. I’d fit in the back seat so long as I laid out lengthwise, though my horn would make things awkward. It’d be almost impossible to look out the narrow side windows without either sticking my head outside or twisting it completely sideways, neither of which sounded appealing.

The wagon rocked as Sickle climbed up behind me. “Guess you’re back here with me, huh?”

“If I were feeling better, I’d try flying along with Echo,” I said. Then I added, “So I’m not crowding you.”

“Shit, ain’t like I mind getting up close and personal.” She chuckled, lips peeling back in a lewd grin. “But hey, if you want to make the trip a lot more fun…”

Starlight called back from the driver’s seat. “Sickle…”

“Oh, relax,” Sickle replied, sprawling back against the back armor and filling almost half the cargo bay by herself. “I’ll keep your bug-friend nice and cozy back here.”

Once we were all settled in, we drove to the same gate we had entered. There were many more of the Mareford Militia soldiers gathered there. At least fifty were formed into ranks in their identical uniforms and almost-identical kit, while commanders reviewed their troops. More were marching in. A few smaller groups of similar soldiers stood to the side, bearing heavier weapons. I saw a few machine guns, massive rifles, and even a pair of rocket launchers.

A bit further away, some twenty other soldiers sat, talking while going over their gear. They were less uniform in their appearance, with seemingly personal selections of headgear, eyewear, and other accessories. They were also more heavily equipped, with a wide variety of weapons, and each had the bulge of a PipBuck hidden under the flaps on their legs. Rangers.

Several wagons were parked nearby, laden with supplies. Many ponies milled around them, checking them over. Some of Seroon’s tribe was there, too. I saw Bloodbeak among them, who hopped and happily waved at us. I raised a hoof, offering a cautious wave in reply, which produced a pleased smile from her.

As the gate slowly ground open, Two Bits parted from the group of Militia ponies to trot our way. “Hey, Dusty!”

Dusty poked his head out of the passenger-side window. “Yeah?”

Two Bits hopped up, hooking a hoof over the edge of Dusty’s window to be even with the other pony. “You heading out to the Trotsen camp?”

“We are,” Dusty replied.

“Good. The Militia is assembling. Let Sandstorm know we should be ready to march in twenty minutes.” He’d unbuckled the flap over his PipBuck, revealing a map. “We’re figuring about two days march to the rally point, here, though it’s a bit fluid right now. Sandstorm’s being bitchy about the wait, but she finally agreed we should hit the downed cloudship first. We don’t want the bugs getting it running. She also agreed to play a screening force for our march, so that should speed things up.”

“Sounds good. I’m sure Serenity will want to try something. Hopefully that’ll limit their options.” He paused, looking slowly over the map before nodding. “Okay. So who’s in charge of this show, anyway?”

Two Bits gave a dry laugh. “Shit, does it look like anypony’s in charge? We’re just all kinda going in the same direction. At best, we’re bashing our heads together until everypony’s more-or-less on the same page.”

I had to chime in. “That sounds like a disaster waiting to happen. Serenity will be looking to exploit any divisions.”

“Not to mention it’ll make tactical command a bitch,” Dusty said. “You remember how the Bloodletter raid went?”

“Fuck, don’t remind me of Bloodletter,” Two Bits said with a groan. “I still don’t know how you kept from strangling Hardhat for that shit.”

“And now we’re looking at the same thing with twice the number of commands and ten times the ponies. We need somepony in command, or at least a joint headquarters.”

“Yeah, I know.” Two Bits sighed. “Everypony’s getting together at camp tonight. We’re still trying to hammer out some details, but maybe we can beat some sense into these ponies. I could use your help there, Dusty.”

“I’ll be there.”

Military matters weren’t my strong suit, but if it was a matter of persuading ponies to do something, perhaps there was something I could do. “Is there any way I could help?”

Two Bits paused, looking back at me in a way that struck me as very analytical, though whether it was considering my ability to help or contemplating what threat I might pose, I couldn’t say. “I don’t know. Half of me says they’re not going to listen to some changeling, but it seems like everypony else knew it and went along with you anyway.” He considered a moment longer before nodding. “Yeah. If you think you can help, show up. I doubt it’ll hurt. Besides, I still need to pick your brains now that you’re not conked out on painkillers.”

I nodded. “If there’s anything I can do to help our odds, I’m at your disposal.”

He nodded back, then hopped down again, waving us through the open gate. “Get going! We’ll talk about the rest later!”

“Wait!”

I looked back as Bloodbeak came running up, barely keeping her pack and rifle balanced on her back with her good wing. She skittered to a stop before giving us a big grin. “Can I ride with you guys?”

“Sure!” Starlight called out. “Hop on!”

“Woo!” Bloodbeak leaped, pumping a fist, followed by scrambling to keep from dropping her gear. She quickly got ahold of the straps in her talons, and hopped up, pulling herself into the cargo bed. “Thanks, Starlight!” She dropped her gear in the back, turning to give me a smile. “Hi, Whisper!”

“Hello,” I said, giving a smile and nod. As much as I was pleased to see her showing no concern over my appearance, I couldn’t help but glance at the pip on my E.F.S. compass. Non-hostile, for what that was worth. I didn’t like being suspicious, especially when she seemed so happy just to be there, but I’d already been quite literally shot in the back. A little wariness seemed appropriate.

“And you guys, too!” She quickly added, flashing a smile to Sickle and Dusty. Sickle just snickered, while Dusty nodded. “Oh, this is going to be so cool! I love this thing. How fast do you think you can get it up to this time?”

I caught Dusty both rolling his eyes and smiling. He gave Two Bits a parting wave before turning back to Starlight. “All right, Starlight. Take us out.”

Bloodbeak cheered, rearing up to place her talons on the edge of the roof, and looking for all the world like an excitable and unusually feathery puppy.

We rolled forward once more, passing under the watchful eyes of the wall-top guards, and made our way to the small army camped outside, busy as ponies packed up supplies and boarded wagons. The ruined skywagon sat just outside the Loyalist camp, an empty shell scavenged for any vital parts. The destroyed motorwagons were nowhere to be seen; they had been stripped and cannibalized for parts, even the frames.

Thirty minutes later, the army started to move. It was a slow thing, like a great beast slowly coming to life, snaking its way onto the bare dirt path. Already, Loyalist flights were taking to the air, spreading out into a loose but well-organized formation on the flanks of the procession, while a few pairs climbed and flew further afield, on the lookout. Sandstorm’s Beast and some of the other large motorwagons led the great column, with us following close behind. Many of the Trotsen ponies were walking now, while the many lighter wagons, freed of the burden of their occupants, now roamed out ahead of the column. They sped towards hills and ridges, and along the bare path before us, searching for any trouble.

Bloodbeak watched them go with a look of longing. Her eager chatting had ended as soon as we had started moving, but she’d quickly found the pace a bit lacking. “Maybe we should be out there with them?” she asked hopefully, but Dusty insisted we remained in the formation.

Behind us marched the Mareford Militia, neat and orderly. They weren’t some immaculate unit, like the Ministry of Image’s pictures of pristine parade-ground troops, but that had always struck me as superficial. Their bearing and organization gave me the impression of of experienced soldiers. Their uniforms were worn and faded and stained by long use, but their equipment was well-cared-for. They didn’t march in some picture-perfect formation, but they still formed orderly lines and followed directions, even as some of the ponies chatted and joked. It was a clear contrast to the Trotsen and Gemstone ponies, who walked in a more blob-like herd.

At the rear trailed a few dozen wagons, laden with food, supplies, and munitions, with another group of Mareford soldiers bringing up the rear.

I sat back, watching the motorwagons ahead of us send up lines of dust across the Wasteland.

Over the rumbling of the nearby wagons, I didn’t hear the steadily growing thumping until the last moment. In a sudden burst of sound, a whirligig flew right over-head, just twenty or thirty feet above us, and a second one roared past us a moment later. Both flew low over the convoy at high speed before climbing and banking away in opposite directions.

In the front seat, I heard Dusty chuckling. “Damn showoffs. Heh.” Several of the Mareford ponies cheered behind us.

“That’s so awesome,” Bloodbeak said. “They wouldn’t let me ride on them. Wouldn’t that be cool?”

“They… can be fun,” Dusty admitted, and Bloodbeak chuckled.

We rolled on, as I continued surveying the scene.

We had dozens of armed vehicles, including a tank. We had power-armor clad pegasi, an armored skywagon, and a pair of whirligigs. We had wagons laden with weapons, munitions, and supplies. We had hundreds of armed ponies, many of them professional soldiers.

This was no simple band of Wasteland-dwellers. No raider warlord could compare. Even the most successful mercenary company would fall short. It was a proper army.

The Wasteland had seen no shortage of violence, but this was something different. This wasn’t a minor squabble or raid. This had the feel of something historic, something the Wasteland had never seen.

For the first time in two hundred years, Equestria was marching to war.

And I was right at the head of it.

Chapter Forty: Analysis

I arrived on the Cumulonimbus in something approaching a royal manner. Two Enclave soldiers stood at attention as I touched down. I landed gracefully, standing tall and proud like a proper changeling queen, my mane blowing in the steady wind of the cloudship’s flight. Echo touched down just behind me, following like some royal attendant or guardian.

This was the first time I had seen a cloudship up close, and while the Cumulonimbus was battered and scarred, she was still an impressive vessel. I had landed at the edge of what had once been the hangar deck, prior to it being mostly crushed in. Metal had been peeled away or beaten down to make a flat landing, and a gaping doorway led into the ship. The matching door lay against the wall beyond, its edges jagged and drooping where the Loyalists had blasted their way through it.

The soldiers looked us over, practically radiating suspicion despite their face-concealing helmets, until one of them jerked their head to the side. “Follow us. Commander Hail Burst is waiting for you in the CIC.”

I cast a glance back to Echo—she gave me a tight frown in reply—before following the soldiers through the door. I had to duck my head. Even with their country led by alicorns of impressive size, the corridors were built for regular ponies.

The inside was poorly lit, with walls missing panels, pipes and wiring exposed, and support beams badly warped. Most of the lights were broken or missing, and a scattering of mismatched lights were added in various places to keep areas from being plunged into darkness. The faint creaking and groaning of metal made for a constant background murmur, as if the ship itself were moaning in pain.

As we turned the first corner, it was even worse. The walls were thoroughly peppered with scorch marks and craters, especially along the far end of the hall. Ash had settled into nooks and crannies, while a few larger clumps on the floor were partly scattered by the passage of hooves. Despite the signs of carnage, bloodstains were infrequent, but not absent. The volume of magical energy weapon fire had left few corpses.

The changelings crewing the ship must have mounted a hasty defense here as soon as they realized what the Loyalists had done, and while they had apparently put up a good fight, the effort had cost them dearly.

The signs of combat continued throughout the ship, but more sporadically. I made a conscious effort to avoid stepping in the scattered ash, knowing that these were the incinerated remains of what had been people less than an hour ago, but it was hopeless. The ash had been tracked all over the place; Loyalists and Serenity changelings alike had far more pressing matters to consider at the time.

We went deeper and deeper into the ship, and even with my head held low, I had to crouch to slip under the occasional low-hanging, badly-patched length of pipe or some dangling wires.

The pegasi escorting us didn’t say a word. We would have walked in complete silence, but Echo still had some concerns in mind.

“I still can not believe you would be so incredibly reckless,” she said, scowling as she followed along behind me. “I know you understand how important your life is to both of our plans. You jeopardized everything we are working towards.”

“Not everything,” I said, playing the serene, dignified queen. It’s a hard act to pull off without seeming aloof, especially with Echo being the closest present analogue. I tried to keep Ephema pictured in my mind. “It would have stopped Serenity from getting the megaspell. It would have saved lives.”

“Ponies survived hundreds of megaspells,” Echo shot back. “They will survive one more. I understand that you hold certain ideals, but those ideals will hardly matter if we can not improve the situation of ponies beyond this meager struggle to survive.”

“On the contrary,” I said, putting on a hint of a smile, “those ideals are how we can improve the situation, for ponies and all other people.”

She gave a tired sigh—I have to admit, it was possibly a little cheesy—but fell silent, sulking the rest of the way.

Finally, after a maze of grim, dimly lit passages, we passed through a pressure door and into a room tall enough that I could raise my head, my jagged, queen-like horn not quite touching the ceiling. The room was packed with terminal stations, screens, and rows of indicators. Some were destroyed, and there were extensive signs of repairs and reinforcement, including a large beam that had been welded in place in the middle of the room. Only a few of the consoles were actually crewed, while Hail Burst stood back, her helmet removed, eyes scanning the displayed information. Other pegasi crewed a few of the many stations, calling out back and forth as they checked over the systems.

She turned to me a moment later, eying me just as severely before giving a curt nod. “Welcome aboard.”

“Thank you,” I replied with a courteous nod, before putting on a more serious expression. “Before we continue, a question. When we met in Rust, who was the first of us to speak to you?”

She blinked, expression tightening for a moment, but she snorted before jerking her head toward Echo. “She was. Wait, no. She was the first one we saw. That was Dusty that called out, wasn’t it?” She frowned. “Satisfied?”

“Yes, thank you. And I’m sorry that I had to ask, but the dark and isolated passages of a damaged ship seem like the perfect place to pick off a pony for impersonation. I’d advise you to conduct some brief interviews with your ponies. They—”

“Already taken care of,” Hail Burst replied. “You’re not the only one to think of that.”

I nodded. “Again, I’m sorry. I don’t mean to be stepping on your hooves. You said you have prisoners?”

“We do,” she said, relaxing slightly. “Three, to be precise. All wounded. Not a single changeling surrendered. I get the feeling they’re not going to talk, either, but I thought you might take a shot.”

“I’ll certainly try, but you’re right. The chances of them telling me anything useful is slim. I might be able to discern some information through indirect means, but I doubt I’ll get much. Actually, I think I have a more likely source of information.”

“And this would be?”

“PipBucks,” I said, raising my leg to show my own. “Every changeling that wasn’t in power armor should have one, and they are a wealth of potential intelligence. I’d like to get a copy of the data contained on every PipBuck that can be found. I may not be much as a combatant, but I have experience in data intrusion, cryptography, and intelligence analysis, and I believe I can contribute more effectively toward our joint cause that way.”

Echo snorted. “Good. You have a troubling propensity for getting yourself into dangerous situations. The further we can keep you from the fighting, the better.”

An opportunity presented itself. I gave Hail Burst an uneven smile. “Apologies for Echo. She’s taken issue with some of my recent actions.”

Echo’s voice didn’t boom out at full volume, but it was certainly elevated in that tight space. “You were shooting at a megaspell with a machine gun. I know you understand their danger. If you or Dusty had managed to hit it, you would have all been killed.”

“Probably,” I said, slowly nodding, “but we had to do what we could to stop them. Our wagon was the one that got closest. As much as I’d rather not, we had to take the shot.”

“You would not have survived a megaspell detonation at such close range,” Echo said, her eyes narrowing dangerously. “I have intimate experience with their destructive potential. You would have killed yourself.”

“But not you,” I noted. “My hive would still have a future, and your own goals would merely be delayed, not destroyed.”

She frowned, glaring at me for several seconds before grunting. “You are the singularly most frustrating individual I have ever spoken with.”

Hail Burst had been eying me in silence, taking in our conversation, but she finally gave a faint snort of amusement at Echo’s reply. “You’ve certainly got that right.” She lifted a hoof, waving to the door. “Come on. Prisoners are this way.”

“Thank you,” I replied with a gracious nod. “To get back to the subject of PipBucks…”

“We were already collecting them to get what intel we could,” Hail Burst said as Echo and I followed her, with the pair of guards bringing up the rear. “I’ll get you a copy of the data we pull off them.”

“Thank you,” I said, ducking my head as we exited the room.

While extensive damage had rendered the Cumulonimbus a maze of collapsed and blocked passages, Hail Burst navigated the ship with ease, leading us through halls, stairs, and the occasional room. Every space had some unique damage: walls creased their whole length by the tremendous impact of the crash, floors replaced with crudely welded scrap, wires and cables routed through doors that could no longer be shut. The variety of damage and destruction was impressive, and made the fact that the cloudship still flew all the more amazing.

Finally, we ended in a dead-end hallway with a single sealed door. Hail Burst came to a halt, turning to face me. “We don’t have a proper functioning brig, so we’re keeping the prisoners under guard in here.”

I quirked an eyebrow. “They’re all in the same room?”

“They are,” she said with a nod. “Not ideal, but we’re short on ponies, and I wanted to keep at least two ponies watching them at all times.”

“Good,” I said, giving a nod that was made much more awkward by the low ceiling. “Changelings can be slippery. I escaped from inside their hive because they assigned only a single individual to watch me directly.”

She frowned. “I think I’d like to hear the details of that story, though it may have to wait. Right now I’d like any insight you have on keeping these prisoners secured. What capabilities do your people have that might aid their escape? What kind of magic? What should we look out for?”

“The most obvious is our shapeshifting,” I said. “It’s not limited to pony forms, or even to identical mass, as you’ve no doubt noticed from me. The exact capabilities of any changeling will depend on their skill, but assume any changeling should be able to transform into anything ranging in size from a newborn foal to a buffalo. This includes inanimate objects, or facsimiles of such, although I personally find the experience to be… unpleasant.

“Then there’s the standard range of other magical capabilities. Telekinesis, light, and conjuring fire are the only other universal abilities, but they’re fairly versatile, especially in combination. Offensive bolts of magic are relatively common, too. Changeling magic is also apparently capable of mental domination and limited teleportation, though I’m only aware of a single individual in all of history to have ever possessed those skills, and she was a queen.” I frowned for emphasis. “Which isn’t to say they couldn’t possess such skills, just that it would be very exceptional.”

“I see,” Hail Burst said, wearing a frown of her own. “Let’s just hope they can’t do that. Anything else?”

I considered that for a long moment before replying. “Just the obvious: don’t trust anything they say. It’s unlikely that you’ve captured proper infiltrators, but there are many professions that benefit from training in deception techniques.”

“Changelings are good liars,” Hail Burst said, giving me a flat stare. “Somehow, I think I’ve picked up on that.”

I gave a short chuckle, cracking a smile. “Which ironically means I haven’t done such a good job of it.”

She paused. “I can’t even be sure if that’s a joke or not.”

I gave another amused snort. “I’ve been shot, blown up, thrown around, came very close to being incinerated by a balefire megaspell—”

“That was your own fault,” Echo reminded me.

“—and I have a crack in my carapace that’s been a literal pain in my side all day long. I could use some stress relief, and humor is good for that.”

“Yeah, you sound like a barrel of laughs,” she said with a shake of her head, then lifted a hoof to gesture back the way we came. “The first door leads to a vacant room, if you want to use that for interrogation.” She stepped up to the door, knocking twice before opening it. “She’s here.”

A voice acknowledged her, and she turned back to me. “I’ll leave you to it. The Rangers are bringing aboard the last of the wounded. I’ll either be in the sickbay or CIC when you’re done here.”

“I’ll let you know what I find,” I said. “One last question. Approximately how many of Serenity’s changelings were on the ship? And approximately how many were killed?”

“We’re still trying to work that out,” she said. “Judging by initial accounts, I’d estimate they had about a company at most, including the changelings that went after the megaspell. Most looked to be crew rather than soldier, with only basic equipment, though there was at least a squad of soldiers in stolen Enclave power armor. We’re also estimating they took forty to sixty KIA in the Cumulonimbus, and maybe a few more wounded that managed to escape.”

“Thank you,” I said, bowing my head a little more.

She nodded, then turned and walked off.

I paused, taking a slow and careful breath, and stepped through the doorway.

The room had been a bunk room, and sadly no taller than the hall. Most of the furniture had been removed. Two soldiers in power armor stood guard near the door, heads turning slightly to look at me as I entered. Their weapons remained trained on the far side of the room, as if guarding the most dangerous prisoners they have ever faced.

Those prisoners were a trio of changelings, strapped down to the only remaining bunks, and practically mummified in bandages. Two were missing legs, with heavily bandaged stumps where the limbs should be. The third had bandages across her face, covering her eyes.

Only one showed any signs of consciousness. Her breathing was slow and labored, but as her barely open eyes drifted over to me, they narrowed. Even incapacitated, all three showed as hostile on my E.F.S.

I turned to one of the soldiers guarding them. “I see only one of them is conscious.”

“The bugs don’t give up easy,” the soldier replied, her helmeted head remaining fixed on the prisoners. “They fought until they were dead or unconscious, and M.E.W.s don’t give much margin between the two.”

“And their condition?”

“Stable.” Simple and brief.

“Very well,” I said, nodding. “I’d like to move the conscious one to a nearby room for some questions.

“Commander Hail Burst has given us strict orders for the handling of these prisoners,” the soldier said. “You will not be permitted to be alone with the prisoners. At least two Enclave soldiers must be present with a prisoner at all times. Furthermore, the ranking Enclave soldier present has authority to terminate any further contact with the prisoners. Understand?”

Translation: they didn’t entirely trust me, and the soldiers were there to guard against my misbehavior as much as the prisoners’. Some might find that to be irritating or insulting, but I found it strangely comforting. It was a very professional caution.

I nodded. “Of course.”

Our escort led us to the interrogation room, while Echo floated the helpless and wounded changeling soldier into the room, bunk and all. The room itself was another small bunk room, just large enough to not feel crowded with the number of occupants, though not so large that I could stand normally. Instead, I laid down on one of the cots, facing sideways from where Echo was setting down the wounded changeling.

I lay there, head held high, my eyes focused on the wall at the end of the room. I let the silence stretch on, visibly brooding. When I spoke, it was soft and quiet.

“Is there any way this does not end in bloodshed?”

The injured changeling made a weak exhalation that could generously be interpreted as a snort.

I finally turned to look at her. Even lying on the cot, I was taller than everyone but Echo. I could have loomed over her, powerful and terrifying, but I did not. I kept my expression soft and somber. “I know that things are steadily heading towards a cataclysmic battle, but I still hope for some peaceful resolution. I have seen far too many changelings die already.” I paused, and in consideration of our observers, added, “And ponies, too.”

She grunted, teeth gritting for a moment before giving a weak, barely audible reply. “Go… fuck… yourself.”

I frowned at that. “Do you think I’m talking about my own hive? I’m not. Regardless of how this all turns out, I am the only one of my hive in danger. I’m talking about your hive.”

Her dismissive snort had a bit more strength behind it this time.

“Your hive can’t win this,” I said, slowly shaking my head, adding a touch of sadness to my expression. “Your queen is forcing a situation where only one side survives. If we don’t find some other course of action, your hive is going to be wiped out.”

She gave a weak, pained laugh, followed by a grimace, grunting as she sucked in a few shallow breaths. It was a few seconds before she started to relax again, hissing out a quiet reply. “You already lost. We got the bomb.”

“And look at what it cost you,” I said. “You gave your opponent a powerful weapons platform, and lost a hundred changelings in the process. In exchange, you killed less than thirty ponies, destroyed a couple of motorwagons, and got a megaspell that will do you little good. A few more ‘victories’ like this, and your hive won’t exist. That army is going to wipe you out if we don’t find a peaceful solution.”

I might have rounded the numbers a little, but she could hardly know that.

She gave another weak laugh through gritted teeth. “Your… army. Heh. Not… not going to find much of it…”

“You mean the attack intended to take advantage of us splitting our forces?” I said, adding a hint of boredom to my expression; it was a guess and a bluff rolled into one, but all well-reasoned. “I think you’ll find things have played out differently than you imagined, much like it did here.”

Her eyes narrowed slightly, then looked away. “Doesn’t matter... We have… the megaspell…”

“And you really think that’s going to make a difference? I think you underestimate these ponies. They won’t make it that easy for you.”

Another choked laugh. “Doesn’t matter. Ponies… ponies are selfish. Now they know we have the megaspell… they either turn around… or we burn their homes. Heh. No army.”

She closed her eyes.

“You underestimate them,” I said, slowly shaking my head in case she opened her eyes again. “I’ve seen them. I’ve fought alongside them. They’re not going to be deterred by that threat. You’ve only got the one megaspell against five major enemies.”

She gave another dismissive exhale.

“And when they fight past your defensive forces, and they will, then they’ll be right on the steps of your hive.” Her eyes had opened, so I raised a hoof, gesturing around. “And you’ve already seen how easily these ponies can storm a confined interior environment like this. You had a perfect defensive position, and yet, how many of your fellow changelings died trying to hold them off?”

Another weak snort. “Engineers. Your ponies sure look good fighting crew with basic weapons… no armor. Heh.” She managed a weak sneer. “I heard the explosion. How many did we get?”

One of the Loyalist soldiers shifted a hoof slightly, the first reaction I’d seen them give since the interrogation started.

“Only a couple,” I replied, while silently noting how the term was frequently used in a much more vague manner than its strict dictionary definition. “And I saw the scorch marks on the walls. Magical energy weapons are impressive armaments for mere engineers. That’s hardly basic weapons.”

Her sharp-toothed grin was marred and contorted with her pain, but it conveyed the right emotion. “Should try the soldiers. Then you’ll see. Then you’ll die.”

“Considering the number we shot out of the air so recently, it seems you’re overestimating them.” I gave a mild shrug. “The power armor was interesting, I’ll admit. Though I’m afraid your hive just lost a good twenty sets or more.”

“Doesn’t matter,” she said. “Got ten times that. Maybe more. Your army dies.” She grunted, laying her head back again, eyes closing. “Wish I could watch.”

I paused a moment, considering her, but finally turned away. “Echo, could you please return her?”

As Echo levitated the changeling, one of the Loyalists spoke. “Done already?”

“She’s not going to give us anything more useful,” I said, rising to my hooves once more, with all the awkwardness of the low ceiling.

A minute later, the prisoner was safely under guard in the makeshift brig, and our escorts led us up a flight of stairs and through the maze of corridors. Soon after, we reached the sickbay. It wasn’t a single room, as I had imagined, but an entire section of the deck, with multiple rooms. We passed a group of Rangers heading the other way—Two Bits gave me a smile and a nod—and entered the main ward, full of ponies.

When looking over a room filled with twenty wounded ponies and four armored pegasi trying to treat them, I would have expected to describe the scene as chaotic, but what I found was as orderly as you could imagine. A few of the ponies were breathing hard, jaws tight in pain, but neatly tucked into medical beds. Some of them had IVs hooked up. The pegasi were calm and professional, and already making use of scavenged Serenity PipBucks to diagnose their patients. Even the half dozen cots brought in from other sections were neatly arranged into the scant available space, and gave room for the less severe cases to rest and await treatment.

Hail Burst stood at the edge of the ward, looking over the scene. She didn’t react as I stepped up beside her, so I spoke up, softly. “Commander.”

“Queen Whisper,” she replied, a frown touching her lips. “It was a bloody day. Still, far better than it could have been.”

There was a thump of a door opening in the back of the ward. Soaring Heart, and some pegasus I only vaguely recognized, wheeled out a a gurney with an unconscious patient. Two of the armored pegasi went over to help, easily transferring the pony into a bed.

“Okay, who’s up next?” Soaring Heart asked. His voice was exhausted, but he didn’t show it.

The armored pegasus beside him replied. “Over here,” she said, nodding her head towards the opposite bed.

The ponies in armor helped move the groaning patient into the gurney, while Soaring Heart quickly clasped a PipBuck around their remaining foreleg. He was already rattling off instructions to the pony assisting him as they wheeled the patient out into the adjacent room.

Hail Burst watched them go. “Bit of a step up from combat medic, but Soaring’s been handling it well.” She shook her head, then looked to me. “Come with me.”

She led me out of the sickbay and into a neighboring and unoccupied compartment, which looked to have been about twice the size before the ship’s crash landing had smashed in the far wall. Inside, with the door shut, she turned to face me. “Your interrogation didn’t last long. I’m guessing it went as expected?”

“Only one was conscious,” I said, taking the opportunity to lie down and give my neck a rest. “She’s under the impression that the balefire bomb is to be used as a deterrent. A threat that, if the army doesn’t turn back, they’ll incinerate their homes.”

She frowned slightly. “So no surprise there.”

“There’s also a good chance that Serenity is taking advantage of our absence to attack the rest of the army, though I couldn’t say for absolute sure. The forces you faced on the Cumulonimbus were mostly not soldiers and had what she considered minimal weaponry. Proper soldiers will be more well-equipped. They also have upwards of two hundred sets of power armor, though that number has a very wide margin of error. I’d estimate the actual number at between one hundred and one hundred fifty.”

Her frown deepened. “That’s a lot.”

“It is concerning,” I said with a slow nod. “Unfortunately, I couldn’t give you an accurate estimate of how many of those are Steel Ranger armor and how many are pegasus armor. I haven’t seen enough of their force to make that guess. At best I could say that a minimum of about ten percent of their armors are Steel Ranger models. Probably more.”

“Hopefully more,” she said. “Steel Rangers pack a lot of armor and firepower, but they can’t fly. They’ll have to use skywagons for rapid mobility, and they’re down one of those.” She silently pondered that for a moment before shaking her head. “Anyway, their deterrent. Do you think it’ll work?”

“Sandstorm’s out for blood. If anything, I think the threat would just piss her off more. Gemstone is small enough that a balefire bomb is no more of a threat than a couple squads of power-armor soldiers, so this doesn’t really change their situation. And while I imagine you dislike the idea of them using the balefire bomb on Enclave citizens, it would be the hardest target for them to strike, and I get the impression that this threat will not deter you.”

“Your impression is correct,” she said, her voice perfectly even.

“Which leaves only Mareford. They’re a professional force, so I don’t expect intimidation to work well on them. I don’t know Two Bits well enough to make precise judgments of his mentality, but he does take Dusty’s word seriously, and he was one of the few pushing for going with us. That said, it was a narrow thing getting them involved in the first place, and those soldiers’ duty is first and foremost to protect their homes. I think they’re likely to stay, but I’d like it to be a more sure thing. There are too many unknowns.”

“And even if their threat doesn’t work, they might just use the bomb on the army itself,” Hail Burst noted. “I don’t suppose you got any information that could help take it off the table?”

“No,” I said with a shake of my head. “Unless she was secretly the captain, I doubt she would have any idea about where they’re taking it, and even if she did, I doubt she’d let that information slip. I’d like to go over whatever data we can get from their PipBucks to see if they contain any useful information. If that doesn’t turn up anything, the best I could do is make estimates about where it would make sense for them to hide it.”

“Okay,” she said. “Assume you don’t get any useful information. Where do you think they’d put that bomb?”

I frowned, thinking on the question for a moment. “It depends,” I said, and lifted my PipBuck-clad foreleg. “About how far can one of these broadcasters reach?”

She looked down at it. “I’m not sure. If it’s anything like ours, maybe thirty miles line-of-sight. But that’s topside. Perfect conditions. Down here, I’d say line-of-sight might get you fifteen, twenty tops. Less in bad weather. Down in the dirt you’ll be lucky to get five.”

“Then that gives us a couple of slightly higher-likeliness areas. Someone would have to make the decision to actually deploy it, so there’s a chance it’s being kept within about twenty miles of either the changeling leading the defensive forces on the surface, or the hive itself. If this Queen Chrysalis is anything like her namesake, I expect she’d want to be the one to decide on its use, which would suggest it’s hidden near or in her hive. Then again, if she’s anything like her namesake, she’d probably also want to lead any attack herself, which would suggest it’s being kept near any intervening forces.”

“Mmm.” She frowned again. “That sounds like a lot of ifs, maybes, and guesses.”

“An unfortunate reality of my profession,” I said with a wry smile.

That drew a single faint chuckle from her. “Mine too, I suppose. That said, I’m not sure that helps us any.”

“It might not,” I said with a shrug. “But it does give us a potential vector for further action if the opportunity presents itself, and something to look out for.” I paused. “But the more I think on it, the more things don’t quite line up.”

Her gaze sharpened, eyes fixed attentively to me. “How so?”

“It’s not much of a deterrent if your opponent doesn’t know your intent.”

She paused. “And I don’t suppose they’d expect us to infer that threat from their actions.”

“It’s possible, but it seems sloppy to me,” I said. “Which means we need to return to the army as swiftly as possible. If Serenity does not deliver some form of ultimatum, then it would suggest they intend to use the megaspell on the army itself.”

Hail Burst grimaced. “And if they’re holding a condensed position to defend against a concentrated attack…” She considered this for several long seconds before her expression hardened, taking on the look of authority. “The Cumulonimbus is under-crewed, while the Trotsen force is small and under-gunned. Separated, we would be vulnerable to attack. We have only a few more hours of daylight. I do not expect the Trotsen force will be able to travel effectively at night, and we do not have the capacity to carry their motorwagons.

“Queen Whisper, I need you to get the Trotsen force moving with all urgency. The intent will be to cover as much ground as possible tonight and set out first thing in the morning to rejoin the army as soon as possible. I will be dispatching a messenger immediately to pass this intelligence on to the main force.”

She abruptly turned her head, reaching into a compartment. When she drew back, she was clutching a datastore, holding it out to me. I took it in my magic.

“That contains all of the data we retrieved from the recovered PipBucks. Hopefully you can make some sense of it while we’re traveling.” She ended with a firm and decisive nod. “Good luck.”

I bowed my head in reply. “And to you.”

She turned, opening the door. “Show Queen Whisper out,” she said, already breaking into a trot. Then she activated her radio, her receding voice echoing strangely from my earbud. “Firefly to CIC, immediately. Repeat, Firefly to CIC.”

As the guards motioned for us to follow them, Echo stepped forward. “That will not be necessary,” she said, and we vanished in a flash of purple.

☢

We were moving in less than half an hour. The conversation with Axle was so simplistic in its mechanics that I could have predicted the entire course of the conversation, if not the specific words. I told him we needed to hurry to return to the army, and he countered that he had several damaged wagons that he wasn’t going to further damage for my needs, demonstrating his position of strength to his ponies by refusing me. I state that the main army, including Sandstorm, was under attack, and he angrily tells me I should have just said that before yelling at ponies to get those same wagons moving right now, having made my idea his own.

I might have found the entire charade annoying if it didn’t get me exactly what I wanted. Instead it left me pondering whether Queen Whisper should exhibit any signs of regal pride that might have just been slighted, or if I should maintain the professional Infiltrator practicality of real-Whisper. Both had their benefits, after all. Pitfalls, too.

But seeing as I had six captured PipBucks—I had returned the one Skim had laid claim to immediately after the conversation with Axle—I quickly settled on “real Whisper” as a way of shelving those thoughts and starting on something far more exciting.

Settled into the rear seat of our motorwagon and returned to my natural form, I turned to my collection of PipBucks and the data they contained.

I was immediately interrupted by the intrusion of a very cheerful griffin’s face. “Hey!” Bloodbeak said, showing no sign of impairment from her earlier injury. “What was that ship like? It looks so cool! I mean, it’s all banged up, but still cool. Was it cool?”

I found myself uncertain of how to reply, managing only a quiet “Uh…” for the first few moments. “It… it was pretty trashed in the fighting, and it got kind of ugly in there, but… well, it is still an impressive piece of hardware. Yeah, it’s cool.”

She gave a happy squee, sliding forward until her belly was resting on the back of the seat. That produced a wince and a sharp hiss, but a moment later she giggled again. “Ow. So are you going back up there? Could I go with you? They won’t let me ride in the whirlydingies, but maybe those pegasi would let me look around?” She raised her good wing. “Feathery solidarity! Right?”

I silently glanced down at my equipment, and the great deal of potential data I might find on them, and found myself somewhat disappointed in myself. I know, it’s logical and professional, but that doesn’t mean I had to like it: I didn’t trust Bloodbeak. No, she almost certainly wasn’t a changeling spy, and while she was incredibly talkative, the chances of her leaking information that then got to an actual changeling spy was very low, but it was the kind of risk an Infiltrator has to avoid. It wasn’t even a criticism or personal judgment of her. It was simply professional.

That didn’t make me feel like any less of a horrible jerk for doubting the friendly and outgoing griffin smiling so happily before me.

I glanced past her to where Echo sat. “Resting her wings” was the excuse she had given for riding in the motorwagon instead of flying above. I suspected the only reason she was tolerating Sickle’s close presence—and frequent lewd comments—was to guard me. I was her key to a better future, and she didn’t intend to lose me to my own “carelessness”.

“Perhaps Echo could give you a lift?” I said. It was a convenient way of getting rid of Bloodbeak, and I felt a stab of guilt as I thought of it in those terms. It was a practical method of steering another person’s actions, the kind of thing an Infiltrator would frequently take advantage of out of necessity.

Then again, I wasn’t exactly an Infiltrator any more. I was something much more complex, now. As hesitant as I was to use the term, I was the queen now, and I was guiding the future of my hive.

“Bloodbeak, wait.”

Despite the energy of her pleading with Echo, she immediately stopped and turned my way. “Yeah?”

“There may well be some information or conversations here that could be very sensitive, and that we need to keep secret for the good of the army and everyone in general. I don’t want mislead you, but I also don’t want you to feel insulted or excluded. It’s just that there are a lot of lives on the line, and I’d really like to minimize the number of ears hearing this.” I gave a soft, if somewhat awkward smile. “I’d be happy to spend more time with you, but when we’re working on this, I’m afraid we’re going to need some privacy.”

Her head had cocked slightly to the side as she listened attentively and quite seriously. The moment I finished, her smile returned. “Oh, yeah, sure! I won’t get in the way of that. Besides, that’s a great excuse to go on the ship! ‘Queen Whisper said you have to let me on!’ Hah!”

I blinked at her enthusiastically casual response to my serious moral introspection, and I felt a momentary urge to chastise myself for thinking so little of her. I could have dug even deeper into those thoughts, but I instead focused on what she had said, giving a weak chuckle. “I, uh, doubt my rank has any official influence over Enclave personnel, friendly or not.”

“Well it should,” she replied. “But yeah, I can go up and hang out there while you work. When do you think you’ll be done?”

My slim smile faded as I considered that. “I suppose that depends on what I find. I’ll probably be busy until we get back to the army. Maybe… maybe until we’ve dealt with Serenity for good.” I gave a lopsided smile. “If it lasts that long, I’ll make sure to take some breaks from the work. Working constantly all day long just leads to problems.”

“Not to mention it’s no fun at all,” Bloodbeak said, taking on a decidedly sly and knowing look. It was gone an instant later as she flashed a grin at Echo. “See? It’s vitally important that I’m allowed to check out that cloudship. Lives are on the line!”

Echo’s frown grew ever darker. “That is not what she—”

“Lives are on the line!” Bloodbeak repeated, throwing up her forelegs and spreading her good wing in a dramatic flourish before dropping back to all fours and leveling her most wide and innocent grin at the grumpy alicorn.

Echo held her disapproving gaze for an impressive two seconds before sighing and rolling her eyes. “Fine. I will take you to the cloudship just to get you out of our manes.”

Bloodbeak cheered, jumping in the air quite gracefully despite the motorwagon’s rocking. Moments later, they were flying off, with Echo’s magic holding the energetic griffin a safe distance away from her body.

“I like her,” Starlight cheerfully noted, and I couldn’t help chuckling.

With that done, I turned to the data that we had collected. There was disappointingly little, and at the same time, far too much.

Many of the PipBucks had contained a good number of audio files, though only a couple of them matched the collection of thirty six journals I had recorded. I skimmed the audio file names in the first few PipBucks, and almost all were music, or at least titled like music. There were hardly any personal recordings. I played a file titled “Notetoself”, dated just five days ago, and was disappointed when a wheezy sounding changeling simply listed a few scheduling changes that needed to be made to cover an injury.

I set the audio files aside for the moment. With none showing obvious value from their title, they were too low in information density by time, so they got low priority. Text files were easier to skim for relevant information and I could read a good deal faster than someone could talk. There were also relatively few of them, and even fewer that had been written or modified recently. Most were useless. One had a list of meals eaten with detailed grading as to desirability. Another gave a detailed list of kills of and deaths by various other changelings in simulated battles. One curious file had a date—the day before yesterday—followed by ten blocks of numbers, each of which was seven lines of sixteen characters each. I filed that away for later; powers of two usually meant something.

There were a few, however, that were slightly more interesting. Mostly, these were notes on units in the “current force”, and one of these gave a basic if slightly unclear breakdown:

1 PLT - mobile force
1 - PAP - assault
2 - PAP - retrieve
3 - INF - retrieve screen
4 - INF - assault screen / reserve
Sky 1 & 2 attached for retrieval on ch 3 and 5

2 PLT - reserve / ship (under st)
1 - PAP - exterior screen
2 - INF - delay/reserve

It was information, though I wasn’t quite certain what to make of it. From the context, it was a division of forces. With my rather insignificant knowledge of military units and tactics I could assume that “PLT” stood for platoon, which probably made the following numbers squads. The breakdown seemed to correspond perfectly to the groups we had seen in battle. “Under st” was under-strength, which I assumed noted that the second platoon had half the squads of the first. Sky 1 and 2 were probably uncreative and obvious designations for the two skywagons we had seen. “Ch” was curious. Channel?

“Hey Dusty?”

He looked back from the front seat. Past him, I could see the other motorwagons, rolling along at a decent clip, though nowhere near as breakneck as on our way out. “Yeah?”

“The context is a list of the Serenity forces we fought, divided by platoon and squad. Any idea what squad being designated P-A-P versus I-N-F could mean?”

“I-N-F makes me think infantry,” he said. “Don’t know about the other one. Did they only have one or the other?”

“Yes.”

“If one’s infantry, the other might be power armor.” He gave a little shrug. “Just a guess. Can I see?”

“Just a moment.” I took up one of the spare datastores I had, plugging it into my PipBuck to copy the file.

Dusty waited, looking at the array of equipment I had set in the seat next to me. The half-dozen PipBucks had been joined by my entire collection of data stores, a collection of electronics tools, and all my cables. “You building a maneframe back there?”

“I wish,” I said, passing over the datastore. “I’ve got a decent amount of raw data. Extra screens and inputs is good for organizing and comparing.” I gave a dry laugh. “What I wouldn’t give for a simple keyboard right now. How large might a squad be?”

Dusty blinked at the abrupt change of topic. “It varies. Ranger squads are seven, to fit in Pigeon. Regular Militia squads have a third fireteam and give the squad leader an assistant, so they’re eleven. Pretty much anything from seven to, say, fifteen.”

“So… forty two to ninety soldiers deployed here. Even on the upper end, that seems pretty slim for what we saw in Serenity.”

“Saving every soldier for the army, probably,” Dusty said, a hint of grumble coloring his voice.

“Likely,” I agreed, returning to my data.

I dug into the remaining data. There were more force lists, but from their dates and few notes I could gather, they seemed to be describing simulated combats. These did provide one minimally useful piece of information: a few had a level of organization above platoon, designated COY—a strange shortening of ‘company’, I assumed—which appeared to usually consist of three platoons. Even more alarming was the occasional note of one or even two other companies with other tasks. A quick bit of math and the assumption that those other companies were fully staffed suggested about 400-plus soldiers.

And even more concerning, this was only one side of the simulated mission. I knew from overheard conversations that some, if not all, of their simulations had Serenity’s soldiers playing both sides. I didn’t even know if their simulation could create fictional constructs to fight against. Surely they wouldn’t be fighting the ponies they fed on?

Most of these force lists came from a single changeling, so I searched her PipBuck for more information. I wasn’t disappointed. In a folder labeled “post mission notes” I found three files. Opening the first, I found a rough shorthoof-filled account of a recent simulated combat. Many of the specific terms and personalized notation escaped me, but I could follow the rough course of the battle, where this changeling’s side had to escort a set of heavily laden wagons from one compound to another, through an area of dense and rocky hills.

“Dusty. Datastore. You’ll want to see this.”

The moment he removed the datastore from his PipBuck, I snatched it in my magic and plugged it into my own. A quick transfer later, and I passed it back. “Open the file ‘Rocky Road’ and tell me what you think.”

The brief look of confusion and curiosity was shortly replaced by surprise, and then interest. We read through the files together, trying to work out this changeling’s shorthoof, along with me asking for the occasional clarification of a term or abbreviation. Some required a bit more explanation than others; explaining that “BOF” stood for “base of fire” meant little to me without then explaining what that term meant. It was an area that I had no experience in, and needed to learn quickly.

Heck, I was pleased with myself just for realizing what “LZ” stood for, even with its context being so painfully obvious.

I continued searching for more information as we talked, and turned up another interesting discovery: this changeling’s PipBuck had dozens of map files. For those who don’t know how PipBucks work, that’s not just unheard of, it’s outright nonsensical. PipBucks have one map file, and it details the entire world, with the ability to adjust and expand upon it as new information is received. There was no support for multiple map files because they had no purpose.

That is, no purpose the designer had conceived of, or had considered important. After all, how likely was a PipBuck to end up in some other world?

I have no idea if PipBucks still interacted with their wearer while they were in one of Serenity’s simulations, or if they had been copied over to the PipBucks for later use, but they had created dozens of worlds to fight in.

“Rocky Road” described a combat in the “Motor Canyons region”. One map file was titled Motor Canyons. A quick file transfer to a spare PipBuck, and we had a map of the battlefield to go with our textual description. The world of Motor Canyons was only fifty miles on a side, but this was apparently sufficient for the battle enacted there. The landmarks referenced in the battle let us follow the exact movements of various units. It was perfect.

It was also concerning. Among the many maps were detailed and fairly accurate renditions of more than a dozen settlements, including Mareford, Trotsen, Gemstone, and even a still-intact Rust. A quick check of the main map files showed location tags spreading well beyond the local area, with every PipBuck having the exact same data. They’d been thorough in mapping out the surrounding area and ensuring their soldiers had the most accurate data.

I hadn’t noticed the darkening skies until we slowed. Even with the superior low-light vision of a changeling, the terrain was getting increasingly hard to pick out. The line of vehicles slowed more and more, limping along, guided by the struggling light of a unicorn in the lead wagon.

Soon Axle had given up the attempt, and the Trotsen vehicles started pulling into a loose group. Dusty directed Starlight to park off to one side, while ponies started to dismount, lit by the occasional flashlight or glowing horn. Soon they were setting a campfire. The dark clouds of the Cumulonimbus flickered like a brewing storm, hovering low above our camp.

We kept to ourselves. Dusty checked in with Two Bits, who clarified that the Rangers were being situated in the Cumulonimbus to give extra security, before signing off for the night.

After a brief dinner, the fatigue of the day had caught up with everyone. Eyes were half-lidded, conversation slow. Not that I minded the sparse conversation. I was still going over the data in my mind, even if I wasn’t sure how it would help us.

Dusty called it quits first. “Time for sleep. Who’s on first watch?”

I glanced at the ragged gash torn in the side of our motorwagon, wondering if he was expecting us to watch for an attacking army or suspicious ponies. Either way, I spoke up. “I’ve got enough rattling around in my head, I doubt I’ll be able to sleep yet. I’ll take it.”

“Good enough for me,” he said. “Just remember to actually keep an eye out instead of burying your muzzle in a PipBuck screen.”

Which I realized was probably what I would have done if he hadn’t said so. “Of course not,” I said, giving a weak smile.

“Okay, then,” he said with a nod, stretching before lying out on his side. “Wake me for second shift.”

The others followed shortly after him, while I walked a short distance away, sitting atop a boulder that rose from a rocky shelf. A quick adjustment of my eyes, with some inspiration from owls, and the wasteland opened up before me. Just an hour out from the Pale Sands basin, the rocky hills and valleys surrounded us, looming in the darkness. The view was all shadows and silhouettes, and almost devoid of color, but those silhouettes were sharp in my eyes. Nothing would approach us without me being able to see them.

As my head jerked back upright from its steady descent, I amended that thought: nothing would approach us without me being able to see them, so long as I could keep my eyes open. Even the new knowledge that was running laps in my head wasn’t enough to stave off the fatigue. I needed to do something. I briefly considered listening to the collection of audio files we had retrieved from the Serenity PipBucks, but I dismissed it; I should keep my ears out for anything my eyes might miss.

A minute later, I concluded that, while I couldn’t listen to audio files, perhaps I could still create them. A short internal debate as to whether that would compromise my hearing any less than listening to audio eventually fell on the side of giving me something to do to keep my eyes open, and I started up a new journal file.

Time passed quickly and uneventfully as I quietly narrated my life. Maybe it was the fatigue speaking, but there was something vaguely unsettling about describing events that were ever closer to the present. It was almost ominous, as if some outside guiding force was steadily converging on some point that was drawing slowly, inexorably closer. Soon I would reach the point where there was no more past to record, and where I once had a neatly organized plan for my future recordings, I would be left only with an unknown and increasingly unsure future.

Or maybe I was just really tired and allowing myself to see connections where there was only coincidence, patterns where there was only noise, imagining some guiding hand of fate that brought some sort of purpose and order to everything, and which was guiding everything to its desired and likely unpleasant end. Ending the recording with me being shot in the back of the head had possibly led me into a slightly more morbid state of mind.

I considered all of those thoughts for a few moments before cracking a smile and dismissing them. Applied psychology can be quite entertaining, even when practiced on myself.

I trotted silently back to camp and gently roused Dusty. Once he had risen and shaken off his drowsiness, I climbed up into the motorwagon. The seat would be more comfortable than the dirt. Besides, I was apparently a high-priority target. At least there I’d have some armor around me.

And it just coincidentally had my collection of PipBucks and their valuable data. As tired as I was, I wanted to check a few things before going to sleep. One of those things was the substantial amount of spells the PipBucks had been programmed with. I wanted to get a basic idea of what the common Serenity soldier would have available to them.

So I called up my spell compiler, loaded one up, and promptly forgot about sleep as the greatest treasure Serenity could have possibly given me unfolded before my eyes.

Chapter Forty Two: A Thousand Lies

There are many forms that danger can take.

The most apparent are also the most immediate. They tend to be the ones that people think of when the word “danger” comes up. In my previous life, that would have been the threat of discovery. The threat of the Ministry of Morale ambushing me, dragging me off, and extracting every vital secret I carried in my head.

In my new life, it meant raiders, corrupt mercenaries, and assassins. I had been in an alarming number of firefights. I had conducted armed and violent infiltrations of facilities. I had been the perpetrator of, witness to, or victim of multiple assassinations and attempted assassinations. I had ridden at the head of an army that marched steadily towards the inevitable violent clash that would decide the future of this land.

But immediate is not the same as greatest. Apparent is not the same as significant. The greatest and most significant dangers are often the most subtle. You do not always need an army or a megaspell to cause devastation to your enemies. Sometimes, all you need is the right word, whispered in the right ear. Nations have risen and fallen on as much.

So after all the raiders and ghouls and monsters I had faced in the Wasteland, I regarded this small, unassuming changeling as one of the most dangerous threats I had come across.

I stood beside Dusty at the headquarters shelter, watching her approach. She had initially flown near the outermost defensive line, holding back as she waved her white banner, until one of the Militia ponies had finally indicated for her to land. An entire squad of ponies walked her further into the camp. She carried nothing with her. She wasn’t wearing a PipBuck. Even the white flag had been taken from her, but the soldiers escorting her were still thoroughly wary. It was a good instinct, I thought, but probably not as useful as they might hope. The danger she posed wasn’t likely to be a physical one.

Even her appearance was a threat. She was slightly smaller than the average pony mare, both in height and weight, but she didn’t have to be. Her ears hung a fraction too low, her demeanor shy and uncertain, but showing emotion was different from feeling it. She could have looked like whatever she wanted, and Serenity could have sent any individual they liked. This was their choice, and it had meaning.

Small. Weak. Non-threatening. I’d spent most of the time since her sighting thinking on what they might try to pull, but on seeing her up close, I quickly revised those expectations. They weren’t starting off with a threat. They were starting with something more subtle and dangerous. They wanted ponies to empathize with them, even if only to a small degree.

Not that I expected her to get much mileage from the charade, of course, but it was only a part of her tactics. A hint of what was to come.

As for myself, I was already at a disadvantage, fatigued by my lack of sleep. The Mint-als made everything seem a touch too sharp, as if everything were too real. I would have gone to Dusty to make use of his coffee, but we didn’t have the time to brew it. Instead I went to Sickle, who had been so overly pleased by my request. I now had a dose of just about every drug in existence tucked away in my bags, just in case I needed it. She’d even cheerfully slipped a Dash inhaler into the mix, despite my objections.

I disliked the idea of relying on chems, but they could be useful tools, and my personal preferences came secondary to survival. Yesterday, it had been Buck and painkillers to fight off a minor concussion. Today it was Mint-als to fight off the dulling of fatigue. Both dangerous situations where I couldn’t risk being anything less than one hundred percent.

The Serenity changeling continued her slow approach until one of the soldiers called out to halt. She obeyed, slowly looking around the group with an uneasy eye. Once again, all the leaders of our army had gathered. This time all the looks of suspicion and distaste were focused on a different changeling, and with significantly more intensity.

She paused, swallowed, and quietly spoke. “Um… hello.”

There were a few raised eyebrows and glances at that, expressions that practically shouted “Seriously?” Sickle snickered as if thinking the same thing.

It was a couple of seconds before Dusty noticed the eyes turning his way, silently electing for their newly appointed commander to take the lead. He gave a momentary grimace before replying. “I take it you want to talk?”

“Ah, yes,” she said with a hesitant nod before pausing again. “Um… before we begin, I was wondering, would you prefer me remaining like this, or would you be more comfortable if I looked like a pony? I know some ponies find our appearance… unpleasant.”

More displays of shyness, and now empathy and a desire to compromise for mutual benefit. I could practically see the plan steadily unfolding, and I really didn’t like where it was going.

“We’re familiar enough with changelings,” Dusty replied, his head inclining toward me. I remained passive, standing tall and confident, though without looking down my muzzle as Echo was.

“Ah,” the changeling said, her eyes flicking to me before darting away shyly. “Yes, I suppose you are.”

Dusty’s expression was still mostly neutral, but I detected a hint of distaste in how the corner of his mouth shifted ever-so-slightly. “How about you tell us your name, and then explain just what it is you want.”

She nodded. “Of course. My name is Cheerlight,” she said, though I suspected that was a fabrication created specifically for this conversation. “I was sent because… because my queen was hoping to defuse this situation before hundreds die. We are capable of defending our hive, but the Wasteland has already seen so much death. We may live hidden from the rest of the Wasteland, but we still don’t want to see hundred of ponies dying just because they believed a lie.”

As she ended, her eyes flicked momentarily towards me.

“Ah,” I said. I might have laughed if the situation weren’t so serious. “So that’s how you’re trying to play this.”

She looked at me again, her eyes narrowing slightly even as she shifted her weight back, wings flicking anxiously. Intimidated, but defiant. Uncowed by the terrifying queen standing before her.

Dusty shot a look to me as well. “What’s up?”

I just shook my head. “I’ll let her explain.”

He gave me a questioning look that I answered with a faint smile and shrug. Then he turned back to Cheerlight. “Okay, fine. Let’s hear it.”

The changeling opened her mouth, then stopped, closing it again. Her expression was concerned. All of it was an act, I was sure. Finally, she spoke again. “I’m not sure if you’re the one I should be discussing it with.”

Dusty frowned. “And why’s that?”

“Because you’ve been with Queen Whisper for months,” she said, warily eying him, glancing to the other leaders, then looking back to him once more. “We’re still not sure if you’re actively aiding her goals, or if she’s been misleading you like all the others.”

I could see Dusty’s jaw tighten. “Since we’ve been working together, the only goals she’s had have been helping her hive and stopping you.”

“Technically true,” Cheerlight said, her voice slightly quieter. “But that’s how she likes to lie, isn’t it? Yes, she wants to stop our hive. She’s been trying to destroy us for almost a decade.”

I turned my head slightly towards Dusty. “And now you see where she’s going with this.”

Somewhere that I couldn’t defend myself. Somewhere that my own skills and training worked against me.

“Yeah, I see,” he said, his eyes hard. “That’s a bald-faced fucking lie.”

She gave a slight nod, though her eyes had taken on a soft, subtly pitying expression. “Because she told you otherwise, and she wouldn’t lie to you.”

Dusty bristled, but he shook it off almost immediately. Instead, his expression turned firm, serious, and calm. It was how he looked in combat. “Because we’ve been working together for two months, and she didn’t learn about Serenity until a month ago.”

Cheerlight was nodding again. “Because that’s what she told you.”

“Because we were there when she discovered it, and it blindsided her. Then she insisted we investigate, and we get blindsided again.”

Her head tilted slightly, her expression sad. “I don’t think you realize how convincing an Infiltrator can be. You are aware that she claims to have spent years in old Equestria, hiding among ponies and collecting their love, yes?”

“I’m more familiar with her past than you are.”

“And do you have any idea how demanding that is?” she asked, and touched a hoof to her chest. “I tried to become an Infiltrator myself, so I could help feed my hive. I couldn’t manage it. It’s beyond just ‘demanding’. You have to be able to play a role perfectly, without even the slightest slip. You have to be comfortable with living a lie for years, without letting anyone in. She claims to have done this for centuries. How hard do you think it would be for her to hold an act together for just a couple of months? To pretend to be surprised by information as a way to convince you of her sincerity? How long did she lie to you, pretending to be something else, only to change her story later on?”

“That’s a load of shit,” Dusty said, raising a hoof to point at her. “And if all you’re going to do is keep telling a bunch of lies, you can fuck right off.”

I didn’t smile, despite how much I wanted to. Dusty knew what to do. I’m glad, because for the moment, I had to remain silent. I was a known Infiltrator. A liar and a manipulator. Anything I said could be regarded with suspicion. It hardly mattered that the same could be said of her. She didn’t need them to trust her. She only needed them to not trust me. This entire little war hinged on the idea that I, a self-admitted professional liar and manipulator, was telling them the truth.

Cheerlight’s eyes had widened slightly, ears drooping, as if shocked by Dusty’s sudden profanity. She looked around, focusing on several of the other leaders. I could see the switch in tactics before she spoke, engaging the other important ponies before Dusty could completely shut down the conversation. “Please, listen to me! She’s been lying to you from the start. First she pretended to be a pony. Then she was a changeling. Now she’s a queen. What will she be tomorrow?”

Sickle snorted out a laugh from behind me. “I’ve been trying to get her to turn into a hellhound for weeks. Maybe that can be tomorrow.”

There were a moment of silence, as ponies blinked at the unexpected comment. It lasted only an instant before Sandstorm stepped up. “Yeah, fuck all of your shit. You fucking roaches killed Raindrops, so you can take all these fucking lies and cram ‘em up your ass. I’m going to enjoy watching you all burn.”

“That wasn’t us!” Cheerlight cried out in despair, then leveled a hoof at me. “Don’t you think it’s a little suspicious that a known changeling spy comes to you in the middle of a changeling scare, points you at a rival hive, and then immediately uncovers another changeling spy? She’s been manipulating all of you from the start!”

“Oh, yeah,” Sandstorm said with a derisive sneer. “And you’re all innocent and peaceful, ain’t you? Let me guess, it wasn’t you that murdered all those ponies back at Mareford, either?”

Cheerlight flinched, ears folding back, and I could already see the machinations behind the suddenly reluctant behavior. You don’t try to sell a lie you know your target won’t buy; instead, you give them the truth they know, and use that as leverage to work a different lie. “That… was unpleasant, but we’re running out of options. You were assembling an army with the goal of wiping us out! We had to do something to protect ourselves! And for the record, I was against the idea. It was an act of desperation that would make any attempts at negotiation that much harder, but… but as much as I disagreed with the decision to conduct the attack, and despite how callous and calculating the logic is, I have to agree that the conclusion was sound. If it did work, it would have stopped this conflict and removed the threat Queen Whisper poses to the Wasteland. Far fewer ponies would have died than if this turns into a war.”

Two Bits had tensed, his eyes hard. “Unpleasant? You murdered our mayor and a bunch of other ponies, and you call it unpleasant? And now, when that doesn’t work, now you want to talk?”

“This is new to us!” she said, raising a hoof pleadingly. “We’ve only survived so long because we’ve remained hidden from ponies who wanted to kill us for centuries! We’ve never worked openly like this.” Her eyes glanced my way, her expression hardening. “And besides, you’ve had this queen whispering lies to you this whole time. She’s already poisoned you against us, and anything we could say, she could come up with a lie to counter.”

I allowed a soft snort of amusement and a faint smile. This seemed like a relatively safe place to slip in a few words. “Cute symbolic use of my name to stir up an emotional response. And I only wish these people trusted me as much as you seem to think they do.”

“Some of us trust you.” It was Seroon who spoke, standing placidly a few yards away.

Cheerlight turned to him. “Because she saved you? She didn’t have to do a thing. She just let you walk along with her as she went where she was going anyway. She didn’t do it to help you. It was an act. She acts nice and sympathetic, and in return, she gets a loyal ally convinced that she can do no wrong.”

Seroon smiled softly. “And if all the people of the Wasteland were to act nicely to each other, even out of self-interest, I would dare say the world would be a much better place.”

“Is that so?” Cheerlight said, her expression turning serious. “And do you know what happened when we tried to be nice to her?”

I tilted my head slightly, signaling my curiosity. Oh, I knew where she was going with that, but it would be better to feign ignorance.

Cheerlight’s cast a sharp glare at me before jerking away, looking to Seroon and Sandstorm with a less hostile expression. “When we came across her, she claimed her hive was dead. We welcomed her into our home. And how did she repay us?” Cheerlight’s ears flicked back as she grimaced, looking away with her expression hard and tight, as if remembering some horrible injustice. “She broke into our computer to steal and destroy records, stole equipment, sabotaged the hive, destroyed our food reserves, killed six, and wounded more than a dozen changelings, many of which were unarmed workers in the wrong place at the wrong time.” Her glare returned as she faced me. “That’s the kind of person Queen Whisper is. We extended a hoof in friendship to a lost and lonely changeling, and she stabbed us in the back.”

Dusty gave an angry snort. “You welcomed her? You gassed us! You stuck us in some mind-fuck prison so you could feed on us!”

Cheerlight stared in surprise and confusion at Dusty. “What? But you weren’t—” Her ears flicked, mouth snapping shut. Then her expression turned to concern, and she took a hesitant half-step back. “So, that answers that question. She hasn’t tricked you. You really are helping her lie to these ponies.”

“Hey.” A rattle of metal rose behind me as Sickle stood. I looked back to see her grin behind the bars of her muzzle. Her rumbling voice was amused, dark and deadly. “I was there, too, you dumb cunt. You chickenshits gassed me. Wanted to kill me in my sleep. Go on. Call me a liar again.” Any sense of amusement instantly vanished, like a light being switched off. “I fucking dare you.”

Cheerlight opened her mouth to reply, but hesitated. No doubt she’d been thoroughly briefed on all of my companions and knew as well as I did that Sickle would have no qualms about killing her. Likely, she was considering whether provoking an attack would serve her purposes, and whether the other ponies here would be willing and capable of stopping Sickle in time. If she was really clever and devoted, she was putting more weight on the former.

Fortunately, I didn’t have to intervene to prevent that. Sickle took Cheerlight’s momentary silence as conceding the point. “Yeah, I thought so.” She gave a deep snort before addressing the other ponies. “And why the fuck are you dumbasses listening to this lying little bitch, anyway?”

“Good question,” Dusty said, and gestured to the nearest couple of soldiers. “Get her out of here.”

Cheerlight staggered back another step, her eyes wide in panic. “Wait!” she said, eyes desperately darting around until they locked on Hail Burst. “What about Rust?!”

The soldiers stopped, casting curious looks back towards Dusty. I tilted my head again, genuinely curious how she was going to play that one. Obviously she was going to play it off as not being her hive, which almost certainly meant blaming me, but I was interested to see her technique. It was a desperation play, a gamble, unless she had some information I wasn’t aware of. It would be better to not let her speak any more poisonous words, of course, but I was effectively powerless to affect that.

Hail Burst’s head had tilted as well, and while it was hard to judge her expression with only her mouth visible under her helmet, she was clearly suspicious.

“I said enough,” Dusty said, waving a hoof at the soldiers. “Get her—”

“Hold up,” Hail Burst said, her tone much too casual. “I think I’d like to hear this. Are you really trying to say you didn’t have anything to do with Rust?”

“Of course not!” Cheerlight said, desperate and pleading. “We were trading with Rust! We’ve gathered a huge amount of equipment and caps, more than enough to trade for some scrap metal. Why would we wipe out our own trading partners? And as for—”

Echo’s voice cut over her. “Rust could harvest and prepare at most a few hundred pounds of quality metal in a day. Judging from the repairs to the Cumulonimbus, you likely required somewhere in the neighborhood of a hundred tons of good-quality structural steel to make the vessel flight-worthy once more. As such, I would assume you concluded that a year or more was simply too long to wait, and chose to expedite the process.”

Cheerlight’s ears were laid back as Hail Burst added, “And we hit one of your scavenging groups that had just looted the place.”

“Of course we scavenged what we could!” Cheerlight said. “That’s how everyone lives in the Wasteland. But we didn’t kill anypony!” She calmed herself, presenting a more stable and reasonable persona; a gentle and shy diplomat, driven to near-panic by the impending violence she hoped to avoid. “We lost contact with our traders, and sent some scouts to investigate. They were almost there when they spotted Enclave soldiers flying in, so they hid to wait until everypony was gone.” She glanced my way again. “And wouldn’t you know it, moments later, Queen Whisper and her companions show up. I’m sure it’s purely a coincidence that they always show up to a crisis at exactly the right moment.”

Hail Burst stared for several long seconds, expression unreadable. “...Nope. Not buying it.”

Cheerlight’s expression softened. “Of all the ponies here, you know most of all what it’s like to be lied to by the ponies you should be able to trust, and to be put in conflict with those who should be your—”

“Don’t even fucking try that,” Hail Burst shot back, lips curling. “And just so you know, I don’t particularly trust Whisper. I trust what I see, and I’ve seen what your so-called Serenity has done with my own two eyes. You’re murderers and butchers. We’ve got a witness to everything you did at Rust. Hell, just yesterday you slaughtered a bunch of uninvolved ponies so you could get your hooves on a fucking megaspell. And you…” she leveled an armored hoof at Cheerlight. “You’re a slimy little lying piece of shit, and a transparent one at that. I may not trust Whisper, but at least when she gets all manipulative, she helps ponies.”

I allowed a small, soft smile. Not enough to look smug, even as much as I felt it. Just pleased, as one might expect. Maybe a little relieved. The last part wasn’t even an act.

Cheerlight’s ears had fallen flat again. “Please. I’m sure your witness saw changelings, but they weren’t our changelings. I know it’s not pleasant to think that you might have been misled again, but think—”

“I said, don’t fucking try that,” Hail Burst said. “I’m done with the scheming changeling crap.” She turned to Dusty. “Are we done with her yet?”

“Yes,” Dusty said grimly, motioning again to the soldiers.

“Wait!” Cheerlight cried out as the closest two soldiers grabbed her shoulders. “We just want to talk! Surely we can find some sort of middle-ground?”

“Hold up.” The soldiers stopped as Dusty walked slowly up to her. When he stopped, he was face-to-face with her, noses almost touching. “You want a middle-ground? Here it is: your hive surrenders, disarms, and releases every pony you’ve got imprisoned for food. That’s our middle-ground.”

Cheerlight’s focus danced between Dusty’s eyes, shifting and anxious and entirely an act. After a moment she looked past Dusty towards the other ponies. “Please, we don’t take ponies, and he knows—”

“Wrong answer,” Dusty said, cutting her off. “I was there.”

“Please!” Cheerlight called out to the others. “He’s lying! We’ve never done anything like that! These are all more of Whisper’s lies!”

Starlight had finally had enough and leaped up to her hooves. “Oh fuck off!”

Dusty snorted and waved a hoof to the guards before turning to walk away. “Get her out of here.”

“We still have the megaspell!”

Dusty stopped cold in his tracks, jaw tightening. The mood over the gathering had abruptly chilled.

“We don’t want to use it,” Cheerlight said, visibly trembling. “We don’t want to cause any more deaths than we have to, but we will defend ourselves. The analysts back home… since your army is spread out, they’ve decided the army is too hard of a target. That it wouldn’t cause enough damage. They say the best target now is the army’s industrial and logistical base. If we don’t find some way to peacefully resolve this, they’re going to use the megaspell on Mareford!”

Dusty leveled a murderous glare at her. Everyone was silent. Finally, he turned to look to Two Bits.

Two Bits caught his eyes, but looked away. For a few seconds, he simply stood there, eyes unfocused. I could practically see the mental struggle going on in his head.

Finally, he turned, his eyes locking onto Cheerlight. “Fuck you.”

“You heard him,” Dusty said, waving his hoof once more. “Get her out of here.”

The Mareford soldiers started guiding Cheerlight away, pushing her ahead despite her protests. “Don’t trust her!” she shouted. “She isn’t trying to help you! If Whisper really cared so much about you ponies, how come she only showed up two months ago?! Wait!”

“Hey!” one of the soldiers snapped, giving her another shove. “Shut it before I gag you with your own damn flag.”

Finally, her protests and verbal maneuvers ceased. She’d taken her shots. They led her away in silence.

“Well,” Dusty said, shaking his head. “Did they really think that would work?”

I looked over at Two Bits’ concerned expression, and Hail Burst’s tense stance. She might not have broken up our little army, but it remained to be seen if she’d caused any damage.

As soon as Cheerlight was out of sight, Two Bits turned to Hail Burst. “Hey. I’m not going to give in to her threat, but the safety of Mareford is still my responsibility. Can I get you to send out some scouts, so if they do try to get that megaspell to Mareford, we have a chance at stopping it? I know it’s a long shot, but we’ve got to try.”

“Of course,” Hail Burst said, giving a grim nod. “It’ll leave us a little thin on the ‘Nimbus, though. If you can spare some soldiers to give ship security, I can spare some scout flights.”

He nodded in return. “I’ll get a couple of squads together for you.”

“Deal.”

A moment of silence followed before Hail Burst turned my way. “You’re awfully quiet all of a sudden.”

I shrugged. “She made the entire conversation about me being a liar and a manipulator. There isn’t much I can say in my own defense there.” Then I put on a soft smile. “Though given my line of work, it’s refreshing to have the truth working in my favor for a change.”

She gave a mild snort as she looked away, though I caught the corner of her mouth lift. “Yeah, well, it doesn’t help that she was so full of shit you could smell it. And like I said, you might be scummy as hell at times, but at least you’ve helped ponies. That’s more than I can say for Serenity.” Another snort. “Hell, most ponies.”

I couldn’t help smiling a little more. That might have been the nicest thing Hail Burst had said to me.

She mused quietly, a thin smile slowly spreading as she looked out at where Cheerlight had disappeared from sight. “It kind of seems like they’re getting desperate, if they’re throwing a move like that.”

“I doubt it,” I said, earning a concerned frown from Hail Burst. “Remember: changeling. She could have come in with any tactic she wanted, any appearance she wanted. She chose to look weak.”

“Hmm.” She looked back again. “But why?”

I shrugged. “Hard to say. Maybe they hoped to tap into some pony empathy. Break up the army to reduce casualties. Maybe they wanted to make us overconfident. Maybe it’s a diversion, getting us to expect one thing before doing something else. Maybe it’s something we’re just not seeing. Maybe it’s a lot of things. Whatever it is, there’s a good chance our reaction to this will play into their plans.”

She grunted. “Changelings.”

“Yep.” I smiled.

“...So what was that whole ‘two month’ thing about?”

My smile vanished. There were so many ways I could answer that, all of varying degrees of honesty. The full truth was complicated and unusual enough that I really didn’t want to rely on it, especially right after being so strongly accused of deception. The temptation to tell a much more believable lie was strong, but I sighed, settling on a more abbreviated truth. “I woke up from a changeling chrysalis—a cocoon—a little over two months ago. It was my hive’s plan to survive some hard times. It… didn’t work very well. Mine was the last one. Even… even my queen, my predecessor, died.”

“Ah,” she said. “Sorry for that.” A pause. “So, your searching. Did you ever find any others?”

My smile returned. “I did. Eggs. It will be some time before they can care for themselves, but my hive will have a future… assuming any of us do.”

“And we should probably get to work on that,” Dusty said. “Whisper, I want that encryption deployed by the end of the day. It’s going to be a fight once we start moving, and I don’t want Serenity listening in on us.”

“Of course,” I said, nodding. The sensation was ever-so-slightly off, as if my sense of balance was delayed by a fraction of a second. It seemed the Mint-als were wearing off. “I think I might take that coffee now.”

☢

Half an hour later, with caffeine buzzing through my veins, I made my rounds of the army. Fatigue was becoming a factor, but this part didn’t require any significant brainpower. I could autopilot through most of it.

I still double-checked my radios. Both of them. The modified encryption program let anyone tune into multiple channels, so my PipBuck was tuned into both the command channel and the new private channel I had setup. That channel was just for us, my closest companions and me. Somewhere that we could talk without worrying at all about outsiders overhearing. Somewhere I could pass intercepted data to Dusty without anyone ever knowing.

And in the other ear, I continued to monitor Serenity radio traffic. There was still no uptick in activity. No plans being discussed, no attack imminent. No reaction at all to the apparent failure of their negotiations. Nothing.

It was enough to make me a little paranoid.

Most of the PipBucks Hail Burst had supplied went to Trotsen ponies. Sandstorm still had the one she had taken off the spy in Trotsen, so I gave her a copy of the encryption program and the key to the command network, then helped her distribute the new PipBucks to her riders. Once that was done, I took the last three to Dazzle. They would make sure that she and those impressive magical energy cannons were always within reach.

Then it was on to the Mareford Militia, and there’s where things got tedious. Way back when Mareford’s ancestors left whatever Stable they had lived in, they had brought along a great number of PipBucks. The town had several dozen of them, which meant the regular Militia could have one for every squad, plus the various levels of HQ units. I had to update every single one, and that meant flying all around our now-spread-out army.

If I’d had access to all of them in one place, I could have done the job in half an hour, tops. Instead, it was nearing evening as I wearily returned from my rounds. The caffeine had long since faded, leaving me feeling heavy, dull, and with a strangely acidic feeling in my stomach.

It irrationally irritated me that Echo showed absolutely no sign of fatigue as she flew close beside me. I knew the precise psychological leaps that led to those feelings, somewhere between envy and a selfish desire for special consideration by the universe. I was just feeling too worn-out to really care. Fortunately, I was also feeling too worn-out to make a fool of myself by acting on it. I just wanted to finally be done with it.

Dusty was back at the army HQ, with our motorwagon parked close by. Sickle was nearby, too, kicked back and lazily chatting with a cluster of Trotsen ponies. As I landed, I could tell from her slow and slightly slurred speech that she’d had plenty of booze, and probably some other drugs, too. Her lewd sprawl also made it plainly obvious to all that she’d had sex with at least one stallion while I was flying all around the army.

The knowledge of this irritated me. This in turn led to the strange recognition that it irritated me that this irritated me so much. I needed sleep.

Only a few ponies were in the headquarters. Dusty was comparing his PipBuck’s map to the large one on the table, while Starlight sat nearby, head bobbing slowly to the music playing in her earbuds. A couple of Mareford Militia ponies were going over some papers of their own, but remaining close by in case Dusty needed them.

Dusty looked up from the maps. “Hey. You finished your rounds?”

“I’ve gotten Trotsen, Gemstone, the Militia, and the Rangers,” I said with a weary nod. “I even caught up with the whirligigs. I’m going up to the Cumulonimbus next to update the Loyalists. I wanted to stop and check in with you first. I’m thinking of staying up in the cloudship. The hills limit radio reception, and I’d like to be able to monitor the whole network.”

I inclined my head slightly, my great horn tipping towards the two Militia ponies, who were still preoccupied by their own work.

Dusty nodded knowingly. “Of course. Let me know if you hear anything interesting that isn’t filtering up.” He understood perfectly.

“Aww,” Starlight said, pulling out one of her earbuds. “You’re bailing on us? But I like having you around.”

So many conflicting thoughts and emotions stirred at that comment, all urged on by the feeling of affection I was sensing from her. “And I’d love to stay around,” I said, putting on a soft smile that really didn’t convey the complex and sleep-deprived feelings rioting around in my head. “But I probably wouldn’t be much good for company. I’ve got a lot of work to do.”

She gave an overacted groan. “Fiiine. How long are you staying up there?”

“Not long. It’ll only be a few days until the army reaches Serenity.” I lifted my PipBuck. “And we’ve got the private channel if we want to chat.”

Dusty gave an amused snort. “I swear, if you two start getting all lovey-dovey on the radio, I’m confiscating your broadcasters.”

Starlight stuck her tongue out at him.

I couldn’t come up with any appropriate response, so I simply moved on. “Anyway, I need to get on that. I still need to get the Loyalists on the new net, and I don’t even know if I need to tweak the program to get it to work on the spell matrix in those armors.”

“Well, good luck with that,” Dusty said. “Stay out of trouble.”

Echo quietly snorted, but said nothing.

“See you later,” Starlight said, giving a lopsided smile that nicely summed up the mixed feelings.

I lingered as my fatigued mind conjured up some very compelling arguments in support of me staying right there, but I reluctantly pushed those thoughts aside. Duty first, especially when hundreds of lives and the future of my hive was at stake. I reminded my tired mind that it was a very temporary and short-term arrangement. I don’t think it listened.

It was a short flight to the Cumulonimbus, which was making a slow orbit over the heart of the army. A call on their unencrypted frequency announced my presence, and a pair of armored soldiers met Echo and myself at the ruined hangar once more. The halls of the ship were still a maze to me, but I was starting to recognize a few intersections.

We were led to the C.I.C. once again. The space was a little more well-lit than last time, and a few more pegasi were at the consoles. The large screen at the front wall was currently showing a map, much like a PipBuck’s. The Cumulonimbus was right in the middle, with several other marks denoting both friendly and suspected enemy positions.

Hail Burst looked over to us and nodded. “Welcome aboard. This is about the encryption?”

“It is,” I said, mirroring her nod. “I need to distribute the encryption spell and the appropriate keys to every Loyalist armor. How would you like to do this?”

“We can handle the distribution,” she said. “Give me a copy of them. I will see that they’re properly distributed.”

I frowned slightly. I didn’t like the idea of letting that information slip out of my control, but neither could I blame her for wanting to take charge of her own forces security. “Very well. There is one possible complication, though. I don’t know the specifics of the pegasus power armor’s spell matrix. I’ll need to examine one to see if the spell needs to be modified for you.”

Hail Burst paused for a moment, a small frown crossing her muzzle for just a moment before she nodded. “Very well. You can hook up to my armor.” She turned her head, awkwardly nipping at the back of her shoulder until a panel popped open, revealing a cable port.

I promptly got to work, and was pleased to see that the power armor’s systems were based on Stable-Tec computers. Better yet, while both Serenity and the Enclave appeared to have made minor post-war modifications to the spell matrices, a good half-hour of examination found that none of the encryption spell’s functionality depended on those modifications. It should work just fine.

With that out of the way, and a copy of the spell and a list of Loyalist encryption keys delivered, I moved on to the next topic. “I hope it isn’t imposing, but I was wondering if I could ask a favor.”

With her helmet off, I could see the raised eyebrow that question brought, and didn’t wait for her to vocalize the question. “Dusty wanted me to monitor all our radio traffic, in hopes I might be able to improve situational awareness. The hills give some interference, so we were hoping you might have room for me somewhere. Preferably some place that won’t block out radio signals.”

She sighed. “Sure, why not? We’re a flying hotel at this point, anyway. There’s another room next to where we stuck that… energetic griffin. You can quarter there. The guards will show you the way. I assume you have your own radio equipment?”

“I do.”

“Good. Then we’ll find you a good place for you to set up in the morning.”

“Thank you.”

Echo cut in. “I have another request.”

This time, I mirrored Hail Burst’s raised eyebrow.

“What is it?” Hail Burst asked.

“We have a suit of damaged pegasus power armor,” Echo said. “It is mostly in good condition, but some parts are irreparably damaged and will require replacements before it will function. I would like to request the spare parts necessary to effect those repairs.” Her eyes turned to me, while her head remained fixed forward. “If Whisper is going to insist on putting herself in danger, we should at least ensure she has adequate protection.”

I sighed; I had no desire to be stuck in some power armor, and I didn’t particularly like the insult it might cause among our pegasus allies to be wearing what was essentially their uniform.

Hail Burst hesitated, frowning, but eventually replied. “I can not permit the distribution of Enclave military equipment to non-Enclave personnel—”

Echo’s mane stirred on an intangible breeze, wings rising at her side, voice sharp. “Given Whisper’s importance to our future, and all that we have done for you, it seems the least you can do to show appreciation for our great effort is—”

“But!” Hail Burst snapped, eyes narrowing to glare. “Given that we’ve captured several suits of Serenity’s power armor, we may be able to find the parts you need from the salvaged enemy equipment.” She took a step toward the alicorn. “Unless you’d like to continue objecting to my extremely generous and questionably legal compromise?”

Echo’s wings returned to her sides, her mane settling. “No. That should suffice quite nicely.”

“Sorry,” I said, giving Hail Burst a tired smile. “We’re still working on teaching her the finer details of social interaction.” I then turned to Echo. “The proper response to someone granting you a favor is to express gratitude.”

Echo’s head tilted ever so slightly. “I had thought that was implied by my statement.”

I sighed again. “Say ‘thank you’.”

She frowned, and after a moment turned to regard Hail Burst formally. “I appreciate your cooperation in this endeavor.”

“Close enough. I guess.”

Hail Burst eyed Echo before turning a smirk toward me. “A stuck-up alicorn learning social skills from you. Celestia help us all.”

Echo’s wings rose again. “I will have you know that Queen Whisper is an excellent teacher and does not deserve such ridiculous scorn!”

“Relax,” I said. “Maybe the next lesson should be on general banter and friendly ribbing. Or maybe just tact.”

“Mmm,” Echo said, pausing thoughtfully, and nodded. “If you think that best, then it sounds like an excellent course of study.”

Hail Burst snorted out a barely restrained laugh, then shook her head. “Yeahhh, okay. Back on-topic, get us a list of parts that you need, and we’ll see what we can do. We might be able to spare a technician if you need any help.”

“I will not,” Echo replied quite primly, her nose lifting a little higher. “We remember a great deal of arcanotech engineering. Repairing the armor should be trivial, given the correct parts.” She turned her head to regard me. “Given that you are in the heart of a Raptor-class cloudship, do you suppose you will be able to refrain from getting yourself killed without me for a few minutes?”

I gave a wry smile. “Yes, I do believe I can manage that.”

Echo frowned. “Hmm. I would prefer more certainty, but I suppose that shall suffice. I will retrieve our salvaged power armor and return shortly.”

With a flash, she was gone.

“Well she’s even more charming than I remember,” Hail Burst said.

“Believe it or not, this is progress,” I said. I mean, she didn’t even mention genocide once. “She’s still new to this. She hadn’t had any proper social interaction prior to about a week ago. Kind of.” I frowned. “She’s complicated.”

With the encryption delivered, we parted ways. The escort guided me through the maze of dim and damaged corridors to my temporary quarters. We had almost arrived when I heard a faint pop. I might not have even noticed if I hadn’t heard it again, a few seconds later and slightly louder. Then again, and again, rapidly drawing closer.

I stopped at an intersection of hallways just as a dazzling purple flash appeared right before me, signaling Echo’s return. “There you are!” she said, turning to face me. The damaged set of pegasus power armor floated behind her as she glared at me. The look lost most of its impact when both of us were ducking under the low ceiling. “I leave you for hardly a minute and you’re already trying to get lost.”

“I’m being escorted by a pair of Loyalist soldiers in their own ship,” I noted, leveling my best flat glare. “I am hardly in danger of anything, least of all getting lost.”

She blinked, then shook her head. “Well. I suppose that is technically true, but I can hardly protect you if you run off without letting me know where you are going.”

“Echo, any soldier on this ship could have told you where I was, and you can always call me on the radio.” I lifted my PipBuck for emphasis before setting it down and fixing her with a hard stare. “And this overprotective thing is getting extremely old.”

“You tried to blow yourself up with a megaspell,” she countered, horn tapping the ceiling as she tried to stand a little taller. “I hardly think I am overreacting.”

“You’re being overbearing and rude,” I said, not relenting. Irritation was growing in my fatigued mind, despite attempts to quash it. “I have no problem with you playing bodyguard and trying to protect me, but the more obnoxious and overly critical you are about it, the more I want to just get away from you.”

Her eyes went wide, head drawing back as if I had slapped her. It resulted in her banging the back of her head against a low-hanging pipe, but she didn’t even seem to notice; the only pain evident in her expression was in response to my words.

I groaned, a hoof rising to my face, and spoke before she could come up with the words to reply. “I’m not saying I hate you, Echo. It’s nothing like that. It’s…” I lowered my hoof again. “Do you remember our first talk?”

The growing look of shock and outrage were immediately wiped away by a thoughtful expression as she thought back. “Yes? To which part are you referring? We discussed several subjects.”

“The part about how you present things,” I said, mellowing my tone as much as possible. “Being demanding and overbearing will drive ponies away, even if you’re trying to act in their best interests. It’s counterproductive to your goals. Not to mention, it’s just plain rude.”

She had frowned, and it took several seconds before she replied. “I had expected that you, at least, would not have been as susceptible to such an emotional reaction.”

“I’m exhausted,” I said. “And it’s not as if you restrict this behavior only to me. I think you would have a lot more success if you didn’t act quite so… condescending towards others.”

She continued to frown thoughtfully for another few seconds before giving a slow nod. “I see. That will be difficult, given the great disparity in power and capability, but… I shall try.”

“Good,” I said, choosing to ignore the low-key condescension for the sake of my own sanity. I even reached up to give her a friendly pat on the shoulder, which merely produced a confused look at the offending hoof. Then, remembering the skeptical-looking soldiers, turned to give them a smile. “Which way?”

The closest soldier snapped out of it immediately. “That room, right there,” she said with a raised hoof.

“Thank you,” I said with a smile, and entered my new quarters, with Echo following close behind. It was a decent enough space. It probably even counted as roomy by warship standards, with the tiny desk, one chair, a locker, and single bunk-bed. I had just removed my saddlebags and was considering the regular-pony-sized bed when a familiar high-pitched voice came from the open doorway.

“Oh, hey,” Bloodbeak said, peeking her head in. “I thought I heard you over here.”

“Hello again,” I said, flashing another smile. “Looks like I’ll be quartered here in the Cumulonimbus for a few days.”

“Cool,” she said, casually strolling in. The room was getting very cramped.

Echo sat down the armor. “I am going to find Hail Burst to get those parts she promised.”

“Please try to be nice about it,” I said. “Please and thank you and all that.”

“Of course,” Echo replied primly, and slipped out the door.

Bloodbeak blinked after her, then flashed a wry smile at me. “She’s funny. You fixing up this armor?”

“She is. She thinks I need more protection.”

“Huh. Neat.” She paused, letting out a long, loud yawn that I struggled to not echo.

“Tired, huh?” I said, stating the obvious in a way to open up further conversation.

She cracked a smile again. “I’ve been running around this ship for hours. Even I have to run out of energy eventually!” She chuckled as she turned and flopped back in the chair—then hissed, grabbing at her side where she had been injured. “Oww, crap! Why do I keep doing that?” She was already chuckling again by the end of the sentence. At least she didn’t seem to be in much pain.

“Is that still giving you trouble?”

“Only when I’m being stupid,” she said, beaming, though she steadily slid down to slouch in the chair. She looked every bit as tired as I felt. “So it looks like we’re neighbors for a bit. Does that mean we get to hang out?”

I looked at my saddlebags, sitting beside the bunk-bed with the vital PipBucks nestled inside. I’m pretty sure I lingered just a little too long, long enough that Bloodbeak had surely noticed my hesitation. I quickly spoke up before she could consider it. “Sure. I’m going to be pretty busy over the next few days, but I’m sure I’ll have free time.” Or at least, I could manage a bit of socializing with the radios playing in my ear.

Bloodbeak smiled. “Cool. I mean, I’m inside this super-awesome flying ship from the ancient past, going to fight some super-secret underground baddies. It’d just be all sorts of wrong if I was bored in the middle of all this.”

I chuckled. “Well, we can’t have that.” Still, I was eying the too-small bed. I called up my magic, stripping away my regal disguise, and sat on the cot with a soft groan. “But I think that’s going to have to wait. I’m exhausted.”

Of course, what I wanted to do was listen in on the radio. Serenity was still quiet. Not silent, mind you. There was still the regular chatter, but it was all suspiciously uneventful.

“Hah, I hear you there,” Bloodbeak said, lifting a hand to cover another, smaller yawn. “Catch you for breakfast, then? Oh, hey, then you can tell me what happened with all that shooting earlier!”

“Hmm? You didn’t see what happened?” I looked over at the wall. “I guess warships don’t have much in the way of windows.”

“Yeah, these pegasi just got all all super-serious and told me to stay in my room. It was dumb and boring.” She paused, giving a weak, uneven smile. “Uh, maybe a little unnerving, too.”

I grunted and frowned. “I can imagine. Hearing the fight and not having any idea of what’s happening…”

“Still kinda silly,” she said, and with a huff, hauled herself back up to her feet. “I mean, this is probably the safest place in the whole army. Just, you know… a window would be nice.”

“How about I talk to Hail Burst in the morning?” I said. “Maybe we can arrange something that doesn’t have us stuck in some dark hole the whole time.”

She grinned. “Hey, thanks. Well, I think I’ll go turn in.” She was just exiting the door when she stopped. “Hey, uh, Whisper?”

I had laid back, sinking into the thin cushion of the bunk. “Yes?”

“It’s just…” She turned, looking to me with a softly concerned expression. “Well, I remember when we met, you were talking about finding your family, and, well…” her gaze wavered awkwardly. “Is this your family?”

I shook my head. “No. This is a different hive.”

“Ah,” she said, a bit of a smile returning for just a moment, before she spoke again. “So… did you ever find them?”

I smiled. “Yes. I found them.”

Her smile returned, soft and warm. She didn’t say anything. She just smiled, and nodded, and then she slipped out of the room.

I floated my bags over, depositing them close by my side so the earbuds’ wires weren’t too tight, and curled up in a thin cot made luxurious by way of fatigue.

The radio crackled occasionally with distant conversations. Echo returned with several parts, quietly tinkering with the armor. None of it mattered to me. I wrapped the blankets snugly around me, nestled my head into the inviting pillow, and I settled in to finally get some much-deserved sleep.

Chapter Forty Three: Close Quarters

Dreams are a strange territory. Many have spent careers trying to find the meanings behind the strange and convoluted paths they might take. Entire fields of psychology and philosophy have been guided by such pursuits.

Fortunately, Infiltrators are taught far more practical psychology, based on study and statistics rather than pure speculation and tenuous correlation. Sure, there’s the occasional prophetic dreamer or invasive dreamform, but those are distinct magical phenomena, not the normal product of a typical subconscious mind. Normal dreams typically mean nothing more than that a thought happened to come to mind, whether it’s some long-held fear about getting stuck in an alien form, a recent interest in a particular brand of snack cake, or some casual thought or memory. Defeating a giant ambulatory blueberry waffle by eating it is less likely to be a deep-seated issue with your parents or repressed sexual fantasy, and more likely to simply mean you’re about to wake up hungry.

I am glad to have been taught this way, because trying to decipher the metaphor behind the neon-green cybernetic male alicorn griffin in custom power armor could take months, fill a thesis paper, and possibly lead to eventual insanity.

As is, I only even remember that one detail, out of the rest of what must have been a supremely strange dream, because he teleported to my left side and buzzed, in his electronic yet clearly feminine voice, “Target in sight.”

The rest of the dream was lost to the volatility of short-term memory as my slowly-stirring conscious mind latched onto those words. More words followed as I became aware of waking up. “One is taking lead.” Other voices overlapped, the calm urgency piercing all the way to my consciousness. Some were distorted, but the two I had made out were crystal clear. Not a single artifact. Close.

My heart was pounding as I jerked awake, adrenaline already burning in my veins. My eyes opened to a dimly lit room, with Echo lying curled neatly beside the bulk of the power armor she had been working on. I quickly snatched at my saddlebags and the networked PipBucks within, nearly falling out of bed in my haste.

All the voices were filling my left ear. The right was silent.

Echo made some soft sound, but I ignored her. My attention went first to the PipBuck monitoring the Serenity channels. The voices were coming in on multiple channels, and I caught snippets of formation, maneuver, and enemy sightings. Channels blinked out and flashed to life as information spread rapidly through the Serenity chain of command.

I quickly switched to my own PipBuck, confirmed that I was set to the private channel, and hit transmit. “Dusty, are you awake?” Echo grunted and stirred at the noise, but no reply came over the radio. “Dusty!”

The soft, alien sound of magical energy weapons barely reached my ears through the thick walls. My ears shot up, head snapping around. A dozen red marks filled my E.F.S. I switched to the command channel, nearly shouting as I broadcast a warning. “The Cumulonimbus is under attack!”

More shots sounded as the entire world leaped into action. Dusty’s groggy voice came across the radio, asking, “What’s going on?” just as a klaxon sounded, and the cloudship twitched beneath me, banking into a turn.

Hail Burst’s voice answered. “The Cumulonimbus is being boarded. Enemy strength is at least a platoon, likely more. I’m getting word of enemy fliers spotted approaching the army from west and southwest—”

The radio squawked with electrical interference, the dim light by the door flickering for a moment. Hail Burst’s voice returned, a little harsher than before. “Be advised, we are now on internal defense and can not provide air support. Enemy is using matrix disruption grenades. We may lose communications.”

Echo was wide awake as the sound of distant but rapidly growing combat echoed through the ship. “What is going on?”

“We’re being boarded,” I said, scrambling out of the bed.

“What?” she blurted, eyes widening. “They dare!”

Dusty spoke across the radio. “Understood. Do you require assistance?”

“Negative,” Hail Burst replied. “Too many hostile fliers, and we can’t give air defense. Those whirligigs would get torn apart. We’ll hold or take as many of these bastards down with us as possible.”

“Don’t get killed!” Dusty said. “We need you ponies a lot more than we need your ship!”

The voices from the Serenity force were coming quicker and louder, overlapping each other with the frantic calls of combat. I pulled out the relevant PipBuck, switching around to find the right channel.

Echo stood tall, her mane flared and blowing as if her power was coursing directly through it. “Whisper! We are leaving!”

“No we’re not!” I said, still switching channels. “We’re safe for now, and you can teleport us out if it gets dangerous. Now be quiet, I need to work!”

“But—” Her mouth snapped shut, followed by an aggravated growl. “Fine! But we are leaving the moment I think you are in danger!”

Another distant explosion rattled the locker behind me, and I found an active Serenity channel. “—partment one is breached, light resistance. I’m seeing lots of contacts moving now.”

“Understood. Get to defensive positions and get ready to push. Just like we practiced.”

I quickly checked my notes, comparing the channel numbers. If my earlier information was correct, and they hadn’t changed anything, this was platoon-level traffic in the first platoon, Alpha company. I bumped it up a channel, listening to company-level communications. It was only a few seconds before I was rewarded. “Command, One. Hoofhold secure. Minimal resistance, we should be able to take the second line before things bog down.”

“Copy,” the reply came, just as clear as the others; the company headquarters was nearby. “Proceed. Two, hustle aft and get that breach going. Push hard before they can relocate.”

Crap. I hit transmit again. “Hail Burst, someone spotted a bunch of changelings going toward the rear of the ship, and they might have explosives. They may be trying to breach there.”

“Shit,” she replied, then, “Understood.”

I was already switching to the private channel. “Dusty, I’m pretty sure we’ve got an entire company hitting the ‘Nimbus.”

There was a pause, possibly as he switched channels to reply. “Copy that. They’re launching an offensive across the entire western edge of the army. If it starts getting bad up there, you get the hell out.”

“I will,” I said, and switched back to the command net.

“An entire company,” Echo darkly intoned. “I would say it has already gotten quite bad.”

I slowly turned my head, watching all of the contact markers moving around, both friendly and enemy. “It’s not bad until Serenity gets close. It’ll only take a second for you to teleport us.”

She grumbled, turning to focus once more on the door.

I noticed one non-hostile mark moving relatively quickly to our door, just before the latch moved. “And don’t kill Bloodbeak, please.”

The door opened to reveal the griffin in question, her rifle slung around her neck as she peered in. “Hey! I think there’s a fight going on!”

“We noticed,” I said, quickly waving a hoof for her to enter before transmitting again. “Hail Burst, this is Whisper. What do you want us doing?”

Bloodbeak slipped in, shutting the door behind her, while I waited for Hail Burst’s reply. It came a few seconds later. “Whisper, monitor channel eight-nine for internal defense, but don’t get in their way.”

“Understood.” A moment later, I was on the new channel. “This is Queen Whisper and company joining this channel. Anything we should know?”

A stallion’s voice immediately replied. “Welcome to the party, Whisper. This is Bastion. What’s your location?”

“Echo, Bloodbeak, and I are all in my quarters.”

“Copy that. Intruders on that deck have pushed halfway to your position, but we’ve halted them. You’re good for now, but be ready to move.”

“I understand. We’ll be ready.”

Another explosion shook the floor. It was almost as if they didn’t care about the state of the ship.

“This is a bad decision,” Echo growled, horn glowing as she glared at the door. “You’re not contributing to the defense, so there is no reason for you to remain.”

“My job hasn’t changed,” I said, not wanting to elaborate more with someone else listening in. “And I’m not bailing on these ponies. We’re staying until Serenity starts overtaking us or the order is given to abandon ship.”

Bloodbeak started. “What? You don’t think they’ll do that, will they?”

“Serenity outnumbers us up here,” I said. “Probably two-to-one or more. On the other hoof, the Loyalists have great defensive positions. I could see it going either way.”

Another Serenity transmission caught my ear, and I quickly singled it out as platoon-level traffic in the second platoon. “Charge set. Pull back. Call when clear.”

While the squads rapidly called out in reply, Bloodbeak sat, shifting her rifle to point roughly at the door. “So, uh, what’re we doing?”

In my ear, some changeling called out “Fire in the hole!” three times. The sound that followed wasn’t the deafening, ship-rattling explosion I had expected. It was a distant, dull thump, as if someone had dropped something on the deck. “Go, go, go!”

“We’re sitting tight here,” I said, even as my heart beat harder. Hostile contact markers were all around. Some must have been Serenity soldiers flying around outside the ship. It made it hard to tell where the boarders were. “I’m on the radio with the Loyalists. If we need to move, they’ll let us know.”

“Oh,” she said, clearly nervous. “Okay.”

My right earbud crackled loudly with a new voice. “Intruders breaching in engineering! At least a squad of power armor. We do not control the compartment.”

“Five, are you in position?”

“Almost. Deck one is clear back to engineering. Still moving up on deck two.”

Left ear, again. “Engineering secure! Enemy forces seen withdrawing into deck three and four main passages.”

As I listened to the rapidly escalating combat, Echo snorted and jerked her head toward the power armor. “Whisper, you should get in the armor. I have not yet completed the repairs, but it will still provide protection.”

I glanced at the armor, grimaced, and shook my head. “Not a good time to learn how to use power armor,” I said. “Besides, I don’t want to look like a Serenity soldier. The Loyalists are expecting me to look like a queen.”

On that note, I focused my magic, pouring it into retaking my regal disguise.

“Great,” Echo grumbled. “Now you’ve made yourself an even bigger target.”

I ignored her, focusing on the radios. Calls were coming out quickly from both sides, and I looked over the local map on my PipBuck, painting a mental picture of the battlefield. The changelings at the front of the ship, the first platoon, were probing the defenses, but several Loyalist and two Militia squads were fighting them off. The second platoon, in the rear, was pushing hard on all decks. They were trying to keep up the momentum, but my warning had cost them the element of surprise, and the Loyalists were slowing them down.

Slowing, but concerningly, not stopping.

Bloodbeak fidgeted with her rifle, checking the chamber before resuming her aim at the door. “How the heck did they sneak up on a cloudship? It’s in the middle of the sky!”

Several distant explosions echoed through the ship, and the light flickered in time to several high-pitched discharges. More matrix disruption grenades.

Without looking up from my screens, I tapped a hoof to my chest. “Black chitin and black armor, at night, under a fully overcast sky. Changelings are about as well-adapted to nighttime operations as you can get, even without our shapeshifting.”

The weapon fire had intensified, ringing through the corridors. Several loud radio calls indicated Serenity’s first platoon had launched a hard push on all defensive positions. Neither side seemed to know how well it was going.

“Or someone was sleeping at their post,” Bloodbeak grumbled. “I know guard duty gets boring, but still…”

One of the Loyalist units had fallen silent. Bastion was giving orders to another. “Three, pull back to the next stairwell. Four isn’t responding. I need you to get a few ponies down there to secure the starboard passage, deck four.”

On Serenity’s side, a squad leader was reporting. “We’ve broken through on deck four. No more resistance. We’re pushing up to secure stairwell S-two.”

I double-checked the map. We were on deck three, and if my guess was correct, that stairwell was just down the corridor and around the corner. The swarm of hostile contacts swirling around made it impossible to tell who was where.

Ten seconds later I heard the rapid discharging of magical energy weapons as Loyalist and Serenity forces clashed. Radio calls reported the contact.

Seconds ticked by, turning to minutes. The defenders on deck three and four had been pushed back from engineering, but had regrouped and were now holding the line. Neither side seemed to have a good picture of how the fight was going in the aft of deck two. Explosions rattled the ship, quickly reported as being on deck one, near the bow. Three reported making contact with survivors from Four. Moments later they reported being fired on by those same survivors. The Militia squad leader gave a rushed report of being overrun and fell silent.

How long had the fighting been going on? Ten minutes? Twenty?

I checked my PipBuck’s clock. Six.

“Queen Whisper.” Bastion’s voice was firm and controlled in the midst of the chaos. “Do you know the way to the sick bay?”

I keyed in. “I can find my way.”

“Good. Move there now. That’s our fallback. Say when you arrive.”

“We’re on the way.”

Echo’s glanced to me. “We’re what now?” Apparently she hadn’t switched to listen to the new channel.

“Going to the sick bay,” I said as I slid the networked PipBucks back into my bag, then turned back to my own. I took a moment to double-check the local map, then rose to my hooves. My rifle floated beside me. “Okay. Follow me.”

I opened the door, the sound of weapon fire suddenly much louder. Close. I peeked out the door, looking down the corridor. Vacant. I could make out two, maybe three magical energy weapons firing in that direction, all in slow, steady bursts. Suppression fire, I assumed. Far enough away that I didn’t see any flashes. Close enough to be terrifyingly loud. Somepony shouted directions, though I couldn’t make out his words.

Echo remained close on my flank as I led the way, with the power armor floating along right behind her. I trotted to the closest junction, well away from the fighting, and took the dim corridor. The air shook with a nearby explosion, and the volume of fire surged. A changeling on the Serenity channel was reporting an enemy counterattack, though I didn’t catch where. Bastion was loud in my other ear, giving quick updates to various squads. I don’t remember all the details now, just the general gist of the commands: collapse and consolidate. They were losing ground.

A couple more turns and a short set of stairs later, we reached the sickbay. I rushed in first, immediately greeted by a pair of pegasi. “Holy shit!” the first one shouted, snatching up a tray in his bandaged hooves before taking to the air, while the other pony scrambled back to put her empty bed between us.

“Easy,” I said. Neither were armed or armored, and a quick glance at my E.F.S. suggested they were non-hostile. I floated my rifle back to my side, the barrel pointing straight up. “We’re on your side.”

Echo and Bloodbeak had entered behind me, shutting the door, the sound of combat abruptly muffled. The stallion paused, looking over us before something like recognition flashed in his eyes. He still held the tray defensively, hovering in place. “What’s going on out there?”

I glanced to his leg, noting the lack of PipBuck. Without power armor, he was entirely out of contact. “We’ve been boarded,” I said, advancing into the room to get away from the door, and took in the surroundings. There were about a dozen ponies still in beds, and only a few were awake. Several carts of medical equipment were parked by various beds, cluttering up the room, but also offering some degree of cover. Then again, the carts were probably made of thin sheet metal, and might not stop anything more energetic than fragments and thrown rocks.

Behind me, Bloodbeak moved to what seemed to be a nurse’s station, with a metal desk that looked a bit more promising. She used the desk to brace her rifle, covering the door. Echo, meanwhile, set the power armor down just before the closest medical bed, and strode lazily into the center of the room.

I looked back to the pegasus stallion, still holding his tray. “Bastion told us to fall back here.”

Which reminded me of his request. I lifted my PipBuck. “Bastion, this is Whisper. We’re in sickbay.”

“Copy,” he said. “Hold tight. All forces! Final positions are C.I.C., sickbay, and corridors between on decks two and three. Peel back now. Two, how strong are you?”

“We’re all up. Six strong.”

“Good. Once we’ve consolidated, you’ll be lifting the wounded out.”

My ears flicked back. The implication was clear: we were going to lose.

The pegasus mare had emerged from behind her bed. Her wing was wrapped in bandages. “We need to get into the fight!”

I looked up from my PipBuck. “Do you have any weapons?”

“No, but the armory is nearby.”

I looked back to my map. “Is that the room one deck down and about three rooms forward?”

“Yeah.” She had started to trot forward, but halted; I wasn’t exactly blocking the way, but she’d have to get close to slip by, and seemed reluctant to do so.

“That location has already been overrun,” I said. Or at least, it was right on the front-line and about to be abandoned, but the fine details didn’t matter right then. “Everyone is falling back here.”

I saw her eyes widen a hair, recognizing the meaning of what I said. She immediately shook it off. “Fuck that. I’m taking this armor, then.”

“That is not yours!” Echo snapped, eyes narrowing. Then, more reasonably, “And besides, it is not yet fully functional.”

“Oh for fuck’s sake!” the mare snapped.

A soft thump almost escaped my attention, only to be followed by an urgent broadcast from Hail Burst. “Breach! Port-side access! We have more intruders!”

I looked at my map. If I was reading it right, the port-side access was right alongside us, one deck down. Between the relocation and local conversations, I’d missed any communications planning that move.

The pegasus stallion had finally set down the tray and flew over to us. “Look, we’re not staying here—”

I held up a hoof, cutting him off, then moving the hoof to my ear to signal the reason for my action: there were more radio calls. “Intruders, port-side corridor, deck three! Three is cut off!”

“Two is in contact. We’re pinned down!”

“There’s a fuckton of bugs on the port side. C.I.C., they’re moving your way!”

“Five, I need you at the C.I.C. as quick as you can. One, support Two. I need you breaking through to the sickbay and extracting the wounded.

A burst of weapon fire made everyone in the room flinch. It wasn’t outside, but it was close.

Echo raised her head, declaring, “It is time to leave.”

“One second,” I said, and hit the transmit button again. “Bastion, this is Whisper. Echo can teleport the wounded out.”

“Do it,” Bastion replied. “Evac everyone in the compartment. Call when clear. We’ll keep the bugs off of you.”

I gave a quick look around the room, making a count. Two conscious and mobile. Five in varying degrees of consciousness but not mobile. Seven unconscious, likely sedated. I turned to Echo. “Okay, I need you to start teleporting these ponies out. Get them to safety. Bloodbeak and I will keep guard here until the last ‘port out.”

“No,” she said, head held high and expression firm. “You will leave now. Staying is—”

“We don’t have time to argue this,” I said, and pointed a hoof at the nearest bed-bound pony. “Dusty isn’t here, so I’m taking charge. Get them out.” With that, I turned, trotting over to Bloodbeak at the nurse’s station.

Behind me, I heard an aggravated growl from Echo, followed by a pop and flash of purple. Taking cover behind the desk and readying my rifle, I saw she had taken the two mobile pegasi and two of the bed-bound ponies. Four trips, then.

“Well,” Bloodbeak said as I crouched beside her, giving a lopsided and insincere grin. “This is fun.”

Several more burst of magical weapon fire echoed through the ship, followed by a pair of explosions that made the lights flicker.

I had my sights lined up on the door. “You know these rifles aren’t going to do anything against power armor.”

Her grin slipped away. “Ah. Yeah. That’s a little less fun.”

Hostile marks were moving all around, too many to localize. Rapid radio calls came on both sides of the fight. The Loyalist “Two” unit was heavily engaged and taking casualties. A Serenity squad leader reported that they were assaulting the C.I.C.

A purple flash announced Echo’s return. Thirty, maybe forty seconds had passed. Four of the beds glowed purple, floating up from the deck to surround her, and with another flash, they were gone.

Bloodbeak glanced my way. “Don’t suppose you have anything harder-hitting tucked away in those bags? Like a missile launcher or something?”

My mind immediately flashed to the explosive charge. I’d have to dig it out, wire a blasting cap, set it, set the detonator, get it outside the room… “Nothing I could use in time. We’ll be gone in a minute.”

Hail Burst’s voice sounded in my ear. “C.I.C. is lost. Five, we’re coming to you by that starboard stairwell, thirty seconds.”

“Understood. We’re in heavy contact. Will try to hold for you.”

A series of hostile-contact markers abruptly swung by on our left. Some Serenity soldiers had passed by, probably just below us, or maybe in the corridor just outside. More were following after them. The sound of combat hammered through the walls in all directions.

Another flash and pop. Echo snatched up four more beds. Then she was gone again.

The cluster of moving marks I had noted didn’t move past us. They came to a stop, just a few degrees left of the door. I snugged the stock of the rifle against my shoulder, eying down the sights as best I could. My voice came out in a quiet, low growl. “I think they’re just outside the—”

The sharp, rapid blasts cut me off, bits of molten metal flying from the joints of the door in flashes of orange and pink. I flinched back, then steeled myself. Adrenaline burned in my veins. The shooting stopped. There was a metal-on-metal crash, the door flying across the room with a power-armored buck. I focused down my sights, ready to engage S.A.T.S. at the first hint of movement. I couldn’t penetrate power armor; I just needed to delay them for a few seconds.

Movement. I hit S.A.T.S. The world seemed to sharpen as I followed the motion. The sights aligned with smooth ease. Rear aperture. Front post. Grenade.

My heart lurched. I lunged to the side, hooking a foreleg around Bloodbeak and bearing her down to the ground. We collapsed in a heap behind the desk, my head buried against the floof of her neck, a foreleg shielding my head and other ear.

I heard the muffled clatter of the grenade, the crash of something falling over, and then the hammer came crashing down on us. I reeled, gasping to regain my breath as I rolled off of Bloodbeak. Hostile marks were already in the room. At least three or four of them. S.A.T.S. was down. The air was thick with haze, dim from the blown-out lights. I could barely hear the stomp of metal hooves and the crash of a medical cart being knocked over past the pounding in my head.

Bloodbeak rolled her head—maybe moaned something, I couldn’t tell—and I quickly placed a hoof on her beak. I pushed against the nearby wall with a hindhoof to push me more tightly against the desk, hiding us as best I could.

I turned my head again, trying to pick out the contacts that were in the room from those further away. Most moved quickly through the ward. More equipment was knocked aside, clattering loudly, and hopefully hiding my rapid breathing.

One had not continued on. That contact moved slowly. I heard the armored hoof-steps, drawing closer to the desk. I brought my rifle up, close to my chest and aimed at the corner of the desk, then dug in my pack for a grenade; I didn’t know if it would kill someone in pegasus power armor, but it might delay them for a few vital seconds.

How much longer?

The mark continued to move. I aimed my rifle at about face-height. Maybe their muzzle wasn’t covered. Maybe the eye lenses were weak points. I had to hope.

I found the grenade and pulled it free. A twist of magic pulled the pin, and I flung it over the desk, hoping I wasn’t about to kill any ponies who might have survived the first grenade.

The response was a startled gasp of breath, followed by a loud shout. “Grenade!” Armored hooves clattered and banged, and the hammering blast of the grenade bucked me in the chest. As the world settled again, I grabbed for the next grenade. I’d just gotten ahold of it when the space lit up in eye-searing red and pinks, bolts of magical weapon fire peppering the wall behind me. Several parts of the desk flared brightly, some disintegrating.

Behind the red and pink, I must have missed the flash of purple before the room exploded. Blinding light strobed through the room as a deafening, crackling boom shook the air, and over it all, Echo’s voice boomed out, clear and terrifying: “Begone!”

Then the world plunged into darkness. The thundering sound cutting off, only a rattling echo and a numbness in my ears. All the lights had blown out. I pushed myself up, blinking at the ghostly images burned into my eyes, and peeked out over the desk.

The room was destroyed. Bedding was charred and burning. Walls were scorched. A nearby medical cart looked partially melted. The husks of four power-armor-clad changelings smoked and smoldered. The shadows thankfully hid the more grisly details of the changelings’ demise. The air reeked.

In the middle of that destruction stood Echo, her horn still illuminated, eyes glowing pure white, mane and tail flared with power. Her head turned, fixing me with her pupil-less stare. “We. Are. Leaving.”

With a flicker of purple magic, our suit of power armor and the last two cots floated into the air, the only two objects apparently untouched by whatever terrible magic she had unleashed. I grabbed for Bloodbeak, but Echo’s magic grabbed us instead, lifting us unceremoniously into the air.

The world twisted around us.

My hooves hit dirt. I staggered, gasping, and tumbled onto my side. It took a second to reorient. Dirt. I was on the ground. The flickering orange light to one side was a campfire. I was beside a large tent. We were in the camp. As I blinked away more of the after-images in my eyes, I saw ponies moving around us. It took a moment to recognize the Mareford Militia bardings and the medical symbols on the armors’ flanks. The medics were moving around the beds arrayed haphazardly outside the tent, many of which I recognized as coming from the Cumulonimbus.

Bloodbeak was sitting at my side, blinking and shaking her head. “Oof. Wow that was weird.”

I pushed myself up to sit. To my side, a pair of medical ponies hurried to the cots floating to the ground. The closest had several growing bloodstains, its occupant still. Ragged cuts had torn up his side, and the medic shouted for assistance. I wavered, wondering if I had done that to him, until the flicker of light above drew my attention upwards.

I could barely see the Cumulonimbus above, a faint silhouette highlighted by the flickering lighting in its supporting clouds. Lines of light flashed, piercing the sky; the Gemstone ponies were going to work, trying to pick off Serenity’s soldiers. Even their magical lasers were having a hard time finding targets in the dark at such a range.

Numbly, I turned to my broadcaster. “Bastion? It’s Whisper. The sickbay is empty and we’re all off the ship.”

“Understood,” Bastion replied. “Thank you. All aft units, peel back to deck one and join with us, we’ll be breaking out there.”

My head was slowly clearing up after the battery of explosions. I still felt off-balance.

Hail Burst spoke on the radio. “All forces, lift all fire around the ‘Nimbus. We’re breaking out now. We’ll be coming in fast on the main camp.”

As Dusty passed on instructions, I pushed myself up to my hooves. I wavered, my sense of balance swinging around for a moment before stabilizing. I looked to Echo, who stood imperiously, unfazed. “...We should get to Dusty.”

She simply nodded, and I turned to start walking, with Echo following close on my flanks. Bloodbeak scrambled to her feet to follow, calling out, “Wait for me!”

I wound my way through the maze of tents. I would have flown, but I didn’t want to make myself that much of a target. A few ponies started when they saw me, but most paid me nothing more than a passing glance.

The whole time, the radios continued to sound in both ears. A Serenity platoon commander was giving a situation report to her commander. “We’re secure here, but they smashed all the controls. We have no control over the ship. We have no steering control, no throttle control, no weapons control. It looks like hasty sabotage. Should be quick for the engineers to fix.”

I glanced up. The Cumulonimbus was still hard to make out, though it looked to be flying out over our front line. A storm of magical weapon fire filled the sky near its bow as Loyalists and Serenity soldiers exchanged fire. I turned back to look where I was going. There was nothing I could do about that fight at the moment.

In the other ear, some Loyalist soldier called out on the internal defense net, “Last mare!”

Hail Burst replied. “Hit it.”

Seconds later, the sky lit up. I looked up again to see the massive fireball lighting up the underside of the clouds, enveloping the Raptor. The lightning-laced clouds were ripped away with a final, dying flash. Shadows flickered in the sky, massive fragments of the ship carried away by the tremendous blast. The fireball rapidly burned out, leaving a cloud of smoke trailing behind the now-ballistic vessel. The guttering light revealed the massive rent torn through the side and belly of the craft.

Hail Burst had just hit Serenity with its own trick, and by the looks of it, to devastating effect.

Bloodbeak shouted something in surprise, and I could hear similar yells from around the camp. The rolling thunder of the explosion washed out those sounds for a moment, quickly fading into echos. Starlight’s voice cut through all of it, loud in my earbud. “Whisper!”

I quickly switched back to the private channel and replied, “I’m here. We’re all safe and on the ground.” My message delivered, I accelerated to a trot, while casting quick glances at the falling cloudship. With the fireball burnt out, it was visible only by the wisps of flame in the torn-open sections. I could barely make it out as the Cumulonimbus fell toward the valley to our west, slowly tumbling, before disappearing below the horizon of the nearby tents. The deep sound of its impact reached us seconds later.

It was the second time the great cloudship had fallen from the sky, and I had a feeling it would be the last.

The radio traffic had gone into overdrive. Serenity was a chaotic mess of voices, coming too quick and loud to pick out individual conversations, and I was too busy running to pull out the PipBuck and switch to individual channels. Dusty was calling for status updates. It was Two Bits who gave the first clear information.

“Command, Ranger Lead. The Cumulonimbus came down roughly two hundred yards out from the west-most defensive line, on the southern slope of the valley. The local hostiles have broken off. I’m going to push some forces forward to secure the crash site. Should give us a better defensive strongpoint.”

“If you can take it safely, do so,” Dusty replied. “Hail Burst? What’s your status?”

There was a pause. A moment of acidic tension before her voice came across the radio. “Unclear. We’re falling back to the main camp to regroup and assess.”

“Understood,” Dusty was saying as I rounded a corner, spotting the silhouette of our motorwagon some fifty feet away. Seconds later, I slowed and trotted into the headquarters. Dusty was lit by the dim screen of his PipBuck and the weak lantern hanging over the table. A few other Mareford ponies were gathered around him. He looked up from the map, a flash of recognition and relief crossing his face before turning back to his work. “Air, call when your last pony is on the ground.”

Starlight scrambled up from her seat. “Whisper! Holy crap I’m glad you got out of there!”

Echo stepped past me. “It is as I said. I will not permit any harm to befall her.”

“Yeah, uh-huh,” Starlight said, trotting up to me. “But you’re okay, right?”

“I’m okay,” I said, flashing a smile.

“It was pretty awesome,” Bloodbeak said with a grin. “Scary, but awesome. Echo fried a squad of power-armors!”

Dusty glanced up from the map. “Glad you’re all okay, but we’ve got a battle going on. If you’re not HQ, I need you out of here. Sorry, Bloodbeak.”

“Nah, no problem!” She said with a chuckle. “I’ll go keep watch or something.” She gave a playful salute before turning, trotting off.

Once she’d left the loose circle of the headquarters, Dusty looked to me again. “Any new info for me?”

“Not yet,” I said, setting out my PipBucks and scanning through Serenity’s channels. “I’ll let you know if I get something.”

“Good,” he said, then raised a hoof to tap at his ear, maintaining eye contact. I assumed he meant to use the radio. I nodded, and he returned to his map.

Starlight sat beside me, fidgeting. I think she was trying not to pry, not when we were still dealing with a battle out there. I reached out to rest a wing across her back. I’ll admit, a nice, heavy pegasus wing is much better at that than a thin changeling wing, but from the smile she flashed, she still appreciated the gesture. “So, what happened up there?”

“We were boarded,” I said, reply coming slow and careful as I tried to focus on the radio traffic. Trying to follow multiple conversations at the same time is a difficult task, even for one trained in social surveillance. “About a company of Serenity soldiers attacked. They got in close without being seen. It was a mess.”

Most of the traffic at the moment was in regards to the advance on the wreck of the Cumulonimbus. On the command net, Hail Burst finally reported in. “Command, Loyal. All Enclave forces are on the ground.”

“Copy that,” Dusty replied. “Gemstone, Command. Air is clear of friendly forces. You are free to fire on anything in the air. Flare going up momentarily.” He turned, gesturing with a hoof to one of the nearby Militia ponies, who immediately trotted to the edge of the shelter, floating out a stubby grenade launcher and loading a round. He fired it into the air with a deceptively soft retort for such a large round, and a second or two later, the area lit up in a soft white light.

A flurry of snaps and flashes followed as Gemstone ponies opened up on newly illuminated targets. I had to assume it was going well by the sound of things, as I couldn’t see it myself. I remained under the shelter; my radios were a more important focus for my attention.

Mareford and Trotsen ponies were radioing reports as they advanced along the southern ridge of the valley. A Serenity commander reported the advance, and was told to withdraw and yield the position. No crisis yet. Then the request went out, again, for company Alpha’s status, and this time, there was a reply.

I listened carefully before raising my own PipBuck, still on our private channel. I started the transmission, murmuring quietly so that nobody else could hear. “Serenity forces just reported their Alpha company as combat ineffective. Most were on the Cumulonimbus when it blew. No casualty counts, but they have a new acting commander, and she said Alpha effectively no longer exists.”

Across the shelter, I saw Dusty’s mouth tighten into a faint, grim, smile, and he gave a little nod, all the acknowledgement he could give with other ponies around him.

“That’s good, right?” Starlight asked.

I nodded. “It means we took a good chunk out of them. Now it’s just a question of how big a chunk they took out of us.”

Fortunately, I could see a group of Loyalists coming our way, as if to answer that question. Unfortunately, my E.F.S. showed they were not all friendly.

I turned to my PipBuck again, murmuring into the radio. “I’ve got a hostile contact in that group. The pony to the left of Hail Burst. Our left.”

Dusty’s head snapped up, eying the approaching pegasi. Echo had turned to face them as well, eyes narrow and head back, as if she could stop hostile intentions through the strength of her condescending glare.

When that failed to work—the pony in question walked right past Hail Burst towards me—she took a more direct approach. Without warning, the offending pony was jerked off his hooves in a glow of purple magic, the barrels of his weapons pointed straight upwards.

Shouting filled the headquarters for a moment, until Echo’s powerful voice cut through the shouts of surprise. “This pony has hostile intent toward Whisper, and I will not allow him to bring harm to her!”

The pony in question kicked out and flapped his wings, trying to pull free of the magic. “I’ll show you hostile intent!” he shouted. “That traitorous bitch let them in!”

The shouting was much more focused as Hail Burst’s head snapped around to him. “What?”

“That is a lie!” Echo boomed. “She was in my presence the entire time, and had no part in this attack!”

“The fuck she didn’t!” He twisted, but despite his efforts, the barrels of his armor-mounted weapons didn’t budge; there was no way he was going to win that fight against Echo’s magic. “We were doing just fine, but the moment she shows up, suddenly hundreds of those fucking bugs show up out of nowhere! She fucked us!”

Hail Burst grimaced as she stepped in front of him. “Enough. Let him down.” She waited until Echo—frowning and reluctant—did so, before speaking again with a voice of firm authority. “Crimson, I know we just got screwed pretty hard, but she wasn’t in any position to aid our enemy. Celestia knows I’d love nothing more than to kick the flank of the one responsible for it, but lashing out at our allies isn’t going to help.”

“Fuck them!” he shouted in her face. “We shouldn’t even be here! We’ve got our own war to fight, instead of mucking around in the mud!”

“This is our war!” Hail Burst snapped back, jaw tight. She wasn’t shouting furiously like him, but there was definitely some heat behind her words. “We’re fighting for what the Enclave stands for, and that means we’re not turning our backs on ponies again. This isn’t a debate. Return to the rally point and wait there with the others.”

“And fuck you,” he said, baring his teeth in a snarl. “I’m done with this shit. I’m going topside and finding some commander who’s still fighting our real enemy.”

She stared at him, eyes hidden behind those amber lenses. When she replied, her voice was icy. “Your input is noted. You’ve been given a lawful order by your superior officer, and I expect you to follow it.”

He opened his mouth, building up to shout back at her, but checked himself at the last moment. His wings lowered to his side. “Fine,” he said, practically spitting the word at her, then turned and walked off, muttering under his breath.

She waited until he’d disappeared behind another tent, and gave a tired sigh.

Dusty had stepped over from his map. “Is this going to be a problem?”

“No problem,” Hail Burst said, turning back to him. “Crimson just runs a bit hot at times. He’ll cool down. What’s our situation?”

“Serenity forces harassing the lines to the west through south, with scouts elsewhere. They’re falling back in the west, but I think they’re trying to make us pull forces off other positions. Now we’re without our eyes in the sky, so we’ve got a pretty poor picture of things. The whirligigs are grounded. Too vulnerable. How’s your force doing? What’s your strength?”

“Pretty shit,” she said with a bitter snort. “About twenty five combat-capable. Some of the wounded will be back in the fight once they’ve gotten some care, but that’ll only bring us up to thirty, maybe a bit more.”

“Damn,” Dusty muttered, then shook his head. “If you’ve got a couple scouts you could spare, I’d appreciate some recon near our lines, but don’t risk your ponies. The rest I’d like to keep here in case we need to defend from an air attack. Get some rest and recover.”

She nodded. “I can do that. I’ve still got the two scout teams out past our lines, looking for that megaspell.”

“Sounds good,” Dusty replied, hesitated, then added, “I’m sorry for how this went.”

“Not your fault,” Hail Burst said with a dismissive wave of her hoof. “We knew the damn bugs would come back for the ‘Nimbus. I just wish I knew how many we took down with it.”

I looked up. “I might be able to help with that.”

Everyone’s attention turned to me, and Starlight sat a little more upright, tense under my wing. I drew it back to lie beside the other before continuing. “Between friendly radio traffic and E.F.S. contacts, I’d estimate about one hundred to one hundred twenty hostile soldiers boarded the Cumulonimbus. I also have excellent low-light vision, and a good view of the ship when it went down. I didn’t see many of Serenity’s soldiers get away, unless they disguised as friendly pegasi. You likely took out about a hundred of their soldiers.”

She frowned in thought for a moment before giving me a simple nod.

“That was quite an explosion,” Dusty noted.

“They may have rebuilt her,” Hail Burst said, a hint of a proud smile touching her lips, “but we lived her for years. They brought the fight to our turf. All we had to do was hold them off long enough to sabotage flight controls and set charges in the bomb-chariot magazine. The bombs might be impact resistant, but that’s nothing a few demo packs couldn’t solve.”

“Well it certainly worked,” Dusty said. “Sorry about your ship, but I’m glad you took some of them down with it.”

“Thanks.”

A thought occurred to me. “Did Soaring Heart make it? I didn’t see him in the sick bay.”

“He did. He was forward, helping with the combat wounded. Bastion said he was going to go back to help evac the wounded until he heard you got them out. Thanks for that, by the way. I’m not sure if we could have fought our way out if we had to move them, too. It was a close thing as it was.”

I nodded. “I’m just glad it turned out well. Relatively speaking, anyway.”

“Though it reminds me,” she said, looking back to Dusty. “Sorry to say, but none of the Militia soldiers made it. They got overrun by power armor. By the time we pushed back out, there was nothing but ash.

Dusty grimaced, then quickly shook it off. “Understood.”

There was a pause as another radio report came in. “Command, Ranger Lead. Lead elements are at the crash site. Hostiles have broken contact and fallen back west. Securing the site now.”

Dusty raised his PipBuck. “Command copies.” Then he looked back to Hail Burst. “I’d like to try salvaging any functioning weapons, if you don’t object. The Gemstone ponies have been doing good work holding off Serenity in the air, and I’d like to supplement that as much as possible.”

Starlight’s ears perked up at the mention of salvage, which prompted me to start thinking on the subject.

Hail Burst thought a moment, then nodded. “I’ll send a couple of technicians to direct salvage, if the Militia can provide some spare hooves for the work.”

“We can do that.”

“Good. Though, I hate to say it, I’ll have to insist that all salvaged Enclave technology will be returned to us once this campaign is over.”

“Of course,” Dusty said with a nod.

“If I could make a request?” I said, drawing their attention once again. “I know you pegasi have a lot of technology that can float. Do you think there might be anything salvageable that could lift an antenna and cable up a hundred feet or so?”

“We have a lot of cloud tech,” Hail Burst said, her head tilting slightly in a way that suggested a suspicious expression behind those amber lenses. “Why?”

“Because I’ve had a hard time listening in on outlying units here on the ground. It’s why I went up to the Cumulonimbus. Once we’re moving, terrain is going to be more of a problem, and communications will be even more important. I figure it’ll make sure Dusty can communicate with everyone regardless of circumstances.”

Dusty cocked his head slightly, looking almost as if he was going to object for a moment. “...Well, it’ll certainly be better than relaying from unit to unit.”

Hail Burst shrugged. “Sure, whatever. If we’ve got the time, we’ll see what we can get, but the weapons come first.”

Starlight hopped to her hooves, grinning. “Nah, don’t worry about it. I’ll get it! Salvage is my thing. Well, that and being an awesome shot, but mostly salvage!”

Hail Burst hesitated, head slightly askew. “You’re a unicorn. You can’t do anything with cloud tech.”

“Oh,” Starlight said, her ears flicking back. “Right.”

I nudged her gently in the side. “You could ask Bloodbeak to help you. I think she’d like having something to do.” I glanced to Hail Burst. “If that’s okay with you?”

Her head rocked a little, as if she were rolling her eyes behind those lenses. “Fine by me. I’d say ‘don’t break anything’, but...”

Starlight laughed and gave me a quick hug before dashing off out of the headquarters. Hail Burst excused herself as well, returning to her own troops. Dusty and I returned our focus to the continuing skirmish, interrupted only by Starlight and Bloodbeak running past, clambering into our motorwagon, and riding off with the trailing sound of eager laughter.

There was little in the way of fighting, it seemed. Serenity had fallen back from the west, while the company to the south was engaging in light, harassing fire. Only the occasional probing force was sent in at the other directions, advancing only far enough to find pony forces, exchange a few ineffective shots, and fall back. I quietly passed on the details to Dusty.

In turn, he issued the orders to start resting in shifts. Sentries and lookouts would hold the line, swapping out regularly, so everyone could get some sleep.

“They’re probably trying to keep us up,” he said to those of us in the headquarters. “Tire us out so we can’t march far tomorrow.” It seemed reasonable to me.

Then I caught a Serenity transmission that made my blood run cold. “Command, Mantis One. Eyes on new hostile vic near the crash site. Looks to be the command wagon. Requesting permission to engage.”

“Wait one, Mantis.”

I was already lifting my own PipBuck, checking that I was on the private channel before whispering into the broadcaster. “Starlight! Some Serenity soldier has the wagon in his sights. Get to cover!”

There was a long pause with no sound but my heartbeat before Starlight’s voice came across the radio. “We’re inside the ‘Nimbus. They’re not going to shoot my wagon, are they?”

“I don’t know. Just stay safe in there, and keep an eye out.”

“I’ve got E.F.S.,” she noted. “Not a single hostile around.”

“Okay… okay, good. Just be careful.”

“You know it.”

I gave a soft sigh of relief, and waited. It was half a minute before Serenity’s commander spoke again.

“Mantis One, Command. Hold fire. The enemy command element is still in the main camp.”

“Mantis One copies, holding fire.”

I slowly relaxed, settling back into the routine of listening to broadcasts, and trying to push away that sense of danger. I disliked the amount of intel they had on our position, but it was hardly surprising, and more importantly, there was nothing I could do about it at the moment.

Minute by minute ticked by, while the probing of our lines continued. Ten minutes after my little scare, Serenity command ordered a platoon to make a probing air attack from the northwest, with the intent of slipping by to hit the main camp. I quietly passed on word to Dusty. He, in turn, was ready to react the moment a Loyalist scout reported possible enemy forces, and seconds later he had sent another flare up.

The Gemstone ponies opened fire again, and this time I leaned out from under the shelter, watching the flickering lines and soaring bolts of magic fill the air. The distant Serenity formation, nicely visible in the flare light, scattered and reversed course. On the radio, a changeling commander was calmly calling to fall back.

The flight returned some time later, probing a different part of our defenses, and then another. Each time, our response was the same, and each time, they fell back. Half an hour later, Serenity’s commander called them off.

Then she called a unit I had heard nothing from that night.

“Package Brachinus, Command. Enemy air defenses are degraded but too effective for strike. Stand down for the night. Expect updates when enemy forces start moving.”

The reply was almost buried under audio artifacts brought on by distance. “Brachinus copies, Command.”

What was this? The only other “package” they had mentioned had been the negotiator. That was something special, something outside the usual military action. Perhaps this package was, too?

First Braconid, then Brachinus. Were they related? Did they only sound similar? They both sounded vaguely scientific, though I had no idea what, specifically, they might refer to. Maybe if I had a good dictionary. There was a vague possibility someone in the army might know what they meant. More likely, the only ones to know would be Serenity spies, who would probably be very curious why I’m asking about their special units’ names. That ruled that option out.

Negotiators came under a flag of truce to talk, not sneaking in past air defense. Possibly this was another infiltrator?

No. They probably had spies already, and sneaking more in wouldn’t require such a massive military distraction.

This was something that needed surprise. Something that needed safe skies over the heart of our camp. Something that they were unwilling to take any chances on.

I couldn’t be certain of what they were planning, but I could make a good guess.

I raised my PipBuck, murmuring quietly into the broadcaster. “Dusty? I think they just called off an attempt to drop their megaspell on us.”

He glanced up from the map, meeting my eyes. I could see my own concern mirrored in his expression. I keyed in again, passing on what information I had. It wasn’t much.

The battle, such as it was, continued, but it had fallen into a routine. Dusty retired for the night, leaving one of the Mareford aides to listen to the radio and wake him if needed.

With ever-growing fatigue from lack of sleep, I finally turned in, as well.

Sleep came fitfully, my ear filled with the sporadic calls on the Serenity radio.

Chapter Forty Four: Push

If there’s one thing I admire the most about ponies, it’s the optimism.

I know, it’s not a universal trait. Back during the war, faced with the seemingly unending news of violence, death, and destruction on a grand scale, there were many who fell into a more cynical mentality. The hardships of the Wasteland kept that way of thinking alive. It wasn’t surprising that many, faced with such insurmountable and existential vileness, might lose hope of seeing better days. It’s a cloud that’s hung over the world for more than two centuries now.

But even in the face of seemingly unending suffering, that optimism was still there. I had seen it in the ponies I lived with in Appleloosa, who frowned and worried about the news, but still treated each other warmly. I saw it in the ponies of Gemstone, who embraced Kindness and Generosity as the solution for the world we found ourselves in. I even saw it in Bastion, laughing along with the Mareford ponies who walked beside him, despite the pronounced limp as he kept his weight off his heavily bandaged leg.

Changelings have a long history of living in relatively harsh conditions, maneuvering in the shadows and hiding from other species that we depended on for food. That kind of history bred a certain amount of stoicism in our cultural learning. We endured. That’s particularly true of my peer group, those with the skill and mental fortitude to become Infiltrators. Those who were expected to go into hostile territory with calmness, determination, and an unburdened mind, capable of playing a role without personal fears betraying us.

But even among those of us who held to great ideals, who looked ahead to a better future, there was much to admire in the optimism of ponies, even as the weight of the war slowly buried it. I think, of all the things my hive learned from our infiltration of Equestria, all the espionage and subterfuge, that was possibly the most important. In the aftermath of the sundering of the hive, it was the ideal that our hive had embraced. The ideal that would lead us to a better future. The ideal that we were working not just to survive, but to become something better.

We, this gathered army, had taken a pounding. The night had been long, full of sporadic gunfire and harassing raids. More wounded filled the medical tents, and new graves had been dug. Even the Cumulonimbus, previously an awe-inspiring symbol of the army’s gathered might, lay in ruins, a crumpled tomb to more than a hundred changelings and ponies. All of that weighed on the army.

In the dim pre-dawn twilight, the atmosphere in the camp was far from joyful, but these ponies held strong. While the dead were missed, there was an air of satisfaction that, after Serenity’s nighttime assault, they still stood strong. They had held their own, and emerged from the darkness victorious. The destruction of the mighty Cumulonimbus wasn’t a crushing loss of their greatest weapon, but a tale of a few dozen ponies holding out against hundreds, and when all seemed lost, turning Serenity’s own trap on them. Soldiers worried about what the following days would bring, but when one pony smiled at some small pleasantry, I saw that bit of brightness reflected in the faces around them.

All around, the camp was coming to life, packing and preparing for the day. We planned to set out in less than an hour. Most of us in the headquarters were getting a quick breakfast of canned goods—seasoned corn that had lost most of its flavor, in my case—and reviewing our plans. The radios were pleasantly quiet in my ear.

Bastion looked away from the ponies who walked alongside him to see me, and he smiled. He was quite athletic and handsome, for a pony, with a white coat and close-cropped blue-and-silver mane. It was a look that seemed so stereotypically military, but there was a genuine warmth to that smile. As he drew closer, he addressed me with a nod. “Your Highness.”

I gave a single soft chuckle, deciding not to interrupt the niceties by insisting on a less formal title. Not unless it started catching on. “Sergeant Bastion,” I said, dipping my jagged horn in greeting. “It’s good to see you. I’d been hoping to catch up with you after breakfast.” I floated up the can before setting it down again. “When I heard you were injured, I had feared the worst.”

“What, this?” he said, raising his bandaged leg. “It’s nothing. I’ve burnt myself worse trying to cook. No, my armor took the brunt of the damage.”

“Better it than you,” I said. “Still, I’m glad to see you’re up and active. I wanted to thank you for everything you did last night. We were badly outnumbered, but your leadership saw us through. You likely saved my life, and many others.” I bowed my head a little. It seemed like the queenly thing to do.

“Oh, I was just doing my job,” he said with a dismissive wave of his hoof. “I just told ponies where to go. It’s the ponies who held the line who deserve the credit. Actually, I came here to thank you.” He glanced past me, to where Echo stood, my ever-vigilant bodyguard. “When you two evacuated the wounded, you might have saved our flanks. If we had tried to fight past that third force to evacuate them ourselves, I don’t think any of us would have gotten out of there. You might have saved a lot of ponies last night.”

He finished by extending his good hoof, and I smiled more as I shook it. He then turned to Echo with the same gesture. She hesitated, uncertain, before accepting and shaking it as well.

“I hope you’re well enough to travel?” I asked, hoping it didn’t seem insensitive, but he waved it off.

“A singed leg isn’t going to keep me from flying,” he said with a smile. “I take it we’re moving out soon? I haven’t caught up with Hail Burst yet.”

That was more of a military matter, and Dusty answered it. “We are. We’ve got a good ways to go before we get to Serenity, and I’d rather not give them any more time than necessary.”

“I hear that,” Bastion said with a nod. “Better get as much progress as possible before the rain hits.”

Dusty’s ears perked up. “Rain?”

“Yeah,” Bastion said, his head inclining a bit. “You saw the way the clouds out west are churning, right?”

Dusty glanced that way, as did I. To my eyes, there wasn’t anything unusual.

“I guess I don’t know clouds as well as you,” Dusty said. “How long do we have?”

“With that much density and current? Two, maybe three days. Going to be bad, too. Those clouds are completely unregulated. With a heavy load, it’ll probably be a full, uncontrolled release. One or two days of heavy rain and near-blackout conditions.”

I frowned, thinking back to my first days in the Wasteland.

Dusty was looking over his map. “That’s a little tighter than I was hoping for. We might make Serenity in two days, if we don’t get bogged down. It’ll be a hard push, but doable.”

“Great,” Starlight said around a mouthful of half-chewed carrots. “So it’s a race.”

“We wanted to get this done as quick as possible,” Dusty said, turning back to his own food. “This just gives us a time-table. Heck, the weather might even give us an advantage. How well can they fly in rain like that?”

Bastion gave a dry chuckle. “If they’re anything like pegasi? They’ll be grounded. Even the Wonderbolts wouldn’t want to fly in that kind of weather. That’s a good way to get killed.”

“Well, we’d have that, at least,” Dusty noted, then shook his head. “But we’ll aim for getting to Serenity before the rain. The army won’t be able to march in weather like that. Not safely. If we can force them back to the Stable, the rain won’t matter.”

“Sounds good to me,” Bastion said with a smile. “Anyway, I need to go check in with Hail Burst. I expect we’re going to have a busy couple of days.”

That earned a wry smile from Dusty. “I don’t doubt it.”

☢

An hour later, the army was moving.

“We’ll be heading north to here,” Dusty said, showing me the location on his PipBuck’s map. “Serenity likely put most of their defensive plans on our west side, so I’m hoping we’ll run into less resistance that way.”

“There’s some discussion about that on Serenity’s net,” I said with a nod. “Sounds like they’re working out a new plan, but they have nothing concrete yet.”

“Good. Let me know if you get any details. We’ll only be going a couple miles before turning west. The hills restrict our movements a bit, but the main obstacle is probably going to be the Rotwater. The old river cut a deep ravine, steep enough to be a problem for ponies on the hoof, much less wagons. There’s a pre-war rail bridge near where we’ll meet it, but Serenity will probably blow it to stop us, so we need to find a place where the banks are shallow enough for motorwagons. The only places indicated on the maps are here…” He indicated a position, then scrolled over to indicate another. “...and here. Serenity will probably try to take advantage of that. Anything you hear about those locations could be critical.”

I nodded again.

“And of course, any word about their megaspell would be good,” he said with a shrug, and sat back in his seat. We were still parked, while the core of the army marched. I could just hear the distant sound of scattered shots to our west. Almost a mile away, some hundred-plus ponies were engaging Serenity forces in a small-scale skirmish that Dusty hoped would keep the enemy defenses pinned down and unable to move against the maneuvering army. “Is everything set up back there? We need to get going soon.”

“I’ll go check,” I said.

While Dusty took the opportunity to pull out a cigarette, I turned back to my radio equipment, which had been nicely expanded. Starlight hadn’t stopped at merely acquiring some cloud tech and cables. She’d brought back about two hundred pounds of electronics, much of it radio equipment, which was currently strapped down just behind my seat. I had to wonder if the Loyalists had actually approved of all the sensitive equipment she had taken.

I climbed out over the back of my seat, a task made more difficult by just how heavily loaded we were. It wasn’t just the new electronics, of course. Sickle was kicked back atop a makeshift bed of ammo canisters and cases, taking up most of the space on her own. Then there were the two power armors wedged in alongside her, with Echo perched protectively above them. There wasn’t a single inch of floor to be seen beneath the gathered equipment. Even Bloodbeak was there, though she made room for me by climbing onto the roof of the wagon, sitting back against the heavy machine gun.

A quick beat of my wings lifted me over the various obstacles, and I alighted on the rear wall of the cargo bed to look down on Starlight and her project. My hooves had just touched down when the mare helping her called out. “Eyes!”

I turned my head, bringing up a hoof to shield my eyes. A second later a searing-bright and flickering light illuminated everything around me, accompanied by the crackling sound of the welder. It lasted for only a couple of seconds before everything dimmed again, but I kept my hoof in place until the voice spoke again. “All clear.”

I lowered my hoof, looking on the small project. Starlight had snagged an entire antenna array, bristling with a dozen antennas of different sizes, and now mated to a pair of cloud-based cargo jacks and tethered by a lengthy cable. That wasn’t all she had brought back for this project, though. She’d also brought the red mare, who currently had her goggles raised to inspect the weld, the welding torch still clutched in her teeth.

Singe looked much better than the last time I had seen her. The ash and dirt had been cleaned from her coat, and while she still showed some signs of her injured ribs in her movements, she seemed otherwise in good health.

She gave a firm tug on the cargo jack before setting down the welding torch and looking up, only to visibly flinch the instant she saw me. I was still in my natural form, to better fit in the wagon, not that I’m sure any of my standard disguises would be any more comforting. Still, she immediately returned to business, as if pretending the reaction hadn’t taken place. “The welds are all good. If the cable’s secure, it’s all set to go up.”

“It’s on there good,” Starlight said, reaching over to pat the again-repurposed towing rig she had welded on so many days ago. Several bolts now held the end of the long cable secure. “I even doubled-up on the connectors to make sure it won’t pull free. We probably won’t want to go crazy while we’re dragging this thing, but it’ll hold up to regular use.”

“Good,” Singe said with a nod, then looked up to me again. Her shoulders tensed, as if wanting to pull away, but she forced herself to face me, unflinching. “Then all that’s left is to wire things in on your end.”

I nodded and smiled, trying to open my mouth only the minimum required to talk without flashing all my sharp teeth at her. “Sounds good. Thank you again for all your help.”

There was a momentary falter in her expression, but she held firm. “I’m just glad to be helping. Doing something.” Her mouth opened again, then shut, falling silent.

“Well, we need to get going. Are you all set to travel?”

“Yes,” she said, not quite meeting my eyes. “The Mareford ponies are giving me a ride in a medical wagon. I can’t really walk that well yet.”

“I’m sure that will be better soon,” I offered, hoping it might be comforting.

“Thanks,” she said, quietly, before finally meeting my gaze again. “Good luck.”

I smiled a little more. “You too, Singe.”

She nodded, passing the borrowed welding equipment back to Starlight before turning to walk to the waiting medical wagons.

Starlight climbed up on the rear of the wagon, her magic grasping the contraption she had hooked up to one of the many wires coming from the long cable. It was little more than a spark battery and a dial. “Okay,” she said, holding the device up. “Let’s see if this thing works.”

The dial twisted, and the desk fan bolted onto the bottom of the antenna array buzzed to life, kicking up bits of dirt as the whole assembly floated slowly but surely into the air.

“Aw, yeah!” Starlight said, grinning. “We are awesome.”

“You did good,” I said, mirroring her grin.

“Aw, heck, it was nothing,” she said with a chuckle and wave of her hoof. “Let’s just wait till it gets up and brings up all the slack, and we’re all set to roll out!”

She hopped down to trot around to the driver’s seat, and I gathered up the bundle of wires, all wired up to new connectors and conveniently labeled with bits of pencil-marked tape, thanks to Starlight’s foresight.

Echo didn’t wait for me finish. “You should be wearing this armor,” she said, still fixated on the subject. “That is why we had it repaired. It doesn’t do anyone any good just sitting there empty.”

“Sorry,” I said with a dismissive shrug. “It won’t really fit in the cab.”

“It is not that bulky!” Echo snapped, and I flinched slightly, regarding her a little more carefully. I hadn’t expected her to be quite so upset over the subject. “I have spent days repairing this armor for your sake. Why are you so stubbornly opposed to making use of it?”

Her ears were pinned back, eyes narrowed. Even her mane flowed more wildly, a form of body language I was still getting used to. I took a few seconds to more carefully formulate my reply. “Echo, my experience and training as an Infiltrator has always taught me to make use of the best tools at my disposal, regardless of my personal preferences.” I reached up to touch my rifle, hanging across my chest. “It’s a lesson that my time in the Wasteland has reinforced. I promise you, if we’re approaching a situation where I would be better off using that armor, I will, but right now, it would just get in the way of what I need to do.”

The anger in her expression faded, covered under a thoughtful frown. “I suppose that seems sensible, though I question the accuracy of your risk assessment. I should point out that the one time in the past week where the armor would have made a difference came with no warning. You must certainly be aware of how unexpected a changeling assassination attempt can be.”

“I am,” I said with a sigh, “and it’s something I will be keeping in mind in the future.”

She held her frown, but after a couple of seconds, finally gave a faint snort that vaguely sounded like an acquiescence.

I replied with a nod, then spread my wings, making a short, buzzing hop over the pile of equipment, wires in tow.

I stopped again as I once again saw Bloodbeak sitting by the gun. I slipped the end of the wires in over the back seat, then stood again to speak to her. “Are you sure about this?”

“Hmm?” She looked back at me. “About what?”

“About coming with us.”

She broke out in a grin, waving her claws at the gun and motorwagon in front of us. “Seriously? Heck yeah, I’m sure! I get to ride with you guys on the coolest wagon, and you’re setting me up with a flank-kicking super-gun!”

“You remember what Dusty and I told you, right? If you do come with us, that’s it. This is the headquarters for the whole army, and Serenity is sure to have spies. We’re taking information security seriously. There are things that will be said that Serenity can not learn, under any circumstances. If you’re in, you’re in until Serenity is done. No alone time, no wandering off without one of us with you, no off-duty time. Are you sure?”

She wiped away the grin, replaced with a thin but determined smile. “I pulled guard duty with the Dawnbringers for years. Never napped or wandered. Duty first.” The grin started to return. “I’m in all the way, superspy. No place I’d rather be.”

I hesitated. “I’m not really a superspy.”

She just waved it off. “Well, that’s what Starry was calling you. I mean, I get it. I’m guessing you’ll be talking lots of spy stuff you don’t want others hearing, and that means you don’t want me repeating it. Makes sense. So yeah, I’ll chill with you guys for a few days. My beak is sealed.”

“And Seroon?” I asked. “You sure you don’t want to travel with him and the other Dawnbringers?”

She chuckled. “Heck, he was telling me I should try to help you guys. He’s got all of Mareford watching his back. Said you could use someone to help watch yours.”

“And you’re absolutely sure you want to stay, then?”

She wrapped a foreleg around the machine gun, grinning. “You’d have to break out Starry’s prybar to get me out of this wagon.”

I cracked a smile. “Well, okay then. I hope you enjoy the ride.”

She gave a mock salute, and I ducked down, squeezing into the backseat once more. It took only a few moments to sort out the cables, and only a few more to plug the connectors into the proper ports of my increasingly convoluted arrangement of networked PipBucks. It was a chaotic jumble of cables and distributed computational power, but it worked. Somehow. I had the distinct sense that it might be overkill for what I was doing with it, but I didn’t really have the luxury of time to streamline things. Sometimes, you just had to settle with a jury-rigging.

The moment I had the right cable in place, the Serenity channel I was monitoring turned garbled for a moment, then cleared up perfectly. The antenna was doing its job.

I pulled out another cable, reaching forward to offer it to Dusty. “Here you go.”

He took it, eying the connector suspiciously. “You’re sure this will work?”

“It’s all hooked up and ready,” I said. “I’m using the main antenna, but that’ll hook you up to one of the secondaries. Just give it a test to make sure the antenna is working right.”

He settled back into his seat, slipping the cable around the chair and plugging it into his PipBuck. The radio gave its electronic squawk as he hit the button to transmit. “Ranger Lead, Command. Radio check.”

It was mere seconds before the reply came back, loud and clear. “Command, Ranger Lead. Roger.”

Dusty looked back to me, giving a nod of approval.

“All right,” Starlight said, finally sliding into the driver’s seat. “The cable’s as taut as it’s getting. We’re good to roll.”

“Good,” Dusty said. “It’s time we got going. Bring us up to the Trotsen wagons.”

“You got it,” Starlight said with a grin.

The wagon rocked gently as Echo took to the wing, and the engine thrummed with magical power, accelerating smoothly. Half a mile ahead, we could make out the gathered wagons, with Hail Burst and her Loyalists flying along above.

I looked back to double-check the cable. The welded-on rig creaked slightly, and the floating antenna dragged behind us at a fairly steep angle, but it wasn’t showing any signs of coming loose. “Looks like it’s all holding together just fine.”

“Good,” Dusty said, already consulting his map to plan and coordinate the movements of the force we had assembled.

☢

We made it less than an hour before the fighting kicked off.

It was inevitable. For all my intelligence gathering, all of Dusty’s clever maneuvering, all the scouting and rapid movements, we still faced the one insurmountable advantage Serenity had over us: their entire force could fly.

Minutes after our wagon started rolling, Serenity started to pull back from the forces attempting to pin them in place. I listened to broadcasts while scanning my PipBuck’s map, trying to track movements. The maneuver was simple and elegant. A few squads kept their position while the rest of the company withdrew, repositioning with incredible speed. A minute later, the maneuvering units had established long-range fire, covering the front-most squads as they fell back.

The Militia ponies tried to press the attack to keep them engaged, but they had to dart from cover to cover, advancing on hoof and under fire, while Serenity’s soldiers could rapidly fly back to their new lines, sweeping low to the ground at high speed. It was hopeless. In less than three minutes, the entire company had broken contact, flying rapidly away from the battlefield.

Ten minutes after we started moving, I heard Serenity organizing raids on our column. My heads-up to Dusty was largely superfluous. He was already aware of the possibility, but at least I could tell him where and when the attacks were going to come in. While he didn’t want to give away our advantage by acting preemptively, it meant he wasn’t surprised by the maneuvers. He had time to plan ahead, and when Serenity made their move, his counter-moves were immediate.

The first raid came in on the main army. I turned to look out the window just as the black dots surged over a ridge barely a mile away. An instant later, Dusty was on the radio. “Loyal Lead, Command! Eyes on enemy fliers, south. Move to engage. Remain within three hundred yards of the column. Gemstone! Take positions and concentrate air defense south. Move at your discretion to remain alongside the column.”

Lines and bolts of light were already cutting through the sky as acknowledgements came in. Gemstone’s three magical energy cannons had been supplemented by four more from the Cumulonimbus, with Arclight working on repairing two more. A little over half were in our portion of the army, and they sent up a dazzling wall of magical death to meet the oncoming attackers.

Above, the Enclave Loyalists banked, coming around in a clean and coordinated formation. They were only a fraction of the oncoming force’s size, but it was enough; as changeling soldiers weaved to avoid fire from the ground, it left them unable to properly engage the pegasi.

Hail Burst didn’t have that problem. She led the first group of pegasi straight on, opening up a withering salvo of long-range fire. Fuschia-colored magic etched the sky, cutting through the loose Serenity formation, though none found their mark. It did, however, break up the formation even further.

Then the flurry of fire stopped, and the pegasi banked around in a neat, tight turn. As they did so, the next group was already turning to make their own run, and the air once again filled with magic.

A few changelings tried to brave the volume of incoming fire to straighten out and return some shots of their own. A few bolts flashed out in return. One of the changelings paid for her bravery, a purple-pink flash of a direct hit enveloping her for a moment before she plummeted towards the ground.

Still, they closed on the column. Half a mile, now. The lead pegasi had banked away, flying back the way they came, while the next batch had turned in towards the oncoming changelings, loosing their own salvo. Nearby, a few ponies had rifles pointed into the sky, firing a few rounds into the air at desperately long ranges, but that volume of fire—and its accuracy!— would only grow as the enemy came closer.

Even if the incoming fire hadn’t hit many of the attackers, it was clearly having an effect. My left earbud crackled. “Lead, One. We’re taking a hell of a lot of fire! Multiple M.E.W. cannons. We’re not going to be effective here.”

A flash of green sliced across the sky, lancing one of the closing changelings. I traced it back to one of the Trotsen wagons, with one of Arclight’s cannons bolted to its roof. I could just make out Blueberry, adjusting his aim before firing again. It was slower firing than the powerful plasma cannons, but its beam was like Starlight’s Lancer; accurate, lightning-fast, and judging by the way the dark form crumbled into glowing green ashes, remarkably powerful.

Another shot barely missed a weaving Serenity soldier, who immediately broke off her approach to enter a spiraling dive to avoid any follow-up shots.

“One, Lead,” the left earbud buzzed again. “Disengage. Break off southeast and rejoin.”

“Copy.”

The incoming changelings veered off, diving towards the ground to pick up more speed and avoid incoming fire. A few let off long-ranged bursts of fire before turning away. I cringed as the bolts arced through the air, seeming to curve as if homing in on us, and ducked as they came crashing down.

Given my expectation, it was rather anticlimactic. There were no loud explosions. Just a rapid pattering of dull puffs and thumps and several shouts. I peeked out the window again to see the column marching along, relatively unscathed. Some of the shouts were from a line of Mareford ponies, one of which was on the ground. Several other ponies had gathered around him to render aid, while the others were continuing to march under the orders of their commander. Well down the line, I could see one of the Trotsen griffins beating at the smoldering spot on the side of her wagon’s armor.

Above, the Loyalists gave a brief pursuit, diving and laying out a parting salvo of fire before breaking off and returning to the column.

Suddenly, it was quiet once more. The Loyalist skywagon swooped in along the line, picking up the unlucky pony who had been struck by one of the long-distance shots and delivering him to the medical wagons. It took a minute for a full casualty report to come in; no dead, three wounded, and only one seriously. Serenity had taken a shot at us, and we’d weathered it almost unscathed, returning better than we got.

But we were only fifteen minutes in.

Ten minutes later, the head of the army was approaching the first of the Serenity ground forces. Two squads were waiting on the back slope of a hill, ready to ambush our force the moment they had advanced far enough along the narrow valley floor. It was a good place for an ambush, if a bit too far to cause real damage.

“They don’t need to hurt us much,” Dusty said when I brought it up, eying the map with all the markers I had provided. “They just need to kick up enough of a fuss that we have to take them seriously. It’s delaying tactics. The slower we are, the more time they have to prep their positions.”

And so, in a calculating move, we once again took no preemptive action. Five minutes later, the lead element crossed into Serenity’s sights.

A moment later, the radio squawked in my left ear. “Lead, One.” Despite the distance, the channel was crisp and clear, without any signs of distortion. The antenna was working wonderfully. “Enemy recon wagon has just passed RP Snare, continuing west along the valley. No contact.”

The reply came swiftly. “Copy. Enemy vanguard should be about five to ten minutes behind. Hold tight.”

“One copies.”

Dusty muttered to himself as I passed that on, then called for a location report from all Mareford units. As that went on, the recon wagon halted at the end of the valley, its position relayed by both the Serenity ambush force and the scout team onboard. I quickly checked my map, doing a little quick geometry. The recon wagon was about half a mile from the ambush force. Closer than Dusty and I would have liked, but still far enough to be somewhat safe.

Still, we waited. Dusty watched the map closely, silently counting down to the moment when the vanguard of our army reached the location tag that marked the intended ambush.

I was almost two miles away, hidden behind a line of hills, and I still felt the adrenaline teasing at my nerves.

By my count, we were about thirty seconds from the ambush when Dusty hit the key to transmit. “Trotsen Lead, Command. Enemy spotted to the south of vanguard elements. Orders for Reaction Force One: move to hill 313, dismount at the top, and assault west into enemy positions on the west slope of that hill. Best speed.”

“About damn time,” came the reply from Sandstorm.

Radio chatter quickly filtered down the lines, and the reaction force—six Trotsen motorwagons bearing several squads of Mareford Militia—was already moving before Serenity’s broadcast went out.

“Eyes on enemy infantry, squad-plus, at RP Snare.”

I looked to Dusty. “Our ponies just entered the ambush site.”

He gave a sharp nod, eyes fixed on his map.

I turned back to my own map, with the jumble of intercepted location tags denoting Serenity positions and points of interest, while mentally overlaying our own force’s positions. The calm was unnerving.

Radio traffic practically exploded, and I filtered out most of the low-level communications. The platoon-level report came in calm and clear, despite the loud gunfire. “Contact, enemy infantry, due south of One, five hundred yards. One is under heavy but distant fire.”

“Understood, One. Take cover, hold position, and pin them down. Mobile units are already on the way.”

Said mobile units were already climbing the opposite slope of the hill. It was a tense minute of listening to them moving and disembarking, all while I silently tracked their position on my map.

The Serenity channel opened with an urgent voice. “One and Two! Enemy forces approaching from your—”

The broadcast was immediately drowned out by explosions and gunfire. “Close contact east! Two is—”

The broadcast cut off, giving an instant of silence, while the numbers indicating squad-level radio traffic flashed and stayed lit. Chaos had descended upon the ambush.

Seconds later, the platoon-level channel opened again. “Lead, One! Two Lead is down. We are being overrun! Infantry and vehicles!”

“Break contact. Pull back. I’m calling for support.”

“We’re trying!”

In the other ear, the leader of the vanguard element reported that he was lifting fire. The Militia pony relaying information for the reaction force simply reported that they were in contact.

Dusty was nodding in satisfaction, and after a few seconds, keyed in again. “Ranger Lead, Command. If the reaction force has that ambush locked down, I want you to keep the column moving at good speed. We can’t get bogged down here. I’ll get some more air recon up there for you.”

“Ranger Lead copies. Wilco.”

It was just two minutes later when the final details of the conflict came over the radio. One dead and two wounded in the vanguard, with one more dead in the assault on the Serenity positions. In exchange, the timely counter-assault at point-blank range had devastated the ambushers. The final tally was twenty one casualties, all deceased. At least one had been merely wounded. It seems she had played dead until one of the Militia ponies came near, then tried to bring her rifle up to shoot him. They hadn’t taken any more chances after that.

I frowned when that information was passed on, but said nothing. I didn’t like it, but I understood it.

The leader of the assault estimated that no more than half a dozen changelings had managed to get away. The order was passed down to rapidly secure weapons and equipment, then fall back to the main column.

Dusty took a moment to pass on a request to Hail Burst, sending a pair of recon flights over to scout ahead. With that resolved, he brought up his map once more, scrolling another mile past the ambush point. I did the same, eying the multitude of location markers that had been passed over the Serenity network.

“Okay,” Dusty said, looking back to me. “What’s next?”

☢

Ten hours.

I thought I had acquired a decent experience with combat. I thought I had seen battle, or at least enough to have a good idea of what it was like. The carnage at Paradise Beach. The mercenary attack in the outskirts of Dodge City. Multiple firefights with raiders. All terrifying, chaotic, dangerous, and even traumatizing events filled with death and desperation.

But the longest of those fights was still measured in minutes. When our diverse army encountered Serenity’s first significant resistance, it kicked off ten continuous hours of relentless battle.

For those ten hours, battle raged, and I saw almost none of it.

Serenity launched five more raids over the course of the rolling battle, hoping to capitalize on the distraction of combat to strike exposed groups in the rear. Two tried to target the center group, where I was. One even descended straight down from the clouds, in what could have been a devastating attack if Dusty hadn’t been warned and ready to respond immediately. I could see the changelings in the sky, turned back by the Gemstone and Loyalist defenders. A few bolts of magic struck amidst the column, but as callous as it sounds when describing casualties, the damage they caused was minimal. It was the closest I got to the actual fighting.

The rest of the time, I might be able to see groups of ponies on hills or ridges, as much as a mile away, or the rapid movement and dusty plume of motorwagons displacing in reaction to some new threat. Sometimes I even saw them firing on distant enemies I couldn’t see.

Yet at the same time, I probably had a better picture of what was going on than anyone else, in either army.

That isn’t to say my view was perfect. There was still plenty of uncertainty. To determine where any group was, I had to rely on radio reports. Sometimes they came from that unit, while sometimes they came from others. Information came in too quickly for me to process all of it, so I had to prioritize general strategy over fine detail. Despite those limitations, I had a wealth of information. I tracked where everyone went to the best of my ability, listened in on their plans, and passed the information on to Dusty.

It was fascinating to watch him work, his eyes fixed upon the map as he passed down orders, a cigarette all but forgotten on his lips. The movements of the armies unfolded with agonizing slowness, like some glacial dance. Dusty would give the order for one of the reaction forces to move to counter an anticipated threat, and we might wait five minutes to hear that they were disembarking at their destination. Other times, the dance accelerated to a frantic pace; multiple platoons of Serenity soldiers moving at high speed, trying to exploit some perceived weakness in our lines, and our rapid and urgent responses to counter that threat.

Serenity had so many advantages on us. They were faster. Their soldiers were well-trained and exceptionally equipped. They were a single, unified force, without any inter-faction conflicts that might diminish their effectiveness.

Yet every time they made a move, their foe adapted instantly. Every time they exhibited some weakness, their foe exploited it. Every time they attempted a ruse, their foe refused to take the bait. By all appearances, Dusty was a master of war.

Of course, we were cheating. Neither of us had any problem with this.

As he told me, so much of what makes good tactics and strategy is intuiting what your enemy is doing and balancing the risks you take. Was that flank really weak, or was there another unit that could punish any attempts to exploit it? Was that ambushing force on its own, or did they have other units giving security? Did that enemy force really retreat, or had they just fallen back to better defensive positions? Was that withdrawing unit in good order or in shambles? What lay over that ridge? Where was the rest of their army?

Risk is a part of warfare, but when you know exactly where the enemy is and what they plan to do, you cut out most of the risk.

When the lead units came into contact, Dusty already knew where they were, and how to counter them. I watched as he directed platoons down poorly defended approaches, pinned down exposed defenders, and launched assaults on weak positions. Serenity’s more agile forces found themselves outmaneuvered time and again.

Through it all, there was one prevailing order: keep pushing. Stop to fight when needed, but then get moving again. If you weren’t in contact, you were advancing. Serenity lay before us. We had to push them back to their hive. The word had gone out: if we take Serenity, we win.

The dark clouds churned above us.

Despite our overwhelming advantage in information, Serenity’s soldiers tried their best, and their discipline showed. While Dusty managed to reverse their traps on them, they fought back fiercely. They rarely panicked, and never surrendered.

They even managed a few surprises. No mention had been made on the radio of land mines until the recon motorwagon lost a wheel to one. That kicked off a quick scramble as Dusty directed the reaction force to save them, narrowly fending off an assault by a Serenity force, to minor casualties on both sides. From then on, the recon element included one of the Militia combat engineers, a unicorn adept at detecting and disarming explosives. They found only six more mines during the march; few enough to be a minor expenditure, but enough to keep us wary.

Our motorwagon followed as the army continued its slow but steady pace, and half an hour after the vanguard made contact with the first real opposition, I saw another side of the battle.

The first corpse I saw was a changeling, not far from the path we rode along. She lay beside a dead bush at the edge of a shallow depression. Even as we passed just thirty yards away, I couldn’t see any signs of the injury that had killed her. If not for the awkward contortion of her neck and hindlegs from her sprawled position, or the bit of dirt scattered atop an extended wing, I might have thought she was asleep.

I didn’t spare many glances away from my map and radios, but it was enough to take in a bit of what the casualty reports had already told me. Serenity wanted to slow us down, and they tried to withdraw before Dusty could pin them down in a fight. Casualties were relatively light on both sides, but it was a slow trickle that continued on, hour after hour. The Loyalist’s skywagon flew back and forth, ferrying medical ponies to the front, or bringing the worst of the wounded back to the medical wagons. The less injured were patched up and resumed the march, or sat and waited for the next available wagon.

The dead were left for the logistics ponies to collect. I would see the occasional scattered corpse where Serenity had managed a clean escape. Where they hadn’t, I saw clusters of bodies. Little clumps of intense violence, signified by a dozen or so corpses. Most of these were changelings, but a few were ponies, killed where Serenity’s soldiers had fought back more effectively, or even managed some small-scale surprise.

I caught Dusty looking over some of those groups of fallen ponies with grim eyes. Then he took a deep drag on his cigarette, turned back to his map, and ordered more ponies to their deaths.

We rolled on, following the trail of bodies for ten hours.

☢

We had almost two hours of light left when we reached Rotwater Creek. The lead elements of the army had taken up sheltered positions just a quarter mile from where the narrow ravine opened up into wider banks. On the map, it looked to be a passage about three hundred yards wide.

It sounded like a wonderfully spacious and open piece of terrain, until you factored in just how many soldiers were determined to kill us there.

“Show me,” Dusty said, turned in his seat as I presented my PipBuck. Intercepted location markers dotted the far shore, noting Serenity positions, built-up defences, fall-backs, and support. Markers on our side of the creek noted sectors of responsibility for various units, and now, markers for “enemy” positions. They were making excellent use of the PipBuck technology. Any commander could put down a custom location tag, and their communications network would rapidly distribute it to every single Serenity changeling, and unknown to them, one particular non-Serenity changeling.

Our own mark showed us just a quarter mile back from the head of our army. It was the closest I’d been to the front all day.

I scrolled to the cluster of marks near the creek. “Their Charlie company has been setting up here. Our swing north forced them to relocate, and they arrived on-site about eight hours ago. They’ve been setting up defensive positions.” I pointed out several marks. “There’s a fortification on either side of the crossing, right by the edge of the ravine, to give a good crossfire, with mines scattered around the creek itself. There’s supposed to be a line of defenses forming a semicircle, extending about a hundred yards back from the creek. Then there’s a second pair of fortifications on a line two hundred yards back from that for supporting fire, with a few defensive positions between them. Details are pretty vague on how substantial the defenses are, but there was talk of prefabricated structures and heavy materials, as well as digging earthworks along each line. Good news is, they’ve been scrambling. Lots of chatter about how we’re coming on a lot quicker than they expected. The defenses are not nearly as complete as they’d like, and they’re probably tired.”

Dusty gave a satisfied grunt as I continued. “Their Bravo company arrived three hours ago, and they hauled a lot of material from the crossing they were originally guarding. It sounded pretty confused on the radio, and I think I’m only getting part of the conversation. Probably some face-to-face. They’ve split responsibility, so Charlie has the northern side of the defenses, and Bravo has the southern.

“Delta and a freshly reinforced Alpha company were the units trying to delay us, and they got mauled pretty bad. They’ve been merged to form a single company, though they reported that they’re still ‘substantially’ under-strength and disorganized. They didn’t have a solid number on how many casualties they took today, but they’re guessing about a hundred-plus.”

“That sounds about right for what logistics has picked up,” Dusty said with a nod. The non-combatants in our army hadn’t been at rest; as the army marched and fought, they’d roamed behind the lines, ferrying up ammo, and collecting bodies and equipment. “Last tally I heard was ninety six.” He frowned. “I’m still a little uncomfortable that there weren’t any wounded.”

I grimaced. Our own reports had come back, and while the total casualties were about the same, at least half of ours were wounded, with many expected to recover quickly. Then there was the substantial amount of equipment we had recovered, including sixteen sets of pegasus power armor in good enough condition to be rapidly pressed into service. The advantage of controlling the field after a battle, Dusty had said.

I continued. “The merged company, which took on the Alpha designation, was pulled back to the rear to rest and reorganize. They’ve brought forward Echo company instead, which sounds to be a mixed unit, like… reserves or something. It’s unclear. In any case, they deployed out here…” I scrolled the map two miles to the northeast, where a lone map marker—Echo flank—was tucked in a narrow valley. “Their orders are to wait until we start the assault, then press us from the flanks. They discussed using deception techniques to disrupt cohesion before shifting to regular tactics once we catch on. The plan is to disrupt the rear of our army and force it to close in with the front for safety, get us as condensed as possible, then hit us with the megaspell.”

“So we won’t be letting that happen,” Dusty said. “That’s going to be rough. We’ll need enough air defense forward to fend off any megaspell attempt, but that might expose them to the enemy defenses. Any word on heavy weapons?”

“Yes,” I said, scrolling back to the crossing. “At least two plasma cannons, one at each of the second pair of fortifications. Lighter equipment at the first pair, but still something. Maybe heavy machine-guns, by the sound of it. No word of artillery.”

“They probably don’t need it when they control the skies,” Dusty noted. “We might be able to capitalize on that.”

“Would be nice. There’s also a few separate units. Sky One through Three are air transports, probably skywagons, maybe sky-tanks. They’ve been mostly ferrying materials, and by last reports were lingering behind the force for further orders. Ghost One through Six are recon teams, and they’ve been roaming mostly on their own discretion, it seems. Then there’s another unit designated Mantis. No clear info on what that unit is, but it’s been relocated by Sky Two to this high ground here…” I scrolled to a rocky hill about half a mile west of the crossing. “Probably something that can’t be moved easily. Mantis has also been focused on vehicle sightings. It could be some sort of anti-vehicle unit.”

Dusty nodded again, eying the position. “Okay. Anything else?”

“Their HQ and some unit designated Cicada—I have no idea what it is—are stationed in a hasty bunker two hundred yards back from the second defensive line. Logistics units are based just past that, with several motorwagons to ferry supplies. I don’t know if any of that helps us. There was talk about bringing in reserves from the hive, but they aren’t expected to be deployed until the morning, and there were concerns about proper equipment.” I shrugged. “And their megaspell is out there, somewhere. They plan to have it come in from the west, but that’s likely to change.”

Dusty slowly looked over the map again, eying every contour and defensive position. “All right. So, three companies, plus one understrength, and some light support. That’s almost certainly more than the Mareford Militia itself, but we still should outnumber them with everypony else. Not counting however many reinforcements they’ll be getting.” He frowned thoughtfully, mulling it over before continuing. “Guess it comes down to how good their defenses are. Let’s take a look. Starlight? Bring us up. Be ready to pull back if they lob shots our way.”

The engine thrummed as the wagon slowly creeped up the slope. The crest of the hill steadily drew closer, until the top of the distant hills showed above it. A few yards later, and we came to a halt, the valley open before us, with the distant line of the Rotwater snaking through the rough terrain.

Dusty brought up his binoculars, surveying the battlefield. I did the same, giving a quick look over the features. The crossing itself was a low depression of rough, rocky ground, where the steep walls of the ravine gave way to a low valley and gentle slopes. It formed a ring of high-ground over the crossing, and it was here that Serenity chose to fight. For having just eight hours to prepare, they’d established some significant defences.

The front-most fortifications were made of concrete blocks, with metal brackets visible to hold them together and cover any gaps. They must have brought those in by skywagons. The front two were set right where each ravine ended, with the steep, rocky slopes effectively protecting their flanks. Each had a long, low slit to let the occupants fire out of. Curiously, they were not pointed forward to where we would be coming. Instead, each fortification—or pillbox, as Dusty called them—faced the other, three hundred yards apart.

Low walls had been established on the high ground, surrounding the crossing. Most of those walls were simply places where Serenity had dug up dirt and piled it in front of their positions. In some places, large canvas bags had been filled with dirt to form large blocks, which were then used to form walls. Then there were a few places, notably on either side of the pillboxes, where concrete slabs had been used as a backdrop, and the dirt piled in front of it. Some of the walls even extended out on the flanks of the pillboxes, lining the edge of the ravine for some twenty or thirty yards. It looked as though these positions would give good cover over the ravine and anyone attempting to climb out of them, preventing us from simply going around to get behind the fortifications. The intent was clear: they wanted to funnel our largely ground-bound force through the crossing itself, where they could maul us with the greatest amount of firepower.

The second defensive line was further up the gentle slope, allowing the positions to fire down on the crossing. It, too, was built around a pair of concrete fortifications, though it was less extensive. The pillboxes were actually slightly larger, with a second level of barriers surrounding the plasma cannons atop them, but the line of defensive walls were scattered points rather than a continuous line. It looked like this line relied more on the rocky terrain and curvature of the slope to give cover, with earthen walls formed where cover was lacking.

Between the two lines, changelings were hard at work. At least sixty were digging, piling up mounds of dirt as they hurriedly added low lines of walls leading back between the two defensive positions.

“Pretty serious defenses,” Dusty noted as I lowered my binoculars. Now that I had a good idea of the layout, my attention was better spent on the radios. “Looks like they know what they’re doing, too. They’re setting up secondary positions and cover for falling back. They’re going to make us fight for every inch, but they’re planning to give ground instead of dying on it.”

“Any way to go around?” Starlight asked.

“The nearest passable crossing is almost a day’s march south, and we can’t spare that much time if we’re going to beat the weather. Once the rain hits, that’s a couple more days for them to dig in. Besides, if we go for the other crossing, they can still get there first. We’d be facing the same thing there.”

“I mean something more, uh… local? I mean, sure, the motorwagons can’t climb a cliff, but maybe a bunch of soldiers could go around and hit them from behind?”

Dusty slowly shook his head. “They’ve got good recon, and I’m going to assume Whisper’s right about them having good espionage. If we detach any significant force, there’s a good chance Serenity would know exactly where they are. I don’t want to split our forces in the face of a more maneuverable enemy. Something small-scale, maybe… but the bulk of our thrust is going to have to be right down their throat.”

Sickle snickered.

In my left ear, a conversation about logistics and rations was suddenly interrupted. “Break, break. Command, Mantis. Eyes on enemy command wagon, one one zero from our position, skylined on ‘enemy ridge’. Request permission to engage.”

Adrenaline came crashing down. “Dusty! Mantis sees us, and they want to shoot.”

He nodded calmly. “Starlight, roll us back.”

The motorwagon rocked as we drew back. I caught one last glimpse of the tall hill and its sheer cliffs, a mile away, before we slipped out of sight. “Heck of a reach they’ve got.”

Dusty grunted.

“Mantis, Command. Negative. Hold fire for now. Keep eyes on them. Current intent is you will wait until the enemy forces are engaged in their attack, then take them out to disrupt leadership.”

“Understood. Enemy command vic has withdrawn, now out of sight. They have something floating tethered to their vehicle, so we’ll track their position.”

“Command copies.”

Crap. “Dusty? I didn’t really think of it, but they can still see the antenna, so they still know where we are.”

“Of course,” he said, his eyes back on his PipBuck’s map. “I’m still trying to think if there’s some way to make use of that, lure them in or trick them or something. Still coming up blank there.”

I paused for a moment, thinking on the possibility of misdirection, before giving a shrug. “Nothing comes to mind.”

“Yeah.” He sighed, silent for several long seconds. “Well, no point in delaying. Time to call everypony in.”

He brought up his broadcaster, and a minute later, leaders started converging on our position.

☢

Fifteen minutes later, we were all gathered. Dusty hadn’t bothered setting up the tent this time, so we gathered in a level patch of ground, flanked by our motorwagon and Sandstorm’s tank. All the leaders were there. Sandstorm and Axle, Two Bits, Hail Burst, Dazzle, Seroon, and at least a dozen subordinates. All gathered around the table where Dusty had sketched out a rough layout.

He gave one final look over the group. “Okay. I’m not a big speech type of pony, so I’m not going to bore you with some big monologue about honor or destiny or any of that, but there’s one thing I do need to say: the fight here is going to be a big one. Probably the big one. What we do here may well decide whether we win or lose. We’ve hammered them all day long, driven them back, but now they’re making a stand. If we can do what we’ve done all day, if we can deal them one more decisive defeat, then there will be nothing lying between us and their hive. They’ve been running from us all day. Now they’re standing and fighting. If we can push on just a little longer and crush them here, we win.”

There were murmurs and nods of approval.

“I know we’re all tired after a day of marching, but they’ve had it worse than us. We’ve chased them across the Wasteland. They’ve been battered and bloodied. Right now, they need a chance to rest and recover. We’re not going to give it to them. We need to hit them before they dig in so hard that we’ll never uproot them. That means we need to hit them soon, we need to hit them hard, and we need to hit them smart.”

He took a half step back, leading into the part we had rehearsed. “Now then, I’ve been discussing the situation with Queen Whisper, and she has a few things to say about our enemy.”

I nodded in gratitude before stepping up to the table. All eyes turned to me. There were no glares or looks of suspicion. All listened attentively.

“We’re about to face a larger and more chaotic fight than most of us have ever experienced. Chaos leads to confusion, and this is something changelings are adept at exploiting. We’ve seen only a little of such trickery so far, but if they’re making a stand here, we can expect they’ll pull out every trick in the book. My kind’s greatest advantage is our shapeshifting ability. Changelings can look like anyone.” I put on a particularly grave and serious face. “This includes friendly soldiers on the battlefield.”

There were a few frowns and grimaces at this. Good. “Not only do we run the risk of having Serenity forces approach under the guise of friendly units, we run the risk of fighting our own forces if they mistake each other for changelings. We can’t allow that to happen. To that end, it’s going to be vital that commanders keep accountability. We have good communications. Know where your subordinates are, and know where nearby friendly forces are. As long as you do this, we’ll be able to punish them for any attempt, and deprive Serenity of its greatest advantage.

“Above all, I would suggest restraint and caution. We don’t want to kill friendly forces just because we had a lapse in communication. If absolutely uncertain, keep suspicious groups at a distance and call for information.” I raised my PipBuck. “I will also be monitoring friendly radio traffic and tracking movements. If any suspicious circumstances arise, you can always ask Dusty, and we will be able to get to the bottom of it.”

I frowned. “And beware of individuals giving suspicious instructions or attempting to go somewhere or do something they aren’t normally allowed to do. It’s very likely Serenity have some Infiltrators in the army. If there’s any doubt about what someone says, stop them until you can contact someone higher up to confirm it.”

There were a few more nods, even if some ponies still looked concerned. When no questions or objections were voiced, Dusty stepped up again. “So we’ve got a lot to do,” he said. “This is what I want…”

I stood back, listening intently to every plan and detail, as Dusty slowly wove together a picture of what was about to unfold.

Chapter Forty Five: The Rot

Any endeavor is a long and complex chain of events. Despite the natural attraction one might feel toward the dramatic, it’s important to always remember that there is no one critical moment that is the sole deciding factor. Every single moment, no matter how mundane, leads us steadily to the outcome. It is this principle that must guide an Infiltrator.

Yes, the end goal may be some climactic event, but it is never alone. When we look at some great task, such as infiltrating a hostile government, it might well seem as monumental as climbing a mighty mountain, but even the greatest mountain is climbed one step at a time. These are the steps we plan out. The ones we train for.

Despite this, there is no denying that some moments are more significant than others. Some moments are crucial. These moments test us in new ways. While the bulk of our training is rooted in the mundane moments, those simple masquerades and deceptions that serve us daily, we have to be ready for whatever comes our way. This is why our training teaches the basic elements of a wide range of subjects we hope may never come into play. We have to have breadth to handle unexpected circumstances. We have to be flexible, adapting to a situation that is never wholly in our control.

And we have to be ready to do things we may not be entirely comfortable with. This is why I was in my natural form, while Echo stuffed me into the set of power armor she had been fixated on for the past two days.

“I must say, I am very thankful for Sergeant Hail Burst’s accommodation in allowing me access to the salvaged Serenity armors,” she happily informed me as she double-checked the connection of one foreleg’s armor. “I had been concerned about the potential weak point that would be created if I had to cut a hole in the helmet for your horn, since I am certain you would have objected to being unable to use your magic, but Serenity has quite nicely alleviated us of that concern.”

“Yes, we are quite fortunate,” I dryly replied as I used said magic to adjust how the helmet sat. Serenity’s simple addition to the helmet fit snugly around my horn. Its curve matched almost perfectly, with thick padding to protect against impact, while the external metal shell curved up to a sharp tip. The world outside was tinted faintly amber by the helmet’s lenses, and the E.F.S. was arranged in a completely different fashion. I didn’t particularly care for it, but I could adapt.

She gave a sharp tug on the armored hoof before releasing it. “There. It is all secure. I would still recommend against getting shot, but at least you are not so terribly vulnerable.”

“I’m never going to be closer than half a mile from the fighting,” I said, looking up to track the Loyalist skywagon that flew swiftly overhead, helping with some final relocations. The army was all hurrying through last-minute preparations for our hasty assault, with most of them well forward of where I was.

“Yes, and they have weapons that can easily reach that far,” she said with a frown. The dull thump of a distant explosion punctuated her in a way that might seem dramatically convenient if it wasn’t happening every ten or twenty seconds. Serenity was putting out a low volume of fire with the plasma cannons and a few other heavy magical weapons. It wasn’t enough to be a danger, yet, but Dusty said that wasn’t the point. They were just trying to discourage us from poking our heads up. The longer they delayed us, the better off they were.

“I’ll be fine,” I said, lifting a leg to reach out, testing it. The armor felt rigid and somewhat bulky, yet no more heavy than the armor I had taken from my hive. Maybe lighter. “Besides, even if they didn’t have more important things to focus on, I’m wearing this. I’m about as safe as I could be.”

She stood tall to stare down over her upturned frown. “You know as well as I that their soldiers are not the only threat to you, and I suspect you are only wearing that armor because I made it a condition of leaving your side.”

“I was going to wear the armor anyway,” I said, which I think was probably true. “But it still made for a good bargaining chip.”

She snorted, holding her disapproving glare.

“Anyway,” I said, then paused as I looked around for a time display on the armor’s E.F.S. Not finding one—probably one of the options I didn’t understand yet—I sighed and levitated my PipBuck. “Yeah, you’d better get going. It’s getting close to that time. You’ve got everything?”

“I do,” she said as she levitated the saddlebags that lay beside her. They floated up to drape across her back, the straps buckling as she spoke. “You should attach the face mask. Leaving your muzzle exposed is a vulnerability.”

“I need to talk to Dusty, and I’d rather not be announcing things loudly over some speakers. I’ll close up if anything bad happens.”

“Hmmph. I suppose that will do.” She spread her wings. “Be safe.”

“As safe as I can. Good luck.”

She gave a sharp nod, then gave a powerful beat of her wings. As the dust parted, she arced off to the east and climbed, heading away from the battlefield. Soon she would be ascending into the clouds. I double-checked the time. Twelve minutes. That should be plenty.

I turned, careful and conscious of every movement. Despite the heavy appearance, the armor only barely restricted my range of motion, and my movement was hardly impaired. It was almost eerie. There was some powerful enchantment going on to turn what should have been easily a hundred pounds or more of metal into something as light and easy to wear as a thin jacket.

I paced back and forth a few times, getting used to the feel. Even my hoofsteps felt light. Looking at my armored hoof, I expected deep thumps every time I touched the dirt, but there was only the faint sound of dry earth softly crunching. It was a strange disconnect between appearance and behavior, similar to the feeling of a peculiarly botched shapeshifting, but even though that strangeness lingered, it was trivial to adapt to the physical sensation of it.

I wouldn’t say I liked the armor, but I was certainly impressed by it.

The wings still annoyed me, though. Serenity had made some slight modifications to accommodate changeling wings, but they felt remarkably clumsy to me. No amount of enchantment could get rid of the fact that they covered my light, diaphanous wings with thick plates intended to cover a heavy, feathered wing. I had resolved the issue of the helmet and neck armor crushing my dorsal frill by shifting it away, and I was tempted to give myself more pony-like wings, but I decided there wasn’t much point. It’d be bulky either way.

As for the tail, it was still something of a mystery. I could get it to move around some with flicks of my tail, but how exactly a pegasus could stab someone with that tail-tip stinger completely escaped me. I just hoped I wouldn’t accidentally discover it at an inopportune moment.

Setting aside those concerns, I made my way back to the ridge. There was plenty of activity all around. Gemstone and Mareford ponies hustled back and forth, ferrying supplies and preparing heavy weapons just behind the crest. Our motorwagon sat a good fifty feet back from the ridge, facing down the slope. Bloodbeak stood alertly in the back, a set of talons resting atop the rear of the machine gun. She smiled as I looked up to her.

“You all good here?” I asked, and her smile grew.

“You bet!” She patted the gun. “I got your back.”

“Good to hear,” I said, returning the smile. Turning, I followed the cable that led from the base of our tethered antennas to the position we had prepared. Echo hadn’t just tucked me in that bizarrely light metal can. She’d used her powerful telekinesis to tear up a good section of ground, digging a wide trench along the crest of the ridge in a matter of seconds. The position gave us excellent cover, and all we had to do was poke up over the front edge to get a good look over the soon-to-be battlefield.

Dusty was doing exactly that as I stepped into the trench. Two Bits was there, too, discussing a few last-minute details. I simply gave them a nod before turning to the collection of PipBucks arranged at one end of the trench. It took a moment to fish out the earbud cable, which I had tucked into the neck armor, and plug it into a pair of the PipBucks. It wasn’t the most elegant solution; I’d have to take some time to work out a patch to plug those radios into the armor itself, but that would have to wait.

Serenity’s radio traffic was unchanged. Some low-level chatter, some reports from scouts, but nothing high-level. Nothing interesting.

A couple of minutes later, Two Bits excused himself, slipping out of the trench to move to his own position, just fifty feet away; close enough for him and Dusty to yell back and forth if necessary, but separate enough that they wouldn’t be talking over each other, or taken out by the same lucky shot. Dazzle and a couple of other Gemstone ponies occupied a similar position beyond that, near where most of the energy weapons were currently hidden. Sandstorm, on the other hoof, sat in the hatch of her tank, leaving Axle on hoof to coordinate things for her, and Hail Burst was flying around with her Loyalists, keeping an eye on the skies.

As soon as Two Bits was gone, Dusty sat down behind the wall, looking to me. “Anything going on on Serenity’s side?”

“Nothing,” I said, frowning. “They’re waiting for us to make a move. It feels like a trap.”

“Sure, it’s a trap,” Dusty said, rising up to peer out over the valley again. “At least, that’s what they want it to be, but they’re wrong. They’re making a mistake, and I intend to punish them for it.”

“It doesn’t seem like much—” I stopped as Dusty crouched, followed a moment later by the loud, unnatural fwump of a plasma-bolt striking the face of the ridge in front of us, casting a light shower of dirt over us. He was already up and looking again before I spoke again. “I mean, I know I’m not all that versed in strategy, but it doesn’t seem like much of a mistake to me. It seems to me like this is going to be a nasty fight.”

“Oh, it’s going to be bloody,” Dusty noted, a faint grimace touching his expression. “But they’re playing this whole thing wrong. They only put a quarter of their force to delaying us. They underestimated us, and they got their tails handed to them for it. It scared them, so they’re focusing hard on defenses. It’s a conservative strategy. It’s also the wrong one.”

“Why’s that?”

“Because they’re ceding the initiative. They’re going full reactive. Worse, they’re letting us press a decisive battle where we can level the strengths of our forces. You know what they should have learned from today? That they should harass and delay us with all of their force, so we could never leverage a local superiority in numbers. Hit us too frequently and in too many places to respond, and with enough supporting force that they don’t leave weaknesses for us to exploit. We saw enough of how they fought. Their soldiers are solid, and they seem to have good tactics. If they fought to their strengths, it’d be brutal. Your intel would keep it from being as bad as it could be, but it’d cost us, and probably slow the army to a crawl. A few days of that, and they’d steadily pick us apart until we can’t fight them off. But this? They got stung, and now they’re too cautious of getting stung again.”

I was silent for several seconds, pondering that explanation. In most ways, it was perfectly familiar. It was very much like my lessons on practical psychology, as well as my training in threat management and deception. It’s natural to react to a threat or setback with caution, but it’s too easy to overdo it. Falling back to a purely reactive stance might defend against some danger, but it rarely does anything to resolve the cause of that danger. If somepony is suspicious of an Infiltrator, a reactionary stance would be to come up with some lie that alleviates that suspicion. That’s all well and good, but it’s often not enough. Whatever reason that existed to arouse their suspicion could still exist, leading to other ponies getting suspicious, and some may take steps that are not so easily reacted to. That’s why it’s important to be proactive in identifying and removing those threats.

This is also useful knowledge when it comes to manipulation and deception. If you can force someone into a reactionary stance, perhaps by overwhelming their argument with your own statements until they’re focused entirely on responding to you instead of pressing their own arguments, then you can control the course and flow of the conversation for your own benefit. Similarly, you have to know how to avoid being trapped in such a disadvantaged position by others.

Some of my teachers had used an analogy that compared conversations with battles, but Dusty’s words made that comparison all the more apt.

Dusty had turned back to his PipBuck. “It’s about time. Echo’s good?”

“She had plenty of time,” I said with a nod. I glanced at one of my PipBucks. Six minutes. Halfway there.

“Good,” Dusty said, then raised his PipBuck to broadcast. “All forces, Command. Report status.”

Two Bit’s reply was almost instant. “Command, Ranger Lead. We’ve got a few units still getting into position. Should be set in one minute.”

“Command, Loyal Lead. All Enclave forces are ready.”

“This is Sandstorm. We’ve been ready for half a fucking hour.”

“Gemstone’s ready.”

Dusty silently nodded to himself as he switched to our private channel. “Starlight, are you all set?”

“Yep.” Her voice sounded light. Not quite cheerful, but close enough to be encouraging. “It isn’t too tricky of a shot, assuming I can damage that thing. I got this.”

“Just remember,” Dusty said. “One shot, then get behind cover immediately. Don’t wait to observe the shot. We can do that for you. Pull back and relocate. We’ll be giving you as much distraction as possible, but let’s not take chances.”

“Yeah, I remember,” Starlight said, with only the tiniest hint of the eye-roll she was likely giving. I caught Dusty’s momentary frown, but he said nothing.

I raised my head to look off to our left, down along the ridge. Starlight was somewhere out there, just a couple hundred yards away, but I couldn’t see her in the rough terrain. The rocky protrusions and uneven roll of the hill made for excellent cover, which would have been an even greater advantage if it wasn’t half a mile from the crossing.

For some weapons, half a mile wasn’t quite so daunting.

The radio came to life again. “Command, Ranger Lead. Mareford is set and ready.”

“Command copies,” Dusty said, looking down at his PipBuck again. “All forces, be prepared to go in one minute. Ranger Lead, start ranging shots.”

I scanned steadily through the Serenity channels. Nothing yet. The scout channel was reporting on several ponies loading into motorwagons on our northern flank, but nothing critical.

A few seconds later, I heard the shouts from further up the ridge. I raised my head again to look.

About a hundred yards away, and just behind the ridge itself, about a dozen Mareford ponies were gathered around their mortars. There were three of them, including the one Dusty had lent them. They had a good stockpile of ammunition, courtesy of Mareford’s industry, and Dusty was intent on putting them to good use.

One of the ponies brought a mortar round to the muzzle of their mortar, holding it for a moment before releasing and turning away, hooves going to her ears. There was a flash and a thump, kicking up a thin cloud of dust that steadily drifted away behind them. Seconds later another pony repeated the action with another mortar.

I stood to look out across the valley. I could just make out some movement around some of the fallback positions, where soldiers were still digging. It was maybe five seconds from the first shot when an urgent report came across the scout channel. “Command! The pony mortar group just fired two rounds.”

It was another ten seconds before the Serenity commander came on the main channel to spread the warning. She barely had time to finish before the flash and spray of dirt announced the arrival of the first round. It had landed maybe fifteen yards past the wall along the left side of the front line of walls. Seconds later the second round burst, just past the right pillbox. A pair of ponies with binoculars were already shouting back information to the mortar teams.

Two Bits radioed seconds later. “Command, mortars are on target and ready.”

Dusty drew in a deep breath, exhaled, and keyed in again. “Fire for effect. All forces, standby to initiate when the first rounds land.”

I only distantly heard the shout before a trio of thumps sounded in rapid sequence, followed seconds later by three more.

“Command, splash in… twenty seconds.”

The shots were going out rapidly, every few seconds. I understood the purpose of the ranging rounds, but it seemed unfortunate that we would give them so much warning. Serenity’s soldiers could hunker down, minimizing casualties. Dusty, however, was unconcerned. He had told me earlier that any casualties would be a nice bonus, but killing wasn’t their intent.

He sat there, eyes on his PipBuck’s clock as he counted down the seconds. Finally he radioed again. “All forces, Command…” His eyes flicked up, and a second later the rounds impacted. “Go.”

All along the ridge, ponies sprang into action. Heavy weapons, ranging from machine guns to salvaged plasma cannons, were hauled up by teams of ponies, rushing them into hastily prepared positions. A deep rumble and roar sounded as Sandstorm’s Beast climbed the steep slope, until the tank’s cannon rose above the ridge. Already, the first flashes of Gemstone rifles were filling the air with a rainbow of bolts and lines.

I glanced down at my PipBuck again. Four minutes.

Serenity was returning fire. Bolts of burning fuchsia magic sailed through the air in sporadic streams, but at this range, they were no more effective than Gemstone’s shots. More impressive were the plasma cannons atop the rear pillboxes. One was already putting out slow, steady fire, about one per second. The powerful bolts impacted the ridge far to my right like a meteor, throwing dirt and rocks.

I didn’t see if it hit anypony. I didn’t look. I focused on my radios as Serenity traffic spiked. Word was going out that there was a full-scale attack. I knew the Mareford and Trotsen attack force should be moving by then, using the suppression of the mortars and the supporting fire to get into better positions, where they could level their own heavy firepower on the defenses facing them.

In the distance, I heard Sandstorm’s shout. Then I saw the flash of the Beast’s cannon, and the sound hit me like a ton of bricks, even through the armor. The blast kicked up a thick cloud of dust. For a second, I was blinded, but as the dust washed away, I saw the plume of smoke and dirt where the round had landed, maybe five yards short of one of the rear pillboxes.

Our private channel came alive with Dusty’s voice. “Starlight, you’re up.”

“Got it.”

For several seconds, the combat continued unchanged. The heavy weapons were all firing by now, the variety of magical energy cannons backed by a few machine guns. The front line of walls was blanketed in flashes of magic, dirt, and smoke. The second line was taking less fire, but still some. Despite all that, it was easy enough to pick out the Lancer’s brilliant red beam as it speared the left-most plasma cannon. There was a sickly multi-colored flash that blossomed from the side of the cannon as a spark battery discharged.

Dusty was already calling out as I raised my binoculars. “Good effect on target. They’re still up, but I think you did some serious damage. Put your next shot into the other one.”

I finally lined up, seeing the cannon swing around to face where the shot had come from, but it wasn’t firing. I could just make out one changeling helping another up from where she’d been knocked over, and from what little I could see of her movements, she was either injured or dazed by the small explosion. Others were hauling equipment around behind it, connecting something flexible. A power cable, I would guess.

My vision turned to dust, and I reflexively ducked as the Beast fired again. When the dust had cleared and I peered out again, I could see the smoke wafting away from the face of the pillbox. The intact plasma cannon atop it was firing back, with powerful bolts slamming into the hill in front of the tank or sailing overhead. It was a hard target; the tank had advanced just enough to bring the cannon clear. Still, the shots were close, and when one sent a spray of dirt over the tank, Sandstorm finally ducked down into the turret, swinging the hatch shut.

I cast a quick glance to my PipBuck. Three minutes.

My left earbud spoke again. “Mantis, Command. Priority target, enemy armor on ‘enemy ridge’. Engage at will.”

“Mantis copies. Engaging.”

“Dusty!” I called out over the sound of the impacts. “Mantis just got the order to fire on the tank!”

He gave one glance Sandstorm’s way, then turned back to his radio. “Sandstorm, you’re taking cannon fire. Pull back.”

On the distant hill, a mile away, I saw a tiny puff of smoke.

Dusty saw it too. He immediately keyed in, his voice quick but calm. Efficient. “Gemstone, Command. Possible enemy heavy weapons team, bearing two nine zero degrees, the flat hilltop one mile away. I want one of your guns to plaster that entire hilltop.”

As he was speaking, I noticed a small flicker by the distant hill. I couldn’t even be sure I saw it at first. Then I caught a hint of movement again, like something wobbling in midair. It seemed so still, even as I started to pick out a hint of smoke weaving behind it. I realized what I was seeing the instant the illusion of stillness was shattered, as the black missile shrieked across that final distance and smashed into Sandstorm’s Beast.

A flash, and the tank was engulfed in a fireball. The blast was deafening. The massive turret crashed down beside the tank, blown entirely clear of the chassis. Fire roared in the mangled wreck of what had been its hull, now torn apart by the massive explosion.

Explosives love small, enclosed spaces, and the ammunition the Beast had carried was a tremendous amount of explosives.

I stared, stunned by the sight. A voice bloomed in my left ear, calm and dispassionate. “Command, Mantis. Armor neutralized.”

Dusty uttered a quiet curse before calling out to me. “Whisper, get on Trotsen’s channel. Make sure Axle knows he’s in charge and get him on the command channel.”

I’m pretty sure Axle knew, at least on some level. He was already scrambling up from his position to run toward the flaming wreckage, as if he might somehow save Sandstorm. Despite that, I quickly shook myself from my daze and followed directions, changing channels before hitting the button to transmit. “Axle, you’re in charge of the Trotsen forces. Dusty wants you on channel one if you’re not already.”

I saw him freeze, looking down at his PipBuck. Several voices called out over the radio, voicing questions and concerns, until he slapped at his broadcaster and shouted over them. “She’s fucking dead!”

“What?” one of the voices asked.

“The fucking bugs,” Axle said, wavering in place as he looked at the flaming hulk of the tank. “They fucking blew her up!”

“Sandstorm?”

“Yes!” He shouted loud enough that I could hear his voice, even over the continuing impacts of incoming fire. “Those motherfuckers killed her! Those… fuck! We’re going to kill every fucking last one of them!”

I keyed in again. “Axle, tune into channel one. We’ll make sure you get your chance.”

I heard him shout, some sound of anguish, before fiddling with his PipBuck.

Then Dusty shouted. “Get down!”

I ducked an instant before the blast of an explosion hammered my ears. Dusty was already calling out on the radio before I could get up. “Gemstone, command! I need fire on that hilltop immediately before they pick us all off. Do you copy?”

Dazzle’s voice answered immediately. “Got it!”

When I picked myself up, I looked up along the ridge, spotting the smoke and dust blowing away from one of the many rocky positions. Part of the plasma cannon was still there, burning with magical fire. Bits of the cannon—I hoped—were scattered around it.

A few lines of searing light cut through the air, kicking up glowing motes of dust from the distant hill. A moment later, a flash of multicolored light drew my attention back to the valley. The northern plasma cannon had just exploded in a burst of spark-energy.

Dusty echoed in my right ear. “Good effect on target, Star. Shift target, engage Mantis hill. You’re on that until I call again.”

“Okay! Did you see that explosion?”

“Focus,” Dusty chided before switching back to the command channel.

I refocused on my radios. There still wasn’t much happening on their command network. There were reports of our movements, noting how they saw a significant force taking position on the northern side of the approaches, and relatively few on the southern side. I didn’t catch any significant inaccuracies that we could exploit. For a moment, it was relatively calm, so long as one ignored the sounds of weapon fire and mostly-distant explosions. The mortars had stopped firing, for what that was worth.

Starlight radioed in. “Hey, Dusty. Yeah, they’ve got like a half-dozen Steel Ranger armors on that hill. I spotted at least one big-ass missile launcher, but I think Dazzle tagged that guy. They’re keeping their heads down now.”

“Copy,” Dusty replied. “Keep them suppressed.”

“Can do!”

I glanced at the clock again. Two minutes. Standing, I rose high enough to look down the slope into the valley. The rough terrain opened up near the crossing. Mareford ponies had made good use of the suppressing fire to take up positions just two hundred yards from the crossing itself, and were exchanging fire with the defenders. As Serenity had noted, about two thirds were gathered on the right side. The nearest pillbox, with its side-facing opening, couldn’t fire on them, but the one on the far side was spewing a rapid stream of bolts. One of the lighter, faster-firing plasma cannons, I assumed.

Just behind the Mareford soldiers, a few motorwagons were tucked into narrow depressions. They had been guided by ponies on hoof, and protected from return fire by the rolling terrain. It was the closest they could get without being completely exposed.

Two Bits called in again. “Command, Ranger Lead. Mareford forces are in position and reee-eeee ooooh begin assauuuu on yoooo c-mand.”

My ears flattened as the broadcast was abruptly filled with audio artifacts. A quick glance showed the floating antenna was still up.

“Command copies,” Dusty said, speaking with deliberate precision. “Be aware, your transmission is loud but distorted.” He released the button, shooting me a glance. “What’s going on?”

“Under-oood,” Two Bits replied, barely recognizable as the decryption software struggled to decipher the audio stream correctly. “Hevvv interf-errrr.”

“I’m not sure.” I sorted through my collection of PipBucks, finding the one monitoring all of our channels. Every single one was lit up, with only the occasional flicker. “...Oh! Right. I think they’re trying to jam us again.”

“Can you do anything about it?”

I frowned down at the PipBuck. “Maybe if we could get everyone on another frequency, but… well, we’re not doing that in combat. That’d take forever, especially if they can’t hear us. And they’d just change the frequency they’re jamming. No good.” I stared for another moment before lurching into action, pulling the antenna cable from my PipBuck array. The sounds in my ear grew even more distorted. “Here, swap me. The main antenna should give a stronger signal. That might make a difference.”

He unplugged his own cable, and we traded. Friendly transmissions were even more garbled. I couldn’t even place whose voice it was I heard.

Ironically, I could make out the Serenity transmission far more clearly than our own. “Echo, Command. Move to engage enemy forces.”

“Echo copies. ETA four minutes.”

I looked over to Dusty. “Echo is moving.” I paused, blinked. “I mean, Echo company. Serenity’s Echo. Not our Echo. Oof, that’s a mess.” I shook my head, then added. “They’re four minutes out.”

He glanced down to his PipBuck, then nodded. “Good. We’ve got time.”

I looked as well. One minute.

Serenity’s commander was on the radio again. “Brachinus, proceed to holding position and standby.”

The reply was distant and softly distorted. “Brachinus copies.”

The faint tingle of adrenaline ran down my spine. Their megaspell was readying to strike.

Mantis was reporting that they were unable to engage when Dusty keyed in again. “All forces, Command. Prepare for phase two in… thirty seconds.”

I glanced to the time again, seconds ticking away. Garbled voices called in on the radio, presumably to give acknowledgement.

Seconds passed, while the two armies exchanged fire. Serenity’s remaining heavy plasma cannon had fallen silent, perhaps too damaged by Starlight’s strike to function, but the soldiers were putting out heavy fire, filling the air with death. The Mareford soldiers were weathering it well, taking good cover and replying in kind. For the moment, it was indecisive.

Dusty’s hoof raised, holding in wait. The final seconds counted down with agonizing slowness.

Then Dusty’s hoof came down, pointing to me.

I keyed in on our private channel. “Echo, start your run.”

It was a formality. She’d been told to carry out her instructions unless we told her otherwise. Too much rode on her.

Dusty and I looked up, to the darkened clouds above Serenity’s position. His hoof hovered over his broadcaster.

For several long seconds, nothing. Then, a dot of dark purple plunged from the clouds.

Dusty’s hoof jabbed at the button. “All forces, go for phase two. Go!”

In the distance, Echo’s wings pumped as she accelerated towards the earth. Within moments, the mortars were firing in rapid succession. Magical energy cannons fired as fast as they could. Machine guns rattled in long bursts. In the valley, soldiers would be loading into motorwagons while others lay down heavy suppressing fire. Behind us, Hail Burst and her Loyalists sprang into the air, their heavily laden skywagon following close on their tails.

Echo streaked downward, wings tucking in along her sides in a high-speed stoop, straight toward the Serenity forces. It was several seconds before Serenity soldiers spotted Echo’s meteoric descent. Her shield snapped into existence as several bolts sailed up to meet her. Her wings spread, abruptly pulling up from her dive, still a couple of hundred yards above the ground.

Their commander was on the line again. “Mantis, Command. You will relocate to ridge three-one-three. Sky Two will mo—”

At that distance, I couldn’t see the flash of Echo’s magic.

What followed, however, was impossible to miss. The flash of green lit up the western edge of the valley. The sickly green balefire burst out from the rear of the Serenity army. It rose into the sky, flinging the concrete and other debris into the air. Echo’s aim had been perfect. The Serenity commander’s transmission cut off mid-word.

The radio cleared immediately to Hail Burst’s voice. “—beginning our run now.” Serenity’s jammer had been right there with their headquarters.

A second flash announced another detonation, just past the first. Another green fireball rose above the ridge, followed by a rapid series of secondary explosions. The sickly multicolored hue of spark-battery detonations mixed with the balefire green as the fireball grew well beyond the first. Echo had teleported the second balefire egg right into the middle of their logistics company, detonating motorwagons and stocks of spark batteries.

Echo streaked away from the explosions as the Serenity radio descended into chaos.

“Command, Mantis. Say again.”

“Command, what the fuck was that?”

“Enemies rear! Logi just got hit!”

“Command, Ghost Two. Please respond, urgent.”

“I think command is down.”

I turned to the southern end of the Serenity lines, just in time to see the Loyalists sweep over the nearest ridge, flying low. They opened fire immediately, laying out a heavy storm of magical fire all along the southern walls. The defenders were shooting at the ground forces in the opposite direction; by the time the first shots turned to the new threat, the Loyalists were already banking away.

Among all the flashes and bolts of magic, it was easy to overlook the slower green orb that arced downward from one of the Loyalists, until the third and final balefire egg landed right at the rear of the pillbox. I got to see the full power of the deceptively tiny device. Alchemical fire burst forth, tearing through and consuming everything in its wake. The pillbox disintegrated, flinging slabs of concrete out across the slope before it.

Sheltered by the nearby ridge, the Loyalist skywagon was disgorging ponies. Rangers rushed to the crest of the ridge, and within seconds were laying out heavy fire on the surviving Serenity forces. The moment the skywagon was empty, it lurched and took off, and the Loyalists followed it back to friendly territory.

The chaos continued.

“Bravo lead is down! Bravo is under attack by heavy Enclave forces from the south. In danger of being overrun.”

“This is Alpha. What happened to command?”

“Command is down. All of HQ and Logi is down.”

“Who’s in charge?”

“I think you are!”

On the right side, Mareford soldiers had advanced almost to the creek itself, braving the rough and exposed ground as the fighting intensified. Mortars rained down on the line of walls, throwing up plumes of dirt and smoke. A few changelings braved the intense suppressive fire in an attempt to engage the closing ponies, but they were quickly forced down again. The defenses on the left side of the crossing, which should have been providing a crossfire, were too tied up in their own fight to help. It gave the soldiers time, as specialist unicorns quickly found and removed enemy mines, clearing the way.

A couple of weapons teams dashed up behind the lead squad, finding a cluster of small rocks that gave a small degree of cover. Even from that distance, I could clearly see the large tubes mounted on the side of two of the stallions. They took position, aiming at the pillbox less than a hundred yards away. Dust kicked up in an abrupt spray behind them, and a pair of explosions blossomed from the side of the pillbox. Immediately, assistants moved to the rear of the launchers, loading the next round. From that far away, I couldn’t tell if they’d done any more than scorch the side of the pillbox.

“Command—whoever!—this is Bravo!” the distant changeling called out on the radio, shouting over the sound of weapons fire and explosions. “We are overrun! We can not hold. We are pulling back!”

I leaned over toward Dusty. “The southern defenders are trying to retreat.”

He nodded grimly, but said nothing. There wasn’t much to say. It didn’t take a tactical genius to see that the defenses they had prepared to cover their withdrawal did nothing to protect from an enemy that had gotten behind them. They’d be retreating through open ground and air, right in the sights of everypony. The situation was getting worse for them by the moment. Already, the skywagon was lifting from the Mareford positions, with a fresh load of ponies inside and the rest of the Loyalists flying cover overhead.

Back on the right side, ponies had pushed up to the edge of the ravine and the steep slope below the pillbox. Motorwagons bounced across the rocky ground, taking only light fire as they made the quick dash. Equipment bounced haphazardly in the back of the wagons, while ponies clung on. I could see Sickle’s distinctive armor among them.

Small explosions peppered the top of the ridge as ponies threw grenades over the walls. Only a few grenades answered them, and the whole area was quickly choked in smoke and dust. Then the Mareford ponies stepped up the game. I knew the plan; one of the groups in the assault force was a demolition team. I could see the massive demolition charge float up in the grip of some unicorn’s magic until it was placed right against the pillbox.

It was nothing in comparison to a balefire egg, but the blast still made the grenades look anemic. It was also sufficient for the job, blowing a large, ragged hole in the side of the pillbox, probably killing or incapacitating anyone inside.

The motorwagons closed the final distance, halting at the base of the rocky slope. Ladders went up as other ponies started advancing along the low-ground before the pillbox. The mortars had stopped, the suppressing fire moving back to the second line of defenses.

Ponies climbed up the slope. I saw Sickle shove her way past another pony, bounding up to the pillbox and rushing in.

Dusty looked back down to his PipBuck, considered a moment, then hit the key to transmit. “Gemstone, Command. I need the right half of your guns all facing north. Enemy fliers spotted inbound from the north. Ranger Lead, they should be coming in over your reserve forces. Make sure they’re ready to meet the threat. Loyal Lead, I’ll need you back over the northern ridge for a counterattack. Skywagon’s flight should be safe.”

Acknowledgements came in on our command channel. Serenity’s command channel was still disjointed. Someone had finally assumed command, and was calling for everyling to fall back to the second line. The alarmed report of enemies attacking their logistics team circulated, diverting some of the second-line forces to defend against an enemy that didn’t exist. Some changelings tried to fight back, while others tried to break out, all to little effect. Their flanking force, expecting some degree of surprise, came over the final ridge to find themselves facing fully prepared defenders with multiple heavy magical energy cannons. The scouts that had seen the preparations were unable to get that information across the proper channels. Confusion ran rampant.

“Command, this is Brachinus. Are we engaging?”

“Yes!” the urgent reply came. “We’re in danger of being overrun. Engage immediately!”

“Brachinus copies. Turning inbound. Time on target, eight minutes.”

I passed the information on to Dusty. He nodded, glanced at the time on his PipBuck, and returned to watching the battle, all without a word.

“Brachinus, expedite! We need you ASAP.”

“Brachinus copies. Unable. Best time is eight minutes.”

“We’re not going to be here in eight minutes!”

I leaned toward Dusty, speaking quietly. “Serenity command is stressed. I think they’re losing it.”

Another transmission. “Brachinus copies. Time on target, eight minutes.”

I know it was probably just calm professionalism, but something about the reply just felt cold to me.

At this point, there was very little for me to do but relay basic information. Even that was made difficult by the utter confusion on Serenity’s part. Bravo company had been asked three times for a status report, but had stopped responding on the radio. Alpha had been called in to reinforce, but were taking time to sweep the hills behind Serenity’s position to clear out the mysterious attackers some startled changeling had called out in error. Echo had taken light casualties in their attack, but only because of the quick thinking of their commander ordering them to pull back. They prowled around the edges, but between the Whirligigs and Loyalists circling above, their movements were tracked, and Gemstone’s weapons were ready to meet them anywhere they went.

There was still a battle raging on, but it felt almost calm. Controlled.

Then shouts and a burst of gunfire shook me from the illusion. I looked back behind our trench, to where dust wafted away from the ridge just before the motorwagon. A pair of Mareford soldiers were trotting forward, guns leveled at the crumpled form of a changeling. Bloodbeak watched it down the sights of the machine gun, her eyes wide.

The changeling’s foreleg moved slightly, and one of the advancing soldiers snapped off two shots. She jerked, slumped further, and didn’t move again.

Dusty stood up, calling out. “What happened?”

“It’s a changeling spy, sir!” one of the soldiers came back, lowering his rifle once he was satisfied the changeling corpse was no longer a threat. “They were trying to get to headquarters. Tried to run when we went to detain them. Shot them, they lost their disguise.”

Dusty glanced my way, and I could only shrug. I suspected there were a lot of details being left out for the sake of brevity, but it hardly mattered at the moment. “We expected them to try something,” I said. Fortunately, we’d made it reasonably hard on them.

Uneasily, we returned to our work, such as it was. Ponies were storming Serenity positions. There were no more attempts at assassination.

Brachinus was just two minutes out when they radioed again. Her voice was, as always, perfectly perfunctory and professional. “Command, Brachinus. Aborting. Outbound west. Returning to hold.” I looked west, searching the skies.

“Negative, Brachinus! Continue your run!”

“Brachinus is unable. Enemy air defenses are intact and target is dispersed. Brachinus disengaging as per ROE.”

I finally spotted the skywagon, still a few miles out, skimming the underside of the clouds. If it hadn’t been banking away, I probably wouldn’t have seen it.

“We’re being overrun! ROE is rescinded. We need immediate support to preserve the army! Engage now!”

“Negative. The Queen was clear in her orders. ROE does not permit weapon deployment at this time. Brachinus returning to hold.”

It may not have been professional, but I could hardly blame the beleaguered Serenity commander for the profanity that followed.

☢

The motorwagon shook and rattled as it slowly crept along the rocky ground, leaving Rotwater Creek behind. Ponies marched past former Serenity defenses, pocked and charred by the intense fire that had been laid out upon them. Only a few ponies lay before the defenses, left where they fell while medics tended to those who were still alive. They would be collected soon enough.

As we rose up from the low-ground of the crossing and passed the first line of walls, the toll on Serenity started to become clear. Dozens of dead changelings lay behind the walls where they had fought, or on the ground behind where they had tried to flee. Some passing ponies were stripping gear from those who hadn’t already been looted, gathering weapons and spark batteries.

More than a hundred Mareford Militia soldiers marched in our column, past all the devastation. What had been an enemy strongpoint was now just another path on to our final goal. There were no cheers or celebrations, but these ponies held their heads high with pride. They’d faced the enemy head-on and prevailed. The way to Serenity lay essentially unguarded.

The second line showed more signs of carnage. The fighting had clearly been intense. I saw the corpses of at least a dozen ponies, but as we passed the cracked and smoking pillbox with the twisted remains of the heavy plasma cannon, we found even more changelings.

Sickle was waiting for us by the pillbox, trotting our way once we drew close. She looked significantly worse for wear. Her head and hooves were slathered in blood and dirt. Her armor was scorched in several places. An entire plate was missing from her side, revealing bare hide where her coat had been burnt away. She limped heavily, but she was grinning wide.

“You cunts missed a hell of a fight!” she called out as she drew near.

We halted as she climbed in. She groaned, but sighed happily as she flopped out in the back. At least she was content.

“So where do I get more ammo for this thing?”

Ahead of us, arrayed behind the former Serenity positions, the bulk of the army was digging in for the night. Motorwagons were ferrying up heavy weapons. They spread across the valley. Serenity’s megaspell was still out there. Even if I knew it had retired for the night, we didn’t want to leave them an easy target.

While the rest of the ponies took up their own positions, Dusty directed Starlight to a rise close to where Serenity’s headquarters had been. We could see clearly the devastation Echo’s attack had caused. The former headquarters was nothing but a crater. Chunks of concrete and metal were scattered around the field, but all that remained of the original structure was one end of the hasty foundation. Past that lay the remains of the logistical element. A half dozen motorwagons, now mangled and ruined hulks, still smouldered with green fire. The ground was torn up for dozens of yards, with smoke wafting up from the burnt remains of dead vegetation. The balefire had consumed most of the equipment. Only a few broken and damaged crates and cases remained around the edges of the charred area, scattered by the blast.

The devastation was impressive, and sobering. The amount of violence unleashed in that tiny slice of land on the edge of the little creek was incredible. So many people had lost their lives that day.

It was a bittersweet relief that most of them had been changelings. The outcome was exactly what we had hoped for, yet I couldn’t look back at the still black lumps and broken carapaces without feeling something tighten inside.

In the rear, the medical ponies tended to those who could be saved. The final tally hadn’t come in yet, but there were close to a hundred casualties in all, with more than half of them dead. It seemed such an extreme number, but it paled in comparison to Serenity’s losses. I didn’t hear a final tally until the next morning. Just over two hundred changeling bodies had been recovered. We couldn’t even guess how many had died in the balefire blasts, or how many had been vaporized by magical energy weapons.

From the intercepted radio transmissions, Serenity was reeling from their loss. Their army commander and half the company commanders were dead. Two of their companies had essentially ceased to exist, with an overwhelmed new commander trying to rally survivors. Their other two companies were so badly understrength that the commander of one had suggested merging into a single company. None were sure how many changelings were dead or missing. There was confusion over what to do with the few wounded who had escaped the battle. Supplies were short. There was talk of retreating to the hive to make a final stand there.

Not once did anyling suggest striking back. If the previous clashes had been a stinging slap of a hoof, this was a double-hooved buck to the face. For the moment, they were staying well away from us.

☢

The relative peace lasted until we set out the next morning. With reinforcements from the hive, Serenity had organized into two companies, and they tentatively set about trying to delay us once more.

Once again, they found an enemy that was too clever for them. Small and sneaky raids met heavy resistance. When an entire company tried to move into position to engage our column, they found themselves outnumbered two to one. In most cases, they disengaged immediately, sometimes without a shot fired.

One platoon commander tried a more aggressive turn, trying to rely on speed and violence to catch us off-guard. If they’d achieved surprise, it might have even worked. Instead they flew into the jaws of a trap. Ready soldiers met them on the ground. Loyalists flew above, diving down upon the attacking force, while motorwagons rushed more soldiers to their flanks. Only a few changelings escaped, while our casualties were light.

That said, Serenity wasn’t incompetent. Despite the chaos and casualties we inflicted upon them, and the tremendous advantage I held in my hooves, they adapted. They couldn’t press a fight, but they learned how to harass us. They stayed at a distance, sporadically engaging at long range and disappearing behind hills when we returned fire. The fire was mostly inaccurate and low-threat, but every now and then shots struck home. Casualties started to accumulate ever so slowly, while our ability to strike back was limited.

The worst was when Mantis returned. They had taken losses during the previous day’s battle, but they were still able to fight. Our position at the center of the army meant we never presented ourselves to them, but other motorwagons were not so safe.

If that wasn’t bad enough, we didn’t even know they were there until a missile slammed into the leading motorwagon, killing the entire recon team. There hadn’t been any warning on Serenity’s command net. As Dusty quickly pulled motorwagons back to safety, directing infantry to lead the reconnaissance, I carefully listened into what Serenity was doing.

Minutes later, a unit I had heard nothing from engaged the vanguard of the army from almost half a mile away. Less than thirty seconds of firing, and only one pony killed, but the changelings withdrew without any losses, and without anything coming across the command net.

I listened more to lower-level channels.

The next engagement was much like the last. Thirty seconds after the distant shots rang out, the platoon leader called to fall back. Communications were short and brief, and could basically be summed up as “follow me”. Nothing was reported back to the company commander.

In the chaos wrought by their command losses, they had lightened the load by having units operate more independently. It made things easier on their commander, and unknown to them, it made my job much more difficult.

I’d just found Mantis’s channel when another motorwagon, parked on a ridge half a mile ahead of us, exploded in a violent fireball.

“Good kill,” one soldier said.

“Shift left, one seven seven. The motorwagon with the plow. It’s rolling back. When it comes back out, hit it.”

I quickly spotted the wagon in question. “Dusty, tell the wagons to stay in cover,” I said as I switched to my map, quickly plotting the motorwagon’s position and tracking back along the bearing. Leaning forward, I held up the PipBuck for Dusty, and pointed to the hill almost a mile out. “Mantis is right around here.”

He gave a quick nod as he brought up his broadcaster. “Loyal Lead, Command…”

It was about a minute later when I heard from Mantis again, this time on Serenity’s command channel. “This is Mantis! Enemy fliers inbound on our position. We need assistance!”

A minute later, the Loyalists crossed over our lines again at high speed, pursued by dozens of Serenity soldiers. Magical energy cannons opened up, driving the enemy away. Hail Burst stopped by to give Dusty the details. Mantis had been six changelings in Steel Ranger armor, with a variety of heavy weapons, including the missile launcher Starlight had spotted. None had survived the raid. All heavy weapons had been destroyed.

Not that it had been without cost on our behalf. Two pegasi had not returned.

Even without the threat of Mantis, Serenity still kept up the harassment. They continued to take potshots, while avoiding a direct confrontation. It wore on, for hours. Casualties mounted ever so slowly. A couple. A dozen. Two dozen.

But it simply wasn’t enough. Their attacks were nothing but stings to a bear. We didn’t slow. Mile by mile, we drew closer to Serenity and the end of all of this. We pressed on, fueled by the victory we had won and the ever-growing closeness of our goal. Our progress was inexorable. The outcome was inevitable. As night fell, our long march came to a halt, just six miles from Serenity. There was nothing they could do to stop us.

Which is why they decided to change the game.

☢

I was enjoying a late dinner of stale broccoli when a voice came on the radio that sent a chill down my spine. There was no mistaking the resonant tones and commanding authority of a changeling queen. Chrysalis.

“Attention!” she said, her voice crystal clear in my left ear. “This situation has gone far enough. This hostile army stands on our doorstep. Already, ponies have caused untold death and destruction. Now they seek to wipe out our very existence. They must be stopped, whatever the cost.

“To that end, I will be deploying specialists from the hive. At precisely three A.M., they will turn the ponies’ own clouds against them. They will initiate a massive downpour to blind these ponies.

“Commander Notum. You will pull your forces back to three miles distance from any enemy encampments. Prepare for operations in heavy weather.

“Brachinus. You will move to Point Firefly. At exactly three-thirty, you will set out, using the cover of the storm to close on your target. Your target will be the center of the enemy army. You must not let anything stop you. This is our last, best chance to stop this enemy before they destroy our very way of life. I understand that the weather will be treacherous, and the opposition fierce, but the weapon must be delivered. For the good of the hive, I trust you will do what is necessary to see this task through.

“That is all.”

I set down my food and levitated my PipBuck to look at the map. A new marker had come in on the Serenity channel, labeled simply “Target”. It was a mere thirty yards from where I sat.

“Dusty? We’ve got a problem.”

I repeated the information to him. A minute later, he called Hail Burst, asking her to join us. She arrived soon after.

She came gliding in, backwinging to land neatly before me. Even with her eyes hidden beneath those lenses, the questioning look was clear. While I was still wearing the power armor, I had removed the helmet, and she could see my grim expression. “Okay,” she said, turning to Dusty. “So what’s so important we couldn’t talk about it on the radio?”

He just raised a hoof, gesturing my way.

She looked to me again.

I drew in a breath and exhaled. “We need your help.” Her head tilted as I levitated my PipBuck once more, presenting it to her. It was displaying the map, dotted with markers. One was highlighted. Point Firefly.

“I need to organize a raid.”

Chapter Forty Seven: In from the Cold

I stared out the second-story window as the rain poured down with a tremendous roar. Somewhere, far above, the sun must be shining down, but you could be forgiven for thinking otherwise. I couldn’t see even a hundred feet in the dim, gray gloom. Every few minutes, a flash of lightning would cast sharp silhouettes through the pounding rain, accompanied by the powerful, rattling boom of thunder.

It had been raining for more than twelve hours, and showed no sign of relenting.

The world outside was mud. A small river flowed along what had been a ditch along the edge of the construction site. Several of the smaller tunnels, despite their working pumps, were partially flooded by the massive inundation. Even here, in the upper levels of the incomplete office building, everything was soaking wet. The wind was completely wild, whipping the rain around in random directions and getting water everywhere. The air was icy. Despite the pair of blankets draped over me, and Starlight tucked in close at my side, it was still unpleasantly cold.

We’d won, and now we sat there, bunkered down against the storm, with no idea of what to do next. So far, the consensus was that we would wait out the storm, then see what the situation was.

That left us with little to do. I did some more recordings, but even with the glut of activity in the previous two days, I soon found myself with little to occupy myself with.

The earbud in my left ear chirped and warbled, the volume turned down low. Serenity’s communications were all nonsense. I’m not sure what the final straw had been, but they’d finally chosen to change encryption keys. I’d say that it was too little, too late, but they still had probably two hundred soldiers out there. Our soldiers had to remain alert and ready. Even E.F.S. offered no comfort; this close to Serenity, the top levels were within detection range, filling the compass with hostile markers in all directions. If Serenity decided to attack, there would be no warning.

What actually happened was… something else.

It was Axle, of all ponies, who radioed me. His voice was hushed. “Hey, Whisper? Get your buggy ass to the north side of the main building, ground floor. Bring that big bitch with you. And not a fucking word to anypony that I talked to you!”

I blinked in confusion at the strange message.

“The hell?” Starlight said, stirring at my side and looking just as confused as me.

Echo lay nearby, frowning down at her own PipBuck. “I do not trust that stallion. It is clear he has no good wishes for you. And is he asking for Sickle, or is he referring to me in such crude terms?”

Sickle grunted and snorted, her head jerking from the floor as she woke. “Urgh, wha?” She raised a hoof, wiping at her armor-clad face. “Somepony say my name? What’s up?”

I groaned softly as I stood, leaving behind the tenuous warmth of my blankets. “I’m not sure.”

She slowly stretched, giving a deep yawn before asking, “There going to be a fight?”

I hesitated, not entirely sure. “I don’t think so. Probably not.”

She wearily pushed herself up, armor rattling. “Well fuck, probably not is maybe yes. I’m in.”

I couldn’t help a wry smile. “You have such an amusingly strange sense of optimism.”

“Yeah, I’m just a ray of fucking sunshine,” Sickle replied, teeth bared in a grin.

I headed out, with Starlight, Sickle, and Echo all following me. Dusty remained behind, electing to go over his gear once more.

In the depths of the building, the pounding rain turned into a more distant, deep roar, echoing down the hallways. The stairs down were slippery, with the bare concrete coated in water and mud, but we managed without incident.

On the ground floor, as we made our way toward the north face of the building, a new sound reached my ears: yelling.

I walked faster. The yelling was a jumble of anger and eagerness, like a crowd cheering for blood. As I entered the last hallway, I could see a trio of Mareford ponies, weapons in teeth, eyes narrowed. They gave some shouts as well, buried under the rest, but theirs were firm and authoritative to the crowd’s emotion. One cast a glance down the hallway, seeing me, and lowered her weapon, her glare returning to the ponies they were shouting at.

I was almost to the corner when I heard a new voice behind the others. A cry of pain. A shout, pleading in tone, full of pain and fear. A voice that was clearly not a pony.

I prefer to act with a clear and rational mind, but emotion can be a useful tool. So, as the adrenaline flowed, it was with a clear and rational mind that I put on a mask of rage, eyes narrowed and teeth bared as I rounded the corner.

Several Trotsen ponies had confronted the Mareford ponies, their jeers and anger shriveling as they saw me. Eyes went wide, and several staggered back as I advanced. Past them, the rest of the large room was filled with at least fifty Trotsen ponies. Some, at the edges, looked displeased or concerned, with a few trying to calm down the more agitated ponies. It was those angrier ponies, at the center of the room, who drew my attention.

There was shouting. Jeering. Calls for blood and pain and worse. At their center was a lone, muddy changeling. A pony was pulling on her foreleg, and her pleading was cut off by a cry of pain as he twisted on it. I saw blood running from her mouth. Another pony was staggering back, having just delivered a kick to her abdomen.

The dim room abruptly turned green as I lit up my horn, eyes snapping to me as I gave a shout that could have made Sickle proud. “Enough!”

The nearest ponies staggered back as I stalked into the room, my head high and posture imposing. The ponies at the center of the room hesitated for just a moment at the sudden intrusion. I used that pause to speak first, voice cold and hard.

“What are you doing?” I demanded, fixing the ponies with my best glare.

The mare who had delivered the kick looked up to me, perhaps emboldened by her anger. “Fuck off. She’s ours. We caught this cockroach trying to sneak in.”

The changeling gasped and croaked out, “P-please, I—”

The stallion holding her swung a hoof at her head. “Shut your fucking—”

He didn’t get the chance to land the blow. My magic grabbed around his chest and foreleg and tore him away, throwing him against the nearby wall. It took a tremendous amount of magic, but I had plenty to spare and little reason to hold back. Heck, there’s no way I could have even managed such a display of magical might in my natural form. Having a queen’s horn had advantages.

The stallion collapsed to the bare concrete floor, groaning as he tried to get his hooves under himself again. I continued to advance into the center of the room, with several ponies stepping back. “Do not mistake my general civility for timidity,” I said, teeth still bared as I looked around the room. “Let me make this perfectly clear to you: I am here to protect people from cruelty, whether they are pony or changeling. Anyone who insists on behaving like a raider will be treated like a raider.”

The mare in front of me had apparently regained her confidence, puffing up her chest as she squared off with me. “Hey, fuck you! Trotsen ain’t going to be pushed around by you fucking bugs. You don’t scare us.”

Sickle gave a loud, snorting laugh. “That’s because you’re a fucking moron.”

The mare shot Sickle a glare. “Oh, fuck off. I’m talking to queen bitch.”

“You’re about to get torn in half by that queen bitch if you don’t watch your fucking mouth,” Sickle said, advancing a step. “I mean, shit. I’ve seen her walk through a fucking mountain of corpses to get here. She’s wiped out raiders, mercs, monsters, big fucking robots, and all sorts of other shit. She’s probably the most dangerous cunt I’ve ever met. Fuck, why else do you think I’d tag along with her?

“But you know what?” Her muzzle split into a savage, almost manic grin. “All those fights, all that killing, and I ain’t ever seen her even half as pissed as you dumb motherfuckers got her right now.”

The mare glanced my way. I met the look with a cold, hard glare.

“And she’s the nice one,” Sickle growled, drawing the mare’s attention back to her. “She’s the one always trying to help ponies and shit. Me, I’m just here for a fucking fight. So how about it, little bitch?” Her hoof suddenly raised, thumping into the mare’s chest and shoving her back several steps. “You talk a big fucking game for a cunt who can’t even fight a scrawny little bug without somepony else holding them down. Come on. Try a pony that ain’t held back, you little chicken-shit. See how that ends for you.”

The mare regained her balance, glaring back, but smartly chose to not take Sickle’s invitation.

Sickle advanced another step, and while the mare held her ground, she still didn’t retort. Sickle followed with a sneer. “Pussy. Ass. Bitch.” She turned away with a dry laugh. “This is fucking pathetic.”

The gathered ponies grumbled, some glaring back at Sickle, but none challenged her. It seemed the appropriate moment to step in. “Enough,” I said, looking to Echo. “Take and bubble the changeling.”

The changeling, who had remained still during the confrontation, floated from the bare concrete floor, a purple shield snapping into being around her. As she floated over to us, I looked around at the gathered ponies. “This fight isn’t about ponies versus changelings. It’s about right versus wrong. There are still hundreds of Serenity’s soldiers out there. Fight them. But if they are captured, or surrender, then they will be treated fairly. Period.”

I turned to walk away, leaving on a note of finality. I heard some murmurs behind me, some clearly angry, but ignored them. Echo watched over her shoulder, likely waiting for an attack.

Several more Mareford soldiers had arrived, and all were relaxing now that the situation was resolved. The soldier who had first caught sight of me even gave a nod as I passed, which I silently returned.

The moment we were in the hall and walking away, my hard expression crumbled. My ears fell, my head sinking.

I don’t like using threats and strong-hoof tactics. Generally, I see them as a failure of reason, but I also knew that they were tools to be used in the right situation. However mixed my feelings might be, I felt this was one of those situations. Trotsen ponies seemed to recognize and respect strength, and I wanted to make it perfectly clear that this behavior would not be tolerated. I think I had delivered that point.

The walk back was in silence, aside from Sickle, who walked along with a happy strut. “You know, I think I’m starting to enjoy this whole ‘talking’ shit.” At least she was in a good mood.

Dusty was on the radio when we returned, engaged in a hasty exchange with Two Bits. By now, word had filtered up to him. Dusty looked up from his PipBuck, first at me, then at the changeling. “Is everything okay?”

“It’s been resolved,” I said, a bit of the earlier firmness lingering in my tone. “I may have to abuse my apparent position of power.”

“Oh?”

“I declared that anyone acting like a raider would be treated like a raider, regardless of whether their victim is a pony or a changeling. I’d appreciate it if you could make that an official stance of the army.”

Dusty gave a snort. “I’d have thought that was perfectly damn clear, but yeah, we’ll do that.”

“Thank you,” I said, looking back to Echo and gesturing for her to follow.

Sickle flopped down to rest again, while Echo and Starlight followed me into the next room.

I sat with a long, deep sigh. Starlight sat beside me, her movements slow and cautious. Her side brushed gently against my carapace. Her eyes were full of worry.

“Are you okay?” she asked, voice quiet.

I gave a slow, tired nod. I felt like I could fall asleep right then and there, as if it would let everything pass me by, but there was more to do. “Could you get out your medical supplies?”

As she quickly dug through her bags, I looked back to Echo. “You can release her.”

Echo frowned. “I do not think that is a good idea.”

“She couldn’t possibly kill me before either of us could stop her. It will be fine.”

“I still feel that you are excessively optimistic in your evaluation of potential risks,” she said, but she lowered the changeling to the ground, the bubble of purple energy vanishing.

The changeling was in pretty poor shape. She lay on the bare floor, her breathing rough and ragged as she watched me with wide, frightened eyes. Mud still clung thickly to her legs, with smears and spatters in many places. The side of her muzzle was smeared with blood, which ran down to trickle from a fang. Her carapace was discolored in a few places where she had been struck hard enough to bruise through the exoskeleton. Surface cracks crossed her cheek, back, and flank, with a full-depth crack running for several inches along the side of her chest. She held her leg—with a PipBuck still buckled to it—tight to her chest, protecting and cushioning the injury.

I sighed, then reached out with my magic, gently cradling her. Her mouth opened, wavering for a moment before shutting and remaining silent. She trembled as she continued to stare at me, terrified. I couldn’t even blame her. A changeling queen holds a special place of reverence and awe. It is a remarkably short step from awe to terror.

“Here,” I said, floating over a healing potion. She flinched, eying it carefully. “I want to apologize for how you were treated. We may find ourselves as enemies, but that doesn’t excuse what they did.”

She was still trembling, eyes turned back to me. She ignored the potion. Her mouth opened, wavered, and shut again. Her eyes were watering.

“What’s your name?” I asked, my voice quiet and gentle, prompting her.

She hesitated, but finally managed to croak out a word. “Calypter.”

“Calypter. I like the name.” I floated the potion a little closer. “Here, drink up.” She finally relented, taking a slow and careful swig. While she was busy with that, I floated up a washcloth from the supplies, gently removing some of the mud.

There was something surreal about it. She was so tiny and fragile beside me, and I had to remind myself that she was about the same size as I was in my natural form. I think she might have even been taller than me. Supporting her in my magic, gently wiping away the mud from her carapace, it felt like an almost motherly tenderness, like she was a hurt child I was comforting. Yet the truth was that she was probably a well-trained soldier, a survivor of the previous days’ of fighting. Or, possibly, an Infiltrator trying to pull a trick.

She hissed softly as the crack along her side sealed itself, leaving only a thin line. I gently gripped her PipBuck, turning the screen upwards as I switched it to the medical screen and read the information there. “Well, it’s not perfect,” I said, “but at least it’s an improvement. Now, I apologize, but I’m going to have to take this, at least for the time being.”

Her mouth opened to object, but shut again, merely staring at the device as I unbuckled it and set it aside.

I returned to cleaning away the mud. “So, those ponies say they caught you trying to sneak in. What really happened?”

She slowly twisted, trying to pull free of my magic, and I released her. She pushed herself up, wincing, but finally got herself into a sitting posture. She took several slow, deep breaths, her expression steadily setting. When she finally spoke, her eyes were firm and focused, though she couldn’t quite look me in the face. Only the faintest of tremble showed behind the determination. “I came to… talk. To you.”

Now that was interesting, I thought. I carefully maintained my expression of soft neutrality, casting a quick glance to the confiscated PipBuck. “You approached them… undisguised?”

She nodded. “Yes.”

I frowned, a hint of anger stirring in the background. Attacking a just-discovered spy at least had a bit more of an excuse than abusing someone who had surrendered openly, not that I considered either action justified. I pushed that emotion back. “And what did you want to talk to me about?”

Another deep breath. The tremble grew slightly, and her eyes wavered. There was a clear struggle to force herself to speak. “I… I wanted to plead with you.” Her eyes drifted up to mine, then snapped back down to my chest, unable to hold eye contact. “I-I beg you. Please spare my hive.”

My ears drooped once more. The metaphorical weight was heavy on my shoulders. I sighed, and saw Calypter shiver at the sound, assuming the worst. My voice was even quieter when I spoke again. “We are in an awkward situation, aren’t we? I’ve seen enough changelings die for a lifetime, and I have no desire to see more. At the same time… I think it’s clear the current situation can’t be allowed to persist. It’s a problem that’s been hounding me ever since we started this venture, and I still don’t see a good solution.”

“Please,” she said, again trying and not quite meeting my eyes. “You beat us. What more do you want?”

“Myself?” I pondered that for several long seconds before replying. “I was sincere when I was talking to those other ponies. This isn’t about ponies versus changelings. There doesn’t have to be that adversity. If anything, I think this alliance has shown that changelings and ponies can work together, and be stronger for it.”

She looked down.

“I don’t want to see your population exterminated. I would prefer a peaceful resolution. At the same time… your hive has repeatedly hurt ponies through lies and deception. We can’t trust you. I can’t even trust that you’re actually a soldier, and not yet another Infiltrator trying to find some weakness to exploit.”

Her ears drooped, tears gathering. Whether it was a calculated move or true despair, it was still a painfully emotional display.

“Don’t despair,” I said, voice soft and comforting. “I wasn’t trusted when I first revealed myself, either. I earned trust through my actions. The changelings of your hive can do that, too, by showing that they can coexist with others. You have the opportunity to lead the way to a better future, by helping us to bring an end to this conflict.”

Her jaw tightened, ears folding back. A tremble ran through her, though her eyes remained fixed on my hooves. “I-I came to ask for mercy,” she said, her voice tight. “But I will never betray my hive.”

“And I wouldn’t ask you to,” I said. “You clearly have a strong conviction. Whether you’re a soldier or an Infiltrator, you risked your own life to approach an attacking army, intending to speak with a foreign and possibly hostile queen, all with the hope that you might save others in your hive. I’m not going to ask you to betray that. I admire that.”

I raised a hoof, reaching out to her chin and gently but firmly nudging upwards until she was looking at my soft smile. “I want the same thing as you. I don’t want to see more changelings die. So I would ask you, please, help me find a solution to this conflict. Help me show these ponies that we can coexist, and save as many of your hivemates as we can.”

She had gone still. Her expression slowly softened as I spoke, her eyes widening.

The hint of surreality had returned. The scene had a certain familiarity to it, with a scared and desperate changeling looking up to a tender and confident queen, but it was all wrong. I could see myself all too clearly in her. I’d been there before. I could clearly remember the feeling of fear or despair, and the comforting touch of Queen Ephema’s hoof. I remembered feeling so small, yet buoyed up by her presence, her compassion, her confidence. It was almost like looking in a mirror.

Only it was more than just a change in perspective. Now, I was the confident and compassionate queen, calmly and tenderly reassuring a scared changeling. It was all backwards, and should have felt all wrong, but it didn’t. It wasn’t even an act. Everything I had said was what I felt was right. Seeing the fear fading to hope brought a feeling of pride and happiness, a sense that I was doing the right thing. I could save some of these changelings, even if it was just her. I knew already that good changelings could come from her hive, and I hoped that she might be one. From what little I knew of her, I kind of liked her.

At that thought, her reaction made sense. We might be on opposing sides, and I might not be able to trust her, but I did like her. She could sense that. The emotion I was giving off wasn’t of a heartless queen bent on the destruction of her hive and the deaths of her kin.

Of course, she couldn’t trust me, either. A skilled Infiltrator can stir up feelings in themselves, and can retain the clarity of mind to act according to their goals rather than their feelings. While I presented all the signs of being genuinely compassionate, it was perfectly possible that I could be trying to play her. Despite that, my response had apparently been more gentle than she had expected, and must have suggested that her hopes might not have been in vain.

To be absolutely fair, even though I was starting to like her, I wouldn’t have hesitated to blast her if it should become necessary. I’d be disappointed, of course, but I was too well-trained to let emotion get in the way of doing what was necessary and right. They’d tried to assassinate me three times already.

I slowly slid my hoof away, returning it to the floor. “So that brings us to the big question. How do we resolve all of this?”

She blinked, gaze fixed on my smiling face for a moment before she looked away again. “Um… I… I don’t know…”

I hummed thoughtfully. “Well, I suppose we can start by establishing the absolute conditions that must be met, and then working from there. Does that sound good?”

She looked to me again. “Conditions? What conditions?”

“Well, to start with, the people being held in your hive will have to go free.”

“What?” Her wings gave a couple of beats, her head drawing back. “But we’d starve!”

“You would have to make friends with ponies, yes,” I said with a nod. “I’ve already shown that it’s possible to do so openly. I get more than enough love from my friends.”

I finished by inclining my head toward Starlight, who, finding herself suddenly at the center of attention, gave an awkward smile. “Uh, heh, yeah.”

Calypter looked to her, then back to me, her expression hardening. “Friends? Like those ponies who beat me?”

I sighed. “I know, it will be complicated by recent events, but not all ponies are like that. Some of the other Trotsen ponies were trying to stop it. It may not be easy, but there are ponies who would try to help. Gemstone preaches Kindness and Generosity, and I’m sure they’d do what they could. Seroon seems like a very compassionate and wise individual, and I’m sure there are many in Mareford who would follow his lead. And of course, I would be helping. We won’t let you starve.”

Her gaze wavered, finally looking away once more. “Doubt it matters. The hive isn’t going to give them up and trust in pony generosity for survival. You just have to look around the world to see how that went.”

“Then we have two options. Either we, you and I, figure out how to convince at least some of your hivemates to free those prisoners, or we’ll have to figure out a way for the army to rescue them.”

Her ears folded flat. “I won’t help you attack my hive.”

“I understand,” I said, “but they will have to be freed, one way or another. I’d prefer to negotiate their release, and avoid violence. Will you help me with that?”

She hesitated before silently nodding.

“Good. The next condition would be the disarming of the hive. We can’t trust all of your hive to have peaceful intentions, so we’ll have to remove the industrial and military power that let you become such a threat.”

She grimaced. “So we’d be entirely at the mercy of these ponies.”

“You’re already at the mercy of these ponies. At least this way, the ponies will be supporting and protecting you. You’ll have to work alongside them anyway, to develop the friendships you’ll need to survive. We can at least start things off on the right hoof, by making this as peaceful as possible.”

Calypter was silent for several seconds. “...What else?”

I paused, considering that for a moment. “I think that might be it for absolutely necessary conditions. You’d have to surrender to pony authority, of course, but what happens after that is likely to be up for negotiation. I’m sure we can come up with something that’s mutually beneficial.”

“I doubt it,” she mumbled, slowly shaking her head. “You want my hive to give up everything. I don’t think they’ll listen.”

“Then we’ll need to find a way to get them to listen,” I said. “So we need leverage. Something to simultaneously show them that they can not win this, and that these ponies will treat them fairly if they surrender.” I gestured to the vacant window and the pouring rain beyond. “How about the rest of the army? I’m under the impression they’re in bad condition. Battered, low on supplies, exposed to a harsh storm, and with a much larger army between them and the safety of home. I’m guessing that contributed to your willingness to come before me?”

She hesitated, then nodded.

“And are there others who are open to the possibility of negotiation?”

Again, she nodded.

“Then perhaps we should appeal to them. We have supplies and shelter to care for any who surrender. You can serve as an example of the sincerity of the offer. If we can convince them to surrender, they can serve as a similar example to the hive as a whole, and hopefully convince those still in the Stable to surrender peacefully.”

Another pause. “...Okay. I’ll try. I’m just… I’m not sure how many will listen.”

“I know, but we have to try. I think what you’re doing is the best course for the survival of your hive, but I know not everyling will see it that way. I may not know your hive personally, but I know well how strong the devotion can be. There will likely be some who will fight to the death rather than surrender. There may even be some who would prefer to see their hive destroyed rather than compromise. We may face difficulty on both sides, but we will do what we can to save as many lives as possible.”

I saw the tremble run through her, and I lifted my hoof again, this time placing it on her shoulder, reassuring. “I’ve faced the fear of my own hive’s possible destruction, Calypter. I have no desire to see any changeling ever have to go through that again. I hope we can save most of your hive, but even if we’re only able to convince a few other changelings from the army to surrender, at least your hive will have a future.”

She still trembled, eyes watering, but nodded, looking up to me. “Okay.”

☢

Two hours later, I sat by a wide upper-floor window, looking out into the storm. The icy mist spattered against my carapace, forcing me to squint into the gloom. The various work lights around the site had been arranged outside the building and turned on. They struggled to pierce the torrential downpour, while leaving the interior only dimly lit, concealing our positions.

Calypter sat nearby, still and silent. She’d already done her part. Before she had set out to see me, she had confided in a few close friends. They’d arranged a frequency and key to communicate privately if some emergency came up. She’d contacted them, detailing what had happened. A few minutes later, she broadcast a wider message to the army, explaining the situation and pleading with her fellow soldiers to follow her lead.

It wasn’t clear yet how well-received the message was, and Serenity had already gone through the process of changing out encryption keys again, leaving us cut out of their communications once more. Her friends had agreed to surrender, and had said they would persuade any who would listen to come as well.

Three minutes ago, her friends had radioed again on their private network. They were heading towards us, with a good number of other soldiers. They were coming in from the southwest, as we had instructed them. Dusty had arranged the most disciplined of the Mareford soldiers there. Two Bits was some ten yards away from me at another window, to watch over events and give directions. Several Mareford Rangers stood guard around us, weapons ready.

We waited, wary and hopeful.

The rain pounded the wet earth in a dull roar, but I caught another sound. There was something faint and distant, almost hidden behind the rain. It repeated several times, without any apparent pattern. It was several seconds before I recognized them as the discharge of magical energy weapons. I peered out into the rain. I saw nothing but darkness.

Seconds later, one of the Rangers at the next window raised her PipBuck, reporting the shots.

Calypter stood—drawing an alarmed twitch from Echo—and moved to the window. Her ears were perked alertly, though she squinted against the blowing rain. “What’s going on?

My own ears drooped. “I think they’re fighting each other.”

Calypter cast an alarmed look my way.

I turned to my own PipBuck. “Dusty? There might be a complication. It sounds like part of the army is trying to stop the changelings who are surrendering. The surrendering soldiers may be coming in under fire.”

“It can never be simple,” Dusty replied with a grumble. Then, more professionally, “I’ll make sure everypony is ready for it.”

“Thank you.”

Calypter was at the window, her hooves on the sill as she watched and waited. I sat, still able to see over the edge just fine. The darkness continued to yield nothing.

The sounds grew steadily louder, and almost a minute later, we could see flickers of red and purple light. They steadily grew, until we could pick out individual bolts of light. A few even sailed out of the darkness; some hit the ground before us, a few sailed overhead, and a couple struck the face of the building.

Multiple calls went out over the radio, ending with a long burst of fire from one of the nearby Rangers. Both Calypter and I flinched at the sound, a string of tracers lashing out at the source of the distant fire.

“Two Bits!” I called out, looking down the wall. “What are you doing?”

“Relax,” he said. “We’re just suppressing that shooter.” The stallion beside him had a belt-fed weapon, and every few seconds put out another second-long burst.

“Just be careful of who you’re shooting.”

“Yeah, we know our job,” he replied, his tone neutral and matter-of-fact rather than offended.

The volume of magical weapon fire rapidly decreased, but didn’t cease entirely. Flashes and flickers of light filtered through the rain. A few flashes lit up silhouettes, fuzzy and indistinct in the rain. Soon those silhouettes started to resolve into hastily moving forms, moving quickly our way.

“Eyes on!” one soldier called out, with reports quickly spreading down the line.

I leaned close to the edge, half-shielded by the wall. A flash of lightning lit the area in a strobe, highlighting dozens of forms before plunging back into darkness. The after-image lingered for a few seconds before clearing enough to find them again. I could make out the pony-like silhouettes of the closest three, moving with obvious difficulty in the thick mud. They staggered and struggled, working hard just to make a slow walking pace.

Several more bolts sailed out from some distant assailant, immediately answered by another long burst of return fire. The incoming forms all staggered and ducked, but were quickly moving again. I could already pick out the silhouette of curved horns, and the occasional glint of blue eyes reflecting the lights.

They were only about twenty or thirty yards out when the lights finally illuminated them. The closest pair trudged through thick mud, sinking nearly to their knees with each step. They carried almost nothing with them, just light armor and mud-caked PipBucks. Light glistened from wet armor and carapace.

I could hear ponies shouting instructions to the incoming changelings, though I couldn’t understand the words past the rain. More changelings were coming into sight. One had a sodden blanket draped across her back and head, reminding me of my early days in the Wasteland. Another still carried her weapon, pulling the sling over her head as she stepped into the light and letting it fall into the mud. Others still had their rifles strapped across their back, seemingly dazed as they trudged forward almost mindlessly toward the waiting shelter. Another changeling was helping to support a companion with an injured foreleg, and from the lack of bandaging or splinting, it appeared to be a very recent injury.

There were even a couple of power armors, including one soldier in Steel Ranger armor with a pair of changelings laid across her back. There were many shouts, and they halted some ten yards out, turning away. The ponies below were taking no chances, making them get out of their armor, then sending out a half dozen ponies to help carry the wounded in.

The firing in the background finally stopped as the final few changelings trudged into sight. The last was a pair, with one changeling weakly struggling to drag another. She floundered, collapsing in the mud, seeming unable to rise again. A squad of ponies made their way out, fighting against the thick mud, and dragged both of them back.

Nothing else moved out in the gloom.

I stood, turning to Calypter. “I’m going to go check on them, to make sure everything is going well. You should stay here for the moment. When I get back, we can see about talking with the rest of your hive.”

She nodded. Even past the spray of mist from the broad window, I could see her eyes were watering again. She was watching the defeat of her hive, and knew she had a hoof in it.

I placed a hoof gently on her shoulder, offering a momentary gesture of compassion before turning and walking away. Starlight and Echo followed; the Mareford soldiers at the entrance could watch Calypter for us.

The ground floor was a busy place. A large room, likely intended as an open office space for a large team, was now filled with ponies and changelings. While there were a few Mareford soldiers standing guard, most were still at the outer walls and windows, ready to defend against any attack. Instead, most of the ponies in the room were from Gemstone, alongside Seroon and a couple of other zebras.

A pair of fire-pits had been arranged on the bare concrete floor, and most of the changelings were huddled around these. It was a pitiful sight. Most were huddled up and shivering, their armor having been traded for dry blankets. I could see one changeling soldier, shaking uncontrollably, and seemingly too worn out to even help as a pair of ponies unbuckled her armor and wiped away the worst of the mud. Her expression was distant, almost haunted.

It was an expression shared by many of the exhausted changelings in the room. As I made my way through the room, few even acknowledged my existence. None spoke. The looks I did receive varied. A few looked to me with hatred. Others, with fear. Several watched with a mix of curiosity and concern, as if waiting to see what this foreign queen did next. But mostly, the ones who looked at me did so almost entirely devoid of emotion, as if too exhausted by their ordeal, both mentally and physically. It was as if they had lost all capacity to care.

Some ponies were starting to pass around small bowls and cups of soup. It looked like a thin vegetable soup, mostly broth. The Gemstone ponies had quickly cooked it up, and while it was probably not very filling, it was something hot, and that likely mattered far more. Changelings cradled the steaming cups and bowls as they were passed out, taking careful sips. Only a few managed glares at the ponies passing it out. Most were too focused on the source of warmth, assuming they were able to summon the emotion to focus on anything at all. Some were clearly just going through the motions, as if lost to a trance. A few were in such poor shape that they had to be helped, with a pony carefully feeding them.

I slowly made my way across the room, to where the heaps of armor, PipBucks, and a few weapons were gathered. It was also where Soaring Heart and a couple of other Loyalists were gathered, tending the injured changelings. The one I had seen with an injured leg now had a simple splint, and Soaring Heart was wrapping some magic-infused bandages around the side of another changeling, who hissed weakly in pain with every movement. I could see the discoloration of burns across her carapace, peeking out from behind the bandage.

I halted a few feet back, giving them room to work. “How are they doing?”

Soaring Heart glanced my way before returning to his work. “No critical injuries. These four are the only serious injuries, and they’re all stable. The only real concern I have now is hypothermia, and Dazzle’s taking care of that. From what little I got out of them, they had almost nothing in the way of shelter or supplies. Most of it went up with their logistics.”

Two Bits had arrived as well, and I spent a short time talking with him, getting more information, before returning upstairs.

Calypter huddled by the wall, and quickly wiped at her cheeks as I entered. I walked up and sat by her side, while she tried to hide her awkwardness.

“Fifty three made it here,” I said, my voice quiet and gentle. “Four were injured, but they’re stable. As for the rest… well, they’re recovering. I know the storm is a strong one, but I hadn’t expected them to be in such poor shape.”

Calypter’s reply was quiet. “You blew up most of our supplies.”

“I suppose we did,” I said, giving a soft sigh. “Well, they’re warming up now, and we’ll see that they get proper food and shelter. How much of the army is still out there?”

“I don’t know,” Calypter murmured. “Maybe a hundred.”

I nodded, mentally correcting my assumptions of their army’s strength. “I hope the rest will surrender before their situation gets even worse.”

She remained silent.

“Well, as much as I’d like to let you rest, I think we may have to move to the next stage.” My horn lit up as I floated over a PipBuck, one of the new ones we had confiscated. “If we want to get a message to the rest of the hive, we’ll need to do it before they change encryption keys again. Do you think you’re up to it?”

She hesitated, but eventually nodded, reaching out to gingerly grasp the PipBuck.

“Do you need any help?” I asked.

She shook her head. “No. I… I already thought out what I should say…” She brought the PipBuck close to her chest, switching over to the radio screen. She switched channels, then reached to the broadcast button. She hesitated, hoof wavering for a moment, and pressed down.

“...H-hello.”

Her voice almost cracked, and she released the button and swallowed. A different voice came across the radio. “Unidentified speaker, Comms reads you. Identify.”

She took a deep breath, exhaled, and pressed the button again. “Hello,” she said again. “M-my name is Calypter, soldier basic grade, currently assigned to second platoon, Alpha company. The army is… is defeated. We can not continue to fight. Most of us have surrendered. They’re allowing me to use this broadcaster to contact you.

“We… we can’t beat them. If we keep fighting, it’s not going to end until we’re all dead.” Her voice choked up, but she pressed on. “We can’t win this, but… but the ponies are willing to negotiate a surrender. They’ve given us food, shelter, and medical aid. We’re being treated well. They’re willing to extend this to anyling who surrenders. If we—”

“Enough!”

Calypter jerked. Even my own heart skipped a beat at the angry voice of Queen Chrysalis.

Calypter fumbled at the broadcaster. “M-my queen! I—”

“Be silent!” Chrysalis snapped. “We have heard enough of your mewling. To imagine that such cowards could have wormed their way into the ranks of our army. These ponies have already destroyed the world. We will not be baited by their lies, and we will not throw ourselves at their hooves, just to be stomped out! They know they will never take our hive, so they try to lure us out to our destruction. And you… you’re working with that treacherous foreign queen, helping them against your own queen and hive.”

“N-no! I’m trying to help us, to save—”

Chrysalis cut her off, practically growling into the radio. “You have betrayed your hive, betrayed me, all for the empty promises of a queen that’s already taken advantage of our hospitality and murdered your sisters. Now you recite her poisonous words, helping her to tear down everything we’ve accomplished. You have turned your back on your hive and your duty. A strong changeling would have been willing to give her life for the good of her hive, but you’d rather be a slave to a new queen, trading the lives of your entire hive for whatever meager comforts she promises you.

“You, and all the other traitors, have turned your backs on your hive, so I turn my back on you. You no longer have a place among us. Better to have died for the good of the hive than to live as a traitor and slave.”

Tears were gathering in Calypter’s eyes, her hooves trembling. “Please, my queen—”

“You do not get to call me that any more,” Chrysalis said, her voice icy. “I do not want to hear another traitorous word from you. Only actions can speak for you, now. You want to earn your place back? Then you turn to that vile and treacherous queen, and sink your horn into her black, shriveled heart!”

Calypter trembled, growing so strong that I could see her horn wobbling back and forth. Tears ran down her cheeks as she struggled to control her breathing.

Her head turned my way, eyes glancing, but she froze again, clutching the PipBuck like a lifeline. Past the pain, I could see struggle, emotions warring against reason. Somewhere in there, I suspect she was evaluating her position, my defenses, Echo’s reaction time, the amount of force it would take to actually penetrate my carapace, all the factors that might go into her queen’s last demand. The odds of success were practically nonexistent, but emotion was unlikely to care.

I raised a hoof again, gently slipping it across her back to rest on her shoulder. She tensed, the tremble growing… and then gave a weak sob, her head slowly sinking. I gave a gentle squeeze, hoping I could give some small degree of comfort, despite being the source of the conflict causing her such anguish. She remained tense, but didn’t fight it. She simply let the PipBuck slide from her hooves as she broke down into tears over all she had lost.

I remained silent, letting her crying run its course. She twitched or jerked every now and then, changing position, starting to push back against my gentle embrace or leaning against my side. A couple times, her horn ended up resting against me. I wasn’t worried, even if I was very aware of it. She didn’t have the room to give a proper stab, and she’d never be able to build up magic quickly enough to strike. Echo was watching her like a hawk.

Eventually, her trembling started to subside, her sobs growing quieter, and I spoke up. “I know my words can’t offer much comfort right now, and I hope you won’t take offense to this, as I don’t intend any insult, but… she’s wrong. We both know you’re not doing this for some personal reward.” I slid my hoof up, gently touching the side of her head, and her eyes cracked open to look at me past all the tears. My own expression was somber, ears low. I could perfectly imagine how much pain she was going through. “Whatever else happens, you have guaranteed that your hive has a future. Remember that.”

Her head slowly sunk down again, eyes closing, but she gave a weak nod.

I gave her a gentle pat on the back. “Take your time. When you’re ready, we can take you to join the others.”

It was a good ten minutes later when she finally wiped away the last of the tears and rose to her hooves. She looked so tired and fragile, even ignoring the lingering injuries, but she forced herself to stand upright. Her hooves were shaky, but she pushed herself on.

I gathered up my bags, and we made our way down. We passed the ground level to reach the warehouse-like tunnels outside the Stable. Unlike the smaller side tunnels, the drains and pumps were keeping the main chambers dry. The sound of rain was distant, echoing faintly from above.

A section of the storage level had been set aside for the surrendered changelings. A group of six Mareford soldiers stood guard at the entrance to that section, and from the looks of their position, Dusty had posted them there as much to keep ponies out as changelings in.

Calypter came to an abrupt halt some ten yards away. I stopped as well, waiting as her mouth moved in a silent attempt to force out the words, until she finally managed to speak. “What do I tell them?”

The small flicker of happiness that she would ask my advice was buried under the weight of what she asked me. “About your queen?”

She nodded, and I sighed. “I’m afraid I can’t offer an easy way out. They’ll find out eventually. It’s unpleasant, but deceiving them is only likely to make things worse.”

She sighed, weakly nodding.

“But Calypter?” She looked up at me, with my ears low and eyes full of concern. “Please, try to be gentle about it, and… and try to keep them from doing anything drastic out of grief. There’s been enough death and suffering already. More won’t help anyling.”

She swallowed, nodded again, and resumed walking.

I let her lead the way past the makeshift walls that separated the changeling area from the rest of the storage lot.

The area we had given them was one of the more pleasant available. Between the two fires and the walls keeping in the heat, it was actually somewhat pleasantly warm, or at least not as frigid as our place upstairs. There was plenty of room for the changelings, and Gemstone ponies were moving around the room, setting out whatever they could arrange for bedding. Dazzle was among them, smiling and talking with a changeling who looked rather more wary about the whole exchange. There were a few more Mareford soldiers, as well, keeping an eye on things. They looked professionally attentive, but relaxed. There hadn’t been any trouble, then.

Blankets had already been distributed to those who had none, and empty crates had been arranged to form makeshift tables and chairs. The fires were both made out of empty barrels, with metal grates set on top to serve as a grill. One already had a large pot bubbling atop it. It wasn’t luxury by any means, but it was at least as much comfort as our own side was enjoying, and apparently far better than what these changelings had out in the storm.

The changelings looked much improved, as well. The dazed and numb looks had faded, even if they hadn’t entirely vanished. Most seemed to be treating their new situation in an admirably matter-of-fact fashion, with neither fear nor hostility. Even the injured changelings were doing well. While two of the injured were resting in their makeshift beds, having been given the best of what was available, the other two were upright alongside their uninjured kin.

The changelings’ reaction to my entrance was less neutral. Most of them looked my way. Expressions hardened, eyes watching me carefully. There was still little in the way of outright fear or anger, but they clearly didn’t trust me.

I stood tall, speaking in a calm but clear voice. “Excuse me.”

All eyes were on me, including Calypter’s. She stood by the nearest group of changelings, her tail tucked down between her legs. I assume she had expected some unpleasant reaction from her fellow soldiers, but they were too focused on me to spare her any attention.

I stepped forward, so I was perfectly visible to all in the room. “I wanted to express my gratitude for your peaceful surrender, and to affirm the promises we have made to you and your hive. I hope to continue working towards a resolution that doesn’t require any more bloodshed. While we continue our work toward that end, I will also be working with Dusty Trails, the commander of this army, to ensure all surrendered members of your hive are properly cared for.”

My horn lit up, the flaps of my saddlebags opening. Six love crystals floated out on my magic, full and glowing. I set them on the nearby table, the closest changelings eying them with surprise and suspicion.

“If there’s anything that you need, or if you feel you are being mistreated, please bring up your concerns with any of the ponies here, particularly Dazzle or the other Gemstone ponies.” I gestured to Dazzle, who smiled and waved to the gathered changelings. I had to smile as well, seeing her happily helping these changelings. She was a perfect embodiment of Gemstone’s ideals, and I had no doubt there were some changelings very confused by the emotions she must be radiating.

I continued. “If they’re not able to resolve the problem, then they’ll bring it to my attention, and I will personally see to it that the situation is taken care of. I know you have little reason to trust me or any of these ponies at this time, but we will do our best to earn that trust through our actions. I just ask that you give us that opportunity.”

With that said, I dipped my head, just enough to show a small degree of respect. Then I turned and made my way back out.

I was just reaching the exit when the first changeling cautiously took up one of the love crystals I had left them. I had a momentary pang of regret. Those were the same crystals Queen Ephema had left behind for my sisters and me. They were one of the few things I had of her.

I shook the feeling off. There was something fitting about this. A new queen, using those very same crystals to feed some lost and scared changelings. The smile returned, and I continued on.

☢

Dusty had broken out the food by the time we got back. We shared a meal of old oats with a side of vegetables, then sat back with a dessert of canned fruit. I got a can of peaches in heavy syrup.

I was just starting on it when Starlight scooted up beside me, a can of mixed fruit cocktail held in her magic. “You know, you make a pretty good queen.”

I blinked, almost dropping the slice of peach I was about to eat. I looked over, seeing her warm smile. It took me a moment to formulate a reply, as simple as it was. “Thanks. Though to be honest, I was just doing what felt right.”

Her smile grew, and I could swear there was a glint of mischievousness behind it. “So being the whole super-nice and regal queen is what feels right, huh?”

I snorted out a soft laugh. “Well that’s an incredibly generous way of phrasing it. No, I just had a good role model. Still…” I paused, trying to sort out my thoughts. I finally just shook my head, quietly saying, “I wonder if this was what it was like for Queen Ephema?”

Starlight’s head cocked to the side. “Hmm?”

I floated a slice of peach up, savoring the taste before swallowing. “Queen Ephema wasn’t always a queen,” I said, looking to Starlight again.

She blinked. “Really?”

“Mmmhmm,” I said, nodding. “She was hatched as a regular changeling, just like my sisters and me. When our hive was founded, she was changed into a queen. All it takes is enough love.”

“Really?” she repeated, almost dropping her can. “You mean, you can actually become a queen? Like, for real?”

“That would take a lot of love,” I said. “Normally, an egg would be infused with the love. It takes much less to do so early in development, but there’s nothing preventing it from being done with an adult. It just takes a lot more.”

She was staring at me, wide-eyed.

I responded with a shrug. “We’re changelings. Change is in our nature. Quick shapeshifting isn’t the extent of that magic. It’s like how I heal so fast from injuries. An injured changeling’s natural magic burns through love faster, altering their body to shift away the damage. It’s great, so long as you have enough love.”

“Huh,” Starlight said, setting her can down as she stared off into space. “So… Ephema did that, then?”

I nodded. “Remember, the first Chrysalis was the only queen in her hive. When she died and the survivors scattered, there wasn’t a single queen among them. Our new hive had the option of waiting to raise a new queen from an egg, or elevate an already grown and educated changeling to the role. Given the hive’s precarious position, they couldn’t really wait.”

Starlight nodded. “...So how about you, then? You could be a queen for real, right?”

“I… I could. I don’t know. Maybe.”

“Hmm.” She picked up her can once more, leaning lightly against my side. “Well, I think you’d make a great queen.”

I gave a soft chuckle, smiling down at her. “Thanks. And I guess I’m going to be stuck with the role for at least the next decade or two.” I looked off into space, quietly musing. “It’s kind of nice having the future being clear enough to think that far ahead. Dealing with Serenity is just a matter of ‘when’, not ‘if’, now. After that… I can bring back my hive.”

She grinned. “I’ll bet you do great at it,” she said, then nudged me in the side. “So, think you might have any use for a scavenger, hunter, and guard?”

“I certainly wouldn’t turn down the help, or the company.” I looped a foreleg around her shoulder, giving a soft squeeze. “You sure about that, though? That’s a long time I’m going to be stuck in once place. It’s not exactly great adventuring opportunities.”

“Hey, you remember how we met, right?” She chuckled, tilting her head to point her horn to her Lancer. “Me playing at being a guard. Hunting around in ruins for cool tech is fun and all, but what I really want to do is help protect ponies. Uh, people. And you’ve got like a hundred-something little ‘lings that could use protection. I think I could be happy with that.” She shrugged. “Plus I’ve got the wagon, so I can take off every now and then to scavenge some ruins, just for a change of pace. Pretty much everywhere is ‘nearby’ with that thing.”

Across the room, Sickle started snickering. “Just say you want to fuck her, dumbass.”

“I can have other reasons for sticking around!” Starlight shot back, and stuck her tongue out at Sickle. Then she asked, “What about you? What are you doing after all this?”

Sickle snorted, tipping back her own can to get the last of the pear chunks before tossing the can away. “Fuck if I know. I guess purple-bitch already killed off any raiders in the region—and I’m still tempted to kick your scrawny flank for that—so I don’t have much else to do. Guess I could do whatever I want. I mean, I’m all famous and shit, now. Got to be some opportunity there.”

Starlight sat abruptly upright. “Wait, famous?”

“Well, yeah!” Sickle said, chuckling. “While you dumb cunts were hanging back, I got right into the fighting. First into the bunker, first into this building, and plenty of stomping heads. Plus, you know, I kinda stand out. Gave ‘em a good show, too. One of those Serenity cunts shot me in the side with those big magic guns, gave me a nice new scar, and I just turned and caved her fucking head in, power armor and all. Those Mareford shits looked like they couldn’t believe I was still standing. Kept trying to drag me off for healing.”

I looked to her side and that missing armor plate. She hadn’t removed her armor, but I could still see the knotted, burnt flesh beneath it.

“So yeah, I can pretty much go wherever I want. I dunno. Got to be some group out there that knows how to fuck.” She fished around, eventually pulling out a beer. “Think I might start at your little hive, though. You’ve got ice cream.”

“Ice cream,” Starlight echoed, her voice skeptical.

“Fuck yes, ice cream! Chems I can find anywhere. You know how hard it is to find fucking ice cream?” A grin spread across her muzzle. “Hmm, you got a bunch of freezers and shit there. Maybe I can figure out how my mom made that stuff.”

Starlight’s face went taut. “Your mom?”

“Forget you heard that,” Sickle said, absentmindedly tapping her beer bottle against the bars of her muzzle. “Shouldn’t be too hard. Hmm. Finding milk might be a problem.”

I swallowed the last slice of peach, floating my can over to the collection of empties. “Sickle, you’ve made how many thousands of caps in the last couple of months? You could buy a brahmin for milk.”

Sickle stared silently, blinking. “...Holy shit, I could buy a brahmin. Fuck yes. All the ice cream I can eat.” She leveled a hoof my way. “Okay, I’m crashing with you for a while. Need to do something about the whole ‘fucks’ situation, but we’ll figure something out.”

Starlight managed a strangled chuckle, lost somewhere between hilarity and disbelief. “Seriously? Terrifying raider to raider-hunter to war-hero to ice cream mare?”

“Hey, I can still kick more ass and get more sex than the whole lot of you.” She grinned. “I just get to do all that and have ice cream. Or do you not want any?”

Starlight gaped for a few moments before sitting back. “...Okay, ice cream does sound kinda good.”

“Damn straight it does,” Sickle said, finally turning her attention to her beer.

Starlight softly chuckled, then looked over to Dusty. “So, what about you?”

Dusty looked up from his PipBuck. “Hmm? What about me?”

“What are you going to do after all this?”

He paused, giving it a good long thought before shrugging. “Hell if I know. I think I’m about done with all this army stuff, though.”

“You’ve got to have some idea,” Starlight said.

“Ehh.” He shrugged. “I’m pretty sure Two Bits and some of the other Mareford folk want me to come and help them. Two Bits hinted something about being mayor, but screw that. Then there’s all these changelings that need handling, and nopony knows how they’re going to do that. Hell.” He sighed, sitting back. “At this point, I’m starting to think it might be time to retire. Maybe some light duty, like watching the wall at Gemstone or something.”

I smiled. “Well, if you’re looking to settle down, you’re always welcome at my hive. You probably did more to make this possible than I did. Plus, I’m pretty sure there’s plenty of coffee and cigarettes you didn’t already loot.”

He snorted out a laugh. “I’ll think on it.”

“Guess that just leaves you,” Starlight said, now looking at Echo. “What are your plans?”

“That should be obvious,” Echo replied, setting down her own can. “Once this nonsense is done, I will finally have the time to properly analyze Whisper’s magic and research how it could aid my mother’s cause. Once that’s done, I will finally be able to free ponies from the hazards of the wasteland, by helping them rise above it.”

“Poetic,” Starlight dryly noted, before continuing on more cheerfully. “Personally, I’m thinking saving the world deserves a good vacation. I am going to kick back, relax, and just have fun for a while. Seriously, Echo, try relaxing and having a little fun for a week or two. It’ll help.”

Echo frowned. “Research is fun, especially when it’s magic. Or advanced arcane technology.”

Starlight chuckled, rolling her eyes. “Well, as long as it keeps you happy.”

The conversation meandered on for a good half an hour before fatigue started taking over. I had a smile on my face as I settled down for bed, Starlight cuddling up against my side. There was something nice about being able to just kick back and chat like this, almost unconcerned. It was something we’d been missing the last few days, like a returning piece of normality. A ray of sunshine breaking through the clouds, showing the brighter times lying ahead of us.

There was only a little more to do. We had to finish dealing with Serenity, wrap up the last of the conflict, and we’d be on to new and better things. Already, thoughts were coming together, pieces of a broader scheme falling into place.

But that could wait for morning. There would be plenty of time to think on that. Right then, I just focused on cuddling up with Starlight under those blankets, and drifted off to sleep.

Chapter Forty Eight: The Infiltrator Queen

To start off, I’d just like to apologize if this particular recording isn’t up to my usual standards. It’s remarkably difficult to form a larynx that has sufficient audio fidelity with my natural voice while still fitting into such a small form, and the acoustics of the standard Stable-Tec ventilation duct leave a great deal to be desired.

Suffice to say, it’s been an interesting day.

☢

Everything kicked off almost exactly twenty four hours ago, when all the leaders of our army came together to form a plan. We met in the center room of the incomplete office building, where a crude table had been made from sheet metal and old sawhorses. I led with a simple observation.

“Right now, Serenity can simply bunker down and wait. We can’t siege them into surrender. They’re in a Stable. It was designed with the purpose of sustaining their population without any need for outside resources. Unless we want to have soldiers parked at their door for decades to come, we need to take some sort of action to force a surrender, or if necessary, destroy them.”

Hail Burst hummed softly. “What about sealing them in? Weld the door shut, collapse the whole site on them, all that? How long would that hold them?”

“Not long. They’ve got plenty of equipment, and seem to have a decent industry. There’s an entire level of the Stable dedicated to workshops. If I had to guess, they’d be able to dig themselves out in less than a month. They might even be working on an escape tunnel right now.”

Dusty leaned forward. “I’m guessing you have some idea of how to deal with this?”

I smiled. He was right, naturally. “I do, and better yet, it’s one that focuses on saving lives. Serenity is entirely dependent on the dozens of ponies they’re holding captive. Without the love they provide, they’ll be forced to either come out or starve. It would give us the leverage to force a surrender.”

“That would be nice,” Dusty said, “but I’m not sure how we do that. We’re not breaking through that entrance without massive casualties.” He glanced to Echo. “Not even with her able to teleport in explosives.”

“I’m thinking something a bit more complicated, less head-on. I’m talking about another raid. We’ve already seen how dangerous a group of ponies can be when brought in behind enemy defenses, especially when done by surprise.”

Echo snorted softly. “While I appreciate your high appraisal of my abilities, I think you underestimate the difficulty of what you ask. You’re talking about blindly teleporting into a location I have never seen, over a distance that we can only estimate. I can assure safety for the act of teleportation itself, but I could not guarantee where we would arrive, at least not on the first trip. A small misjudgment could place us in the completely wrong room, or even the wrong level. Worse, any assault team could be split up, and I might not be able to quickly locate and evacuate them if that were to happen. This would be extremely dangerous.”

I nodded, still smiling. “I know, but what if it wasn’t blind?”

She cocked her head to the side. “Explain.”

Instead, I turned to Hail Burst. “The Cumulonimbus had video cameras, correct? Do you still have any?”

“Several, including one in each turret,” she said. “I’m sure we have at least one that still works.”

“Good. Because if we take one of those, couple it with a broadcaster, and attach one of those little lift-cloud things, we can use it to to ‘test the waters’. Echo teleports it in, we use the cameras to figure out where it arrived, and we adjust from there.”

“Could work,” Dusty mused. “They must know the danger Echo poses to them by now, so they’ve probably got internal defense already in place, but if we’re able to organize a hard, fast raid…”

Hail Burst was nodding. “Bust in, get those ponies out, and force Serenity to act instead of hiding. I like it.”

Dusty had frowned. “I’m not so sure that Serenity ‘acting’ is a good thing for us. Whisper, what’s your impression of their queen? Will she surrender, or do you think she’d do something desperate?”

“I’ve had only brief encounters with Queen Chrysalis the Sixth, but the impression I’ve gotten was of a very driven and determined individual, absolutely sure of the correctness of her actions. I tried getting more insight from Calypter, and while she is a bit… distressed by recent events, she was of the opinion that Chrysalis would never surrender to ponies.

“That said, I think I can still use the leverage the raid will gain us against the rest of her hive. I have no expectation of persuading all of them to surrender, but if we’ve removed their source of love and are offering the opportunity to surrender instead of just keeping them trapped until they starve to death, we might get some taking us up on the offer.”

Axle grimaced. “And then the ones who don’t surrender get trapped until they starve to death.” He shot me a look.

“I’m not sure what to do about those who won’t surrender,” I said. “The fact is, a changeling queen holds a special place of reverence among changelings, much like Princess Luna and Princess Celestia did among ponies. There are some who will never surrender so long as their queen refuses to, and I don’t see Queen Chrysalis surrendering. Honestly, despite the harsh conditions and the inevitability of their defeat, I’m still a little surprised that we’ve convinced as many to surrender as we have. We’re up to…” I stopped, glancing to Two Bits. “How many are we up to, now?”

“I believe we’re up to eighty two,” he said, double-checking on his PipBuck. While there hadn’t been another massive influx like the first group, surrendering changelings had slowly trickled in overnight and throughout the day. The lighter rainfall might have been a relief for them, but the rapidly dwindling supplies and numbers had convinced a few more to follow.

“Thank you,” I said, nodding, before continuing on. “That’s already more than I had expected we would manage when setting out on this expedition, and I’m feeling more optimistic for it. We know some of the hive is willing to surrender even without Queen Chrysalis. If we can put more pressure on Serenity, make them desperate, and then give them a way out, we might convince even more to surrender. Even if we don’t, we still rescue a good number of ponies.”

“Oh, yeah,” Axle grunted. “Let’s make them desperate while they’re sitting on a balefire bomb.”

Hail Burst’s eyes widened. “Holy shit. The megaspell. We just need to use that camera setup, figure out where that is, and then we can have Echo teleport in a bunch of explosives. Burn out the whole damn stable!”

“Let’s focus on getting the captives out,” I said. “We can look into our options, including the possible use of the megaspell, once we’ve gotten that sorted out. For now, I’d like to come to a consensus on this rescue attempt. Are there any objections, or shall we do this?”

“Seems like a good idea,” Hail Burst said. “Only question I have is who we’re sending in.”

“You can work that out while we’re preparing the camera system,” I said. “Personally, I would imagine we want to sent our hardest hitters. Loyalists, Mareford Rangers, as many captured power armors as possible, all of that. Maybe some heavy weapons. I think I should go, as well. I’ve operated the suspended animation pods before, even if only briefly. I’ll also want to get inside so I can see about splicing into their public intercom. If we’re going to convince more of the hive to surrender, we need to communicate with them, and they’re not listening to the radio.”

Echo was frowning again, but didn’t say anything.

“Works for me,” Hail Burst said. “The assault force goes first, though.”

I nodded. “Of course. There isn’t any point in me being there until we have secured the control room, after all.”

She nodded. “Okay. I’ll see about getting you the equipment you need. Anything else?”

“I think that’s it,” I said, before looking around. “Are we agreed, then?”

Voices of agreement came from all around the table, and the group rose, heading off to their own tasks. I caught Dusty’s attention, asking to speak with him privately. Echo’s frown deepened, but she allowed us our privacy.

We stepped into a neighboring room, alone for the moment. Dusty stopped and turned, looking at me critically. “Putting off planning ahead doesn’t seem like you,” he noted. “What’s up?”

I smiled. I do really love his insight at times. “I am planning ahead. I just didn’t want to discuss it in public.”

He sighed. “Okay, that seems more like you. Are you going to leave me guessing, or would you like to fill me in?”

“That’s what I wanted to talk to you about.” I walked over to the window, sitting by the window. With the rain reduced to a light drizzle, we actually had a view, even it it was fairly bland. “This raid is important, and we need to get those ponies out, but I think we can do more with it. I want to use it as a distraction.”

“A distraction for what?”

“I’m an Infiltrator,” I said, shrugging. “Part of that includes scouting out or infiltrating facilities to gather vital information. We already know I can use their ventilation system to move around with some degree of secrecy, though I won’t say it’s entirely safe. That’s why I want to use a distraction. While they’re preoccupied with our raid, I want to use the opportunity to scout out the hive, and see what further action I might be able to take to end all of this.”

He was frowning, quiet and thoughtful. “...Depends. What ‘further action’ are you thinking of?”

“Two come to mind,” I said. “The first is simple: locate the balefire megaspell, so that we can either take it or detonate it. We can’t leave it in their possession. I am concerned that, if they are driven too far into desperation, they may decide to use it to wipe us out, even if it destroys themselves in the process. They may see that as preferable to being subjugated by ponies.

“The second is dealing with the greatest obstacle we face: Queen Chrysalis the Sixth. I don’t think she will ever surrender, and I expect the great majority of the hive will refuse to leave her side. I want to investigate the plausibility of removing her.”

“You mean assassination,” Dusty said. It wasn’t a question so much as a clarification of what I said.

“Yes. It’s a messy situation. Killing her may even harden some of the more devoted changelings, but without her presence, at least some might be willing to surrender. I think it’s worth investigating, to see if it’s plausible.”

He grunted. “I don’t know. You keep talking about how much changelings revere their queens. Killing her might make ‘em use the megaspell.”

“Which is why the megaspell comes first,” I said.

He was silent for a few more seconds before sighing. “Okay, yeah. Scouting things out might be good. Hail Burst was right; if we know where the megaspell is being stored, we can end this any time we want. We’ll just need enough time to get everypony away, but it only takes a few dozen to hold the door. We’ve got transport to get them away quick.” He paused a moment before adding, “Good luck convincing Echo to go along with this.”

“I think I can handle that.”

☢

To start with, I visited Calypter again. Naturally, Echo wasn’t going to leave me alone and defenseless in the midst of all those changelings, so she walked with me, her critical eyes turning to any changeling who so much as looked at me.

My first stop was the center table, where the six love crystals sat, empty. For the second time, I pushed out my magic, the glow rekindling within them. I’d burned through a lot of magic in the past day. I was finding this regal disguise easier to hold, but it still drained a fair amount of magic. Add in feeding all these changelings, and it was starting to put some stress on me. Or more accurately, it was putting some stress on the people I was feeding on. Starlight had mentioned feeling more tired than usual. I’d have to start rationing a bit more.

With that done, I turned to find Calypter. She was sitting with a group of three other changelings, who all looked on uneasily as I approached them. Calypter looked particularly awkward, especially as I addressed her.

“Hello again, Calypter. Can we talk?”

She glanced around before looking back to me, her ears drooping. “I can’t really say no, can I?”

“You could,” I said. “You may all technically be our prisoners, but I’m not going to put that sort of demand on you. That said, I’d like to ask you something that might help your hivemates.”

She sighed and nodded. “Okay.”

I sat there, beside her and her fellow changelings. Echo remained standing watchfully behind me, while the other changelings watched, distrust and unease evident in their expressions.

“I’ve been talking with Dazzle and Two Bits,” I said. “We’ve been working out how to get you all situated and fed, once this is all over. I’ve only got the basic outline settled so far, but I’d like to get feedback from you, or any of the other changelings here.”

Her head tilted ever so slightly. “Uh… okay? What is it?”

“The short version is, they think there are places where they could use more hooves to help out. I think we’ll be able to arrange food and housing in exchange for work. We all agree it would be better to at least offer the opportunity rather than just dumping you out in the Wasteland to fend for yourselves. I don’t think that would be good for anyone.”

Calypter frowned. “So we get to be slave labor or starve. Wonderful.”

“Absolutely not,” I said. “You’ll be treated the same as any pony in the same job. I was prepared to insist on it, but they had already decided to do so without my intervention. It might be a good while before you’ll be trusted with more sensitive work, like guard duty, and you’ll probably be watched carefully at first, but you’ll be treated fairly. And while I doubt it will be necessary, I will be double-checking to make sure that promise is upheld.”

I could see their suspicion rising in their expressions. Perhaps I was playing the whole Generosity thing up too much.

I smiled and rolled my eyes. “If you’re looking for any self-interest, my hive will have to live alongside ponies as well, once it’s established again. It’s in my interest to promote the acceptance of changelings as friends and equals. I think we’ll all be better off working together.”

They continued to stare at me, until Calypter grunted quietly. “Guess we’ll see.”

“There’s a lot to be gained from such a cooperation,” I said, still smiling. “We are far more versatile than ponies, able to adapt better to our roles. Then there’s the advantage of flight. You might have noticed there’s a severe lack of pegasi here below the clouds, which opens up a great many opportunities for us. We have a lot to offer. At the same time, ponies are also better than us at some things. Earth ponies have their innate magic, from strength to enhanced crafting to magical agriculture, and unicorns can perform magic that’s beyond all but the most talented of changeling queens.”

Calypter looked to the other changelings sitting nearby, who all looked equally unsure of what to think of all this.

“What I’m saying is, you’re not going to be forced into dangerous or demeaning work, and there will be plenty of opportunities for better employment. Jobs like craftsmares, or couriers, or the like.” I paused, then gave a little chuckle as I glanced at Echo. “Or magical research.”

Echo eyed me warily.

I looked back to Calypter. “Actually, that might be a good example of cooperation. Echo here is conducting research into changeling magic. She believes she can make the world better for both ponies and changelings by crossing over the behavior of one species’s magic to the other. She’s been watching me shapeshift, though I have to admit, I’ve been a bit preoccupied lately. She might offer a job as research assistant. Love, food, and shelter, in exchange for shapeshifting every now and then. How does something like that sound?”

Echo’s wary glare was now fixed firmly upon me, the other changelings forgotten. Meanwhile, Calypter cast a quick glance to her companions before turning a suspicious eye to me. “That certainly sounds generous…”

“We’re trying,” I said, smiling and giving a little shrug. “Though it wouldn’t surprise me if Dazzle already talked your ear off about Generosity.”

The change in Calypter’s expression was subtle. Her ears twitched forward, head rising a hair, the hardness of her expression relaxing ever so slightly. “She has,” she said, and as she spoke, I caught a momentary flicker of emotion. It was hard to make out, some low-level but sincere appreciation, perhaps. Dazzle was making an impression on these changelings.

Both sides were following in the hoofsteps of Emerald, in their own way, and my smile grew at the thought.

“Yeah, she’s good at that,” I said. “Anyway, I mostly just wanted to ask about that, to get a reaction to any plans for the future. There isn’t anything firm in place just yet. Probably won’t be, until this is all resolved. And…” I had steadily shifted to a frown as I talked, ending with my ears drooping slightly. “Well, there was another thing I wanted to ask you, and it’s not quite as cheerful.”

Concern had returned to Calypter’s face. “What’s that?”

I gave a sigh before continuing. “The situation is coming to a head. Right now, it looks like Queen Chrysalis intends to fight to the death, and she’ll take the rest of your hive down with her. I… I know the previous attempt wasn’t successful, but I was hoping you might have some insight on how we might convince your queen to surrender, instead.”

Calypter’s expression fell, ears drooping. She looked down, her voice quiet. “She’s… not my queen. She disowned me.”

“And I think we both know that doesn’t make you any less devoted to her or your hive,” I said, my voice soft. “Or that it makes any of this less painful.”

She winced, turning away slightly. “...No.” She huffed in a deep breath before continuing. “I… I can’t think of anything.”

“I’m sorry to hear that,” I said. “I’ll still give it my best try, but at this point… well, I wanted to make sure you were forewarned.”

Calypter’s breathing had deepened, and I saw her blink several times. She didn’t answer.

“I’m sorry,” I said, rising to my hooves. “I hope I’ll have good news when I talk to you again.”

Still no answer. She sniffled once as I started to walk away.

I steadily made my way out, weaving through the small crowd of changelings. Every single one of them watched me.

We had just exited when Echo stepped up closer to me, her eyes narrowed. “What are you up to?”

“Echo, I—”

“You’re going to do something foolhardy and reckless, aren’t you?” she said, moving in close. With her hair flowing aggressively and wings spread, she did a great deal to make up the head’s difference in height between us. “That’s what that was all about? Right?”

I sighed, and motioned further down the tunnel. “We need some privacy.”

“Fine.” She stalked past me, and I followed, avoiding her strangely ethereal tail.

Once we had gotten a safe distance down the spacious tunnel, she turned to glare at me again. “Well?”

“To start with,” I said, coming to a halt before her, “I do not intend to be reckless. I plan on taking a carefully calculated risk, and—”

“And you know quite well that your appraisal of risk and mine do not in any way match up. You risk not only your own life! You risk delaying the salvation of all ponykind!”

I habitually raised a hoof to correct her. “All people, not—”

“Ugh!” she groaned, throwing her head back in an exaggerated show of frustration.

“And in any case, I knew you would object, and that’s why I wanted to bring you to speak with Calypter.”

“Yes, I understand exactly what you are trying to do,” she said, fixing me with a glare again. “You’re being deceptive and manipulative to get what you want, again.”

“I’m not being deceptive in the slightest,” I said, frowning. “Misleading or hiding information would be counterproductive. The entire intent was to establish another source for your research if something were to happen to me, so I could then use that to ease your concerns, and none of that would work if I didn’t present it upfront and clearly to you.”

She frowned as well. “...Yes, well, it was still very manipulative.”

“Ponies might not like to say it, but any conversation where one party wants to convince someone to do something they don’t want to do is essentially manipulative in some degree. Coercion, rationalization, appeals to emotion, bartering, they’re all ways of getting someone to do something they’re not otherwise inclined to do. I’m bartering. You want a cooperative changeling to assist in your research, so I ensured you will have one, regardless of what might happen to me.”

I gave her a moment to contemplate that before adding, “And I could also note that I’ve already arranged that assistance for you, regardless of whether you choose to accept my proposal in return.”

Her thoughtful look vanished under a flat glare. “That is manipulative.”

I smiled. “Maybe a little.”

She held the glare for a couple of seconds before looking away. “You are so incredibly frustrating. Part of me wants to be angry with you, while another part of me admires the way you construct arguments in such a rigorous fashion. It’s so… conflicting.” She sighed and shook her head, fixing me with a fresh glare. “Fine. What are you planning?”

☢

Echo’s irritation was at least mollified once she started tinkering with the equipment I had requested.

The pair of cameras Hail Burst supplied us with were rugged devices, each about the size of a loaf of bread. While Echo and Starlight worked on getting one mated to a small lift-cloud generator salvaged from a cargo-lift, I hooked up a spare PipBuck and broadcaster to the other for testing purposes.

A few quick tests with my diagnostics equipment mapped the outputs, and a bit of spell-matrix wrangling adapted the existing data-channel functionality of Serenity’s encryption spell to work with the video output. More difficult was the awkward bridging of another PipBuck’s receiver to a banged-up video monitor. Convincing the PipBuck’s spell matrix to pass on the data stream was an awkward affair. I’m a little embarrassed to admit it, but in the interest of saving time, I kludged a solution by copying much of the functionality of the audio playback and rewiring the audio jack. I didn’t even have a soldering iron, so it was all twisted wires and a few bits of stripped insulation tied around it to prevent shorts, with a few circuit connections simply wonderglued in place.

I didn’t manage to get that all working until the next morning. As soon as we were done with breakfast, it was time to try it all out.

Both PipBucks were set to the new frequency. The monitor was turned on, showing static. Finally, I turned the camera to look out from the sheet-metal desk to where Echo and Starlight sat, and turned it on.

The static remained unchanged. I frowned.

A second later, a flicker darted across the very top of the screen. It repeated, just a hair lower. Then again, and again, and again. As it worked its way down, shapes and forms started to show, starting with the tip of Echo’s horn and making its way down.

It was at least twenty seconds before the off-center image was complete, a single frozen snapshot of time.

The top of the image then started to fill with the next frame, identical to the first. This was a problem. Contrary to what the screen was showing, Echo now had an expression of confusion and dissatisfaction, while Starlight wasn’t even there any more, having moved to look at the monitor.

“Well,” she said, cocking her head to the side. “It kinda works.”

I’d finally adjusted the display to center the image, and another little tweak adjusted the horizontal and vertical size to more-or-less fill the display. The second frame was complete, slowly being replaced by a third. “Not well enough to be useful,” I grumbled. “I’ll have to check a few things. Maybe there’s something in the spell matrix that’s holding up the process.”

So it was time for one of the most time-consuming and difficult parts of any complex project: troubleshooting and debugging.

The first step was simple enough: remove all of the intermediary parts and ensure that the camera and monitor were functioning correctly. I disconnected the PipBucks and broadcasters, and plugged the two devices directly into each other. The result was a perfect image with good framerate. This meant there was a problem somewhere in my solution, but this was a good thing; it meant this was something I could work on fixing.

Having established that the hardware on both ends was functioning correctly, I reassembled the chain of devices to investigate all that lay between. The next likely suspect was the encryption process, so I hooked up my own PipBuck and all my nice debugging tools, watching the spell matrix as it processed the video feed. Sure enough, it was using almost all of its processing ability on this data stream. This led to a short diversion before a second look revealed that it was processing the data as fast as the camera could provide it. It wasn’t the bottleneck.

A little more digging turned up something unusual. The encryption program fed into a buffer that was then sent to the broadcaster for transmission, but that buffer grew at an incredible rate. Even with an entire frequency to itself, the broadcaster’s radio simply didn’t have enough bandwidth to transmit the data in real-time. I was trying to pour a waterfall through a garden hose.

I turned to tweaking the video feed. Stripping the color channels from the luminance channel turned the image black-and-white, but also gave a small improvement in the time-per-frame. Next was the much more complicated effort of messing with the camera’s output. Its simplistic spell matrix was, ironically, much harder to work with, as it left me with fewer options to tweak. Many things I expect would normally be programmable were handled by dedicated crystal arrays, and altering them would have required rebuilding the whole thing. I eventually gave up and started replicating some of their behavior in a new spell on the broadcasting PipBuck.

This took up the bulk of the time, at least two hours. What I ended up with was a crude and likely far-from-optimal piece of spell-work, but it accomplished my goals. It stripped down the data and let me recompile it, with simple variables to control the resolution and the range of output values. By reducing those, I was finally able to bring the size of the data stream below the bandwidth limitations of the broadcaster.

The resulting image was tiny and rapidly scrolling end-over-end. I had to tweak the monitor’s settings all the way to their limits to get the display working properly. In the end, the video was grainy and washed-out, but I had cut the time-per-frame to about a tenth of a second. The entire chain of multiple encodings and decodings, plus transmission time, had also led to a good quarter-second of latency, but I was willing to overlook that. If I had more time, I might have worked on improving it, but it was sufficient for our purposes.

The time this took gave Echo and Starlight plenty of time to finish their part. By the time we sat down to lunch, they had gotten the camera-cloud floating, with a pair of desk fans wired up to a receiver. A simple tone broadcast on the right channel would activate each fan, allowing it to pitch and yaw.

Echo waved a hoof dismissively when I praised the ingenuity. “Compared to advanced arcano-tech engineering, this was trivial.” She managed to hold out a whole three seconds before adding, “But it was fun.”

After we presented our work to Dusty, it was time to get things rolling. While I prepared the equipment I would need for my own mission, he contacted Two Bits and Hail Burst, calling them over to brief them face-to-face.

By the time I had returned, a small bag in tow, they were down to discussing plans and tactics. Dusty brought me in to brief them on what we would be facing.

“This entire level appears dedicated to their suspended animation technology,” I said as I presented my PipBuck and the relevant map. We all huddled around the tiny display. “That presumably includes both the simulated Serenity where they keep their prisoners, and the combat simulations they used to train their soldiers. We were held in Simulation Chamber One, here.”

I tapped the map. It was one of three chambers, separated by long halls that split the level into thirds. The chambers themselves took up most of the level.

“I only had the two brief experiences with the place, so I can’t say what most of their standard operating procedures were, but I can tell you what the situation was when I was there. The chamber appeared to have an operating staff of eight. The one policy I do know is that there is a hard minimum of two staff in the control room at the back of the chamber, here. Two more were roaming the section, checking systems and the like. And finally, there were four changelings in pods, managing the prisoners inside the simulation. I don’t know what percentage of their time they actually spend in the pod, and it’s possible there were extra that day because of the new prisoners. That said, they’re oblivious to the world outside, but the control room has a way to communicate with them, and they appear able to revive themselves if they don’t get a response.

“So we can expect a minimum of four to eight changelings. Given that they’re certainly aware of Echo’s teleportation and will take steps to mitigate its threat, there may be soldiers stationed throughout the Stable. The staff might have also been armed.”

“That’s a lot of territory to spread out guards,” Hail Burst noted. “And we cut off most of their army. Even if they prioritize a few key locations, they’ll be spread thin until they can reinforce. If we catch them by surprise and move quickly, we might be able to take a few defensive choke points and hold them. What are we looking at for access points?”

“That depends on how much we plan to take and hold,” I said. “I have no idea what’s in the other two simulation chambers. Given the size of the simulated combats Serenity conducted, it’s possible that the entirety of those chambers was used for that purpose, but I can’t be sure. We’d have to actually go in to find out.”

“Couldn’t you send in the camera?”

“They’re likely to be occupied, and the teleportation isn’t very subtle. If we do it before kicking off our attack, they’ll know something is about to happen, and have a good idea of where it will be. During the attack itself, teleporting the camera means not teleporting soldiers, and let’s not forget that even Echo’s magic is finite.”

Two Bits leaned in to peer closer at the map. “...Okay, the first chamber will be the primary objective. If we use that back hallway as a choke point, then it’s just that and the two doors into the main chamber. We’ll probably want to push out a little, and if we hold each end of the hallway outside those doors, and the intersection between them, that’s four, with good fallback positions. We can lock that down with a few squads, while the rest push out to check the other chambers.

“If we do need to hold them… hmm. It looks like there’s only four stairways and three lifts, and there are two pairs that open into the same room. That’s just five access points for the whole level. That’s easily doable. We’ll need more ponies to sweep the rest of the level, but once that’s done, they’ll have a hell of a time uprooting us.”

“It may not be that simple,” I said. “Remember, these are changelings. We can be very tricky. Shapeshifting into a smaller form can turn any vent into an access point. They may not be able to make an assault out of the vents, but if there’s an unobserved room, they could easily arrange the same sort of surprise attack we’re planning.”

“That… puts a damper on things. Hmm.” He looked over the map some more. “How long do you think it will take you to get ponies out of the pods?”

“Assuming I remember the procedure correctly, it’s about thirty seconds or so for the pod to cycle open, and less than a minute before the subject recovers consciousness. They’ll probably be disoriented and erratic, so waking a large number at once might cause problems.”

“Echo can teleport them out as soon as they’re out,” Hail Burst said. “Let the ponies out here deal with that mess.”

“Not a bad idea,” I said, nodding. “Saves us time, too. Assuming you’re up to that much teleportation?”

Echo was frowning, her gaze shifting slightly before fixing on me again. “It should be well within my ability… so long as there aren’t too many.”

“Even after teleporting everyone in?” Two Bits asked. “Because looking at this, I’m putting a hard minimum of two platoons to do this, if we have to push out to secure those other chambers, and that’s assuming we fall back quickly. I’d prefer three.”

Echo tilted her head. “How many is that?”

“Eighty to ninety ponies, minimum. Preferably more.”

Echo’s frown deepened. “...Yes, I believe I should be able to do that… but I am not certain I’ll be able to get everyone out again without a rest to recover. I shall try my best.”

“How long a rest?”

She contemplated that for a moment, her eyes darting across the ceiling as she made calculations. “Approximately an hour, if I am able to rest. Less, if we could find a source of radiation. Maybe as much as two, if there are a lot of ponies to be rescued.”

“Two hours is fine,” Two Bits said. “If we can get two platoons down there, we should be able to hold that chamber indefinitely.”

“Just be ready for any tricks,” I said. “They had gas defenses outside the Stable. They may have more they could use inside. They might also do like they did on the Cumulonimbus and breach a wall or ceiling to make a new access point.”

He nodded. “Yeah, I’ll be planning internal security, too. My plan is to move quick to secure the secondary objectives, then fall back to the primary. Teleport out any ponies in the secondaries that we can, haul the rest back, and hold until Echo is able to get everyone out. That minimizes the risk of breaching. As for gas, the rangers have masks. I assume those power armors of yours do, too?”

Hail Burst nodded. “Our face-masks have filters. I’ll make sure everyone buttons up for the op.”

“Good, because I definitely want you in on this. You, the Rangers, and all the captured power armors. Round out with experienced Militia units. Sound good?”

“Yeah.”

They turned to Dusty, who nodded. “Good. Bitsy, you’re lead on this. You can have your pick of the army. Make this happen.”

Two Bits grinned. “Yes sir.”

☢

Half an hour later, the army was in motion. Under Sandalwood’s command, the bulk of the Mareford Militia was setting out into the light rain, taking up scattered defensive positions all around the site.

I had frequently lamented the two-dimensional thinking behind the E.F.S. design, so it was with some satisfaction that we were now taking advantage of it. Any Serenity defender would see hostile contacts in all directions, obscuring our movements. We had no idea how much of the Stable was in E.F.S. range of the surface, but at least the upper levels were. Hopefully it would reach down to the level we were going to.

In the center room of the building’s ground floor, our assault force had gathered. Almost a hundred ponies, many in power armor, stood ready to begin the rescue.

Dusty stepped into our room, where we waited with Two Bits. “Okay. We’re all set up here. Bitsy, kick it off.”

“Yes, sir,” he said, and turned to Echo. “Find me a way in.”

She nodded. “We should be directly above the target room,” she said as she stepped up to the floating camera-rig. I watched the delayed image of her movements in the monitor. “The only question is estimating the correct distance down.”

With a flash, the floating camera disappeared. The screen flashed with a single frame of nonsense, then turned dark. For a moment, I thought it had stopped transmitting, but then I saw the shadow of shapes. The room it was in was dark.

“Rotate right,” I said, and Starlight twisted the corresponding dial. Somewhere below us, the camera slowly turned, and a quarter second later, so did the image it was sending us. As it turned, I could see shelves, loaded with boxes and other containers. “Bring it back.”

The camera returned with a flash as I turned to my PipBuck, consulting the map. “...Yeah, that matches up with the storage room here, two levels up from the target. Near the ceiling, too.”

“I see,” Echo said. “I will try again.”

Another flash. The screen flickered, then started showing blackness.

“Light,” I said.

Starlight pressed a button, and the screen of the camera’s attached PipBuck came to life, turned up to maximum brightness. It was near the floor, and as the camera panned around, we could see the room was plain, vacant, and sterile, with only a pair of benches within it. It was the same room I had been held in after waking up from Serenity’s simulation. The same room where I had rescued Sickle. A reasonably sized room, just off the main chamber, but used infrequently at best.

“And you got it,” I said, grinning. “You’re low to the floor, but otherwise good.”

Echo nodded. “One last check.”

With a flash, she was gone.

A moment later, the video flashed, and Echo appeared, staggering as she dropped a foot to the ground. She straightened, and nodded, and teleported again. The flash of her arrival beat the flash of her departure in the video.

Echo gave a thin, proud smile. “We are ready.”

Two Bits turned to Hail Burst. “Okay. You’re up.”

Hail Burst nodded and stepped forward. Five more loyalists followed as they gathered around Echo. Then, with a flash, they were gone.

Two Bits called out. “Next team, move up!”

I watched Hail Burst’s team move to cover the door, while the next six Loyalists marched up to Echo. She looked at the monitor, and as soon as the first team had cleared a spot, she teleported the second group in.

Teleport after teleport, the number of ponies in the distant room grew. By the time the last Loyalist was teleported in, they were clearly running out of room.

The radio squawked and came to life with Hail Burst’s voice. “Taking initial positions. Be ready on the music.”

I cast a quick glance to the bulky communications equipment set beside the desk. The indicators were lit, and the spark generator it was plugged into was running. I keyed in. “Music is ready.”

The Loyalists were already heading out the door. They would be taking up initial positions in the access hall, which would give plenty of room and easy defenses, but the chances of a random passing changeling spotting them went up significantly.

The moment they were clear, Echo teleported Two Bits and the first Ranger team. Following teleports took the other Ranger team, then two groups of Mareford Militia in captured power armor, including the massive Steel Ranger suit. Sickle was with them, and gave me a toothy grin, eager to get to work.

Echo’s general air of calm pride steadily decayed, replaced with a look of grim determination. I assumed she was feeling the strain of tearing a few tons of people and equipment out of reality and popping them back into existence a hundred yards away.

As the next group of soldiers were teleported, Two Bits called on the radio. “Beginning assault. Start the music.”

The salvaged communications equipment whined as it came to life. The video feed flickered faintly as the jammer flooded the nearby Serenity frequency. “Music is on.”

My awareness of the events below was restricted to the rare communication on the command net and a tiny slice of video from the room below. I could only imagine what was going on.

Apparently, my imagination was lacking. I was guessing that the fighting must be kicking off when Two Bits radioed out. “Primary secure. Queen is cleared to enter.”

Echo grunted. “As soon as I get the last of these soldiers down there,” she said, horn flashing as another batch disappeared.

I called up my magic, stripping away my disguise. My armor reappeared, fitting snugly around my body. I checked the fit of my holster, and slung my pack across my back. Then it was down to waiting for my turn.

The last group vanished, and Echo turned to look at me.

As I stepped forward, Starlight’s hoof caught my leg. “Hey,” she said, giving a nervous smile. “Good luck.”

I smiled back. “See you soon.”

She smiled a little more, and lowered her hoof. I continued on to stand beside Echo.

The world twisted around me as Echo’s magic deposited us both in the distant chamber below the ground. A pair of Rangers were waiting for us, already wearing their gas masks. The closest gestured with a hoof, her voice muffled behind her mask. “This way, ma’am.”

The pair set out at a trot, and I kept pace with them, even as I pulled out and donned my own respirator mask. A burst of automatic fire echoed from down the hall, followed by the sound of magical energy weapons firing, before silence returned. The fighting was continuing, but it was still low-key. Serenity’s reinforcements hadn’t arrived yet.

The pair of Rangers led us to the control room. I hesitated before stepping across the thin dusting of pink ash that had been one of the changelings stationed there. Through the windows, I could see the main chamber itself. A few ponies were trotting toward one of the doors, while a half-dozen had taken up positions around the room. I could see the form of a downed changeling near the middle of the room, clad in armor. So they had some soldiers here, after all.

Two Bits was at the window, and looked back as I entered. “Welcome to the party. Hail Burst is breaching the second chamber right now. Should have word on that soon.”

“Thank you,” I said, eyes roaming around the room. I quickly found what I was looking for and strode over, snatching up the binder and opening it.

“What’s that?” Two Bits asked.

“Operating manual.” I continued flipping until I found the relevant section. “No harm in refreshing my memory while I have the chance.”

He’d stopped, ear twitching, then focused on his broadcaster. “Understood.” He lowered it and looked to me. “Chamber two is vacant. They’re moving on the last chamber.”

I nodded, looking back and forth between the manual and the various control panels, mentally running through the procedure to open the pods. It was fairly straightforward.

The sound of weapon fire reached my ear again. Two Bits glanced back. “They’re running into some light resistance, but they should have the chamber secure in—”

A loud squelch cut him off as the Stable’s PA system came to life. “Alert! Alert! Intruders have breached the simulation level. Wireless communications are compromised. All active security not on entrance duty are to converge on the simulation level immediately. All inactive and emergency defense forces are to immediately assemble at your designated rally point and join the defense.”

Two Bits frowned at the speaker. “Well, they were going to catch on eventually.” He turned back to his broadcaster. “Hail, you heard the lady. It’s going to get pretty spicy, pretty quick.”

He was silent a moment, ears perked, before speaking again. “Understood. She’s on the way.” He lowered the broadcaster. “They’ve got ponies. Chamber Three. Snapshot, get Queen Whisper there. Double-time.”

The Ranger mare gave a sharp nod to him, then a wave of a hoof toward me. “Follow us, ma’am.”

I snapped the binder shut, floating it along with me as I followed. Snapshot set a brisk pace, setting off at a canter as she led us out through the main chamber and into the connecting hall. The sounds of combat were already picking up, with rapid fire echoing down the corridors. Rounding a corner, I could see the backs of several Mareford ponies, including a couple of power armors, taking cover a good fifty yards down the hall, ready to repel attackers. The door into the chamber was just behind them.

Snapshot came to a halt by the door, raising her PipBuck. “Friendlies coming in, south door.” A momentary pause, then she opened the door, leading us in.

Hail Burst was there to meet us, her armor amplifying her voice. “Whisper. We’ve got five ponies and a griffin in here. Everything else is vacant.” She pointed to the shattered windows overlooking us. “The control room is secure, but not the access hall. Use the window.”

“Got it,” I said. “Thank you.”

While she passed word on ahead, Echo and I took to the air, flying up to the window. We passed Sickle along the way, sitting beside a mangled changeling soldier. She gave a cheerful wave as we passed. She’d managed to get herself all bloody again, and I think most of it wasn’t hers.

The control room was trashed, having been subjected to a withering amount of fire, and scorch marks and craters pocked the walls. Almost all of the glass had been blown out of the windows, leaving us plenty of room to slip in. Another pair of pegasi were waiting for us. One gave a curt nod before turning his attention back to the entrance.

I turned and scanned the controls. Fortunately, they were undamaged.

A quick scan of the indicators located the six occupied pods. With the flip of a few switches, buzzers sounded and lights flashed over the pods. Another couple of switches disengaged various systems, and in less than thirty seconds, the pod doors were swinging open.

I looked to Echo. “You’re up.”

She nodded, spreading her wings to fly down, and I followed. She floated the unconscious ponies and griffin from their pods, gathering them together. A couple of them were just starting to stir when they vanished with a flash.

“Okay,” Hail Burst said in her mechanical voice. “Get your royal flank back to Two Bits. Enclave! Thirty seconds and we’re falling back!”

“Good luck!” I called out, and then we were cantering alongside Snapshot again, dashing out into the hall. In the minute we’d been inside, the volume of fire had grown tremendously. We slowed to a trot once we got back inside the main chamber, sufficiently removed from the combat for the moment. Shortly after that, we were climbing the steps to the control room once more.

Two Bits greeted us with a wordless nod, continuing his conversation on the radio. “Queen has arrived safely. Continue falling back. Call if you need support.” He listened a moment further before lowering his PipBuck again. “If Hail Burst and company can fall back and don’t get pinned down, we’re good here. Echo, will you be able to evacuate these captives?”

She grimaced, but quickly hid the expression. She couldn’t hide how her strange, ethereal mane appeared to hang lower, as if it were somehow more physical than usual. “How many ponies are there?”

“Fifty-five. Not including the two changelings still in their pods.”

Echo grunted. “That’s a lot. But… yes, I believe I can. It will leave me quite drained, however.”

“That’s fine,” he replied. “The sooner we can get them out of this place, the sooner Whisper can start her thing.”

As she made her way back to the main chamber, I turned to the controls again. After a quick scan over the occupied pods, I started opening them in groups of five.

I had just opened the third set when Two Bits told me the Loyalists had fallen back to our primary defensive line. We were as dug-in and prepared as we could be.

Not that it dissuaded Serenity any. The fighting was ferocious, and several blasts shook the floor under my hooves. Two Bits was quiet, listening in on the radio, but barring some crisis, there was little for him to do.

Finally, the last prisoner vanished. I could see Echo give a weary sigh before slumping down to sit against one of the pods, a hoof moving to massage the side of her head.

The captives were safe. Time to make use of that.

Two Bits had supplied one of the PipBucks they had retrieved from slain Serenity changelings, with its precious encryption key. I set it in front of me, then turned to my own broadcaster and our private channel. “Hey, Starlight. We’re set down here. Could you kill the jammer?”

“You got it.”

I floated the captured PipBuck, retaking my queenly disguise. After all, I wanted to properly sound the part.

Warbling sounds came from the PipBuck’s speakers, as transmissions struggled against the interference. Several seconds later, the traffic cleared up, and I hit the button to transmit.

“Attention, Serenity hive. This is Queen Whisper. As you no doubt are aware, pony forces have conducted a raid inside your hive. Your defenses are incapable of protecting you. We have just teleported out the last captive held in suspended animation.

“I understand the significance of what we have done, and the severity of the situation you find yourselves in. Despite this, we have no desire to see you starve. We are willing to offer safe shelter to all who surrender. Already, the majority of your army on the surface has surrendered. They are being cared for as we speak.

“Please, do not throw away your lives. Lay down your arms and surrender to these ponies before it is too late.”

I released the key, bringing the transmission to an end, and immediately turned back to my own PipBuck. “Okay, Starlight. Turn it back on.”

“Jammer on. Good luck.” She sounded so far away.

Two Bits looked to me. “Think it’ll work?”

I sighed. “No. But that’s why I’m here.”

I met up with Echo, and we made our way to the room we had first arrived in. A pair of ponies were there to watch the room’s lone vent. Snapshot ushered them out and shut the door behind her, leaving Echo and me in private.

With the door shut, I turned to the vent.

As I worked, the Stable’s PA speakers squawked, followed by Two Bit’s voice. He gave his own offer of surrender, both reaching those who hadn’t been listening to the radio and reaffirming my own words.

The vent popped free. Echo eyed the opening warily. “Are you sure about this?”

“I am.” No point in elaborating.

I called up my magic, and the world expanded around me. When I was done, I was in the same changeling-horned raccoon form I had used before. I gathered up my PipBuck, hooking it on a strap of my bag. My holster was strapped on beside it. Finally, I took up the strap in my teeth. The bag only weighed about ten or fifteen pounds, and while that was proportionally a lot heavier than I was used to, due to my current size, the strap made it easy to drag.

I crawled into the vent, dragging my bag behind me. Once I’d gotten in far enough to shove it aside and backtrack, I snatched the grate that had covered the vent, pulling it back into place.

Echo had crouched down, looking at me through the gaps. “Be careful… and good luck.”

I smiled a raccoon smile, clumsily squeaking, “Thank you.”

Then I turned, took up the strap once more, and scurried off.

☢

Progress was slow. The bag dragged behind me, and required a little extra attention on the corners. Fortunately, it wasn’t too encumbering, but it did slow me down. The ventilation ducts were dark, lit only by thin slices of light where a vent looked in on a lit room, and snaked their way around the level like a maze. Fortunately, my PipBuck was automatically mapping this new space.

I’d been crawling for barely a minute when a clattering sound reached my ears, echoing from the duct ahead of me. The source was immediately apparent to me: I wasn’t alone in these vents.

Scurrying back a couple of yards, I hauled the bag down a pitch-black side passage. From the map, I knew it was a dead-end, but I had no choice. I conjured a tiny flicker of light, barely a candle, to guide my way, quickly reaching the vent barely thirty feet from the intersection. The room beyond was dark, and the vent itself created a tiny nook. I pushed the bag back behind me, tucking both it and myself against the grate of the vent. I didn’t have the time to open the vent, especially without making enough noise to give myself away.

Instead, I used what little cover there was to minimize my silhouette, hoping they wouldn’t see me. I floated my pistol forward, gripping the cumbersome object in my much-too-small paws. When my magic released, the candle-like glow disappeared, plunging me into darkness.

The sounds grew louder. I had to hope that they continued on the other way, and didn’t notice the gray lump in the darkness.

Whoever it was navigating the tunnels, they didn’t cast any light. The sound grew louder, and I focused on keeping my breathing slow and steady.

At the end of the passage, I saw a dark form shuffle across the gap, all sharp edges and faint glossy highlights. Some sort of insectoid form, most likely. I couldn’t catch any details, but I assumed it was a form much more suited to combat than my own. I’m not sure if that was an entirely justified assumption, but I didn’t care to test it. Better to assume the worst.

The sound was fading again, as they continued on down the duct. A lone changeling, then, likely conducting reconnaissance, and I was now behind them. Of course, they would be conducting reconnaissance for a larger group. If she found a good approach, these narrow ducts might become uncomfortably crowded.

I counted out thirty seconds before daring to stir. Turning back to my PipBuck, I held the earbud to my ear before pressing the transmit button. I spoke in a low whisper. “Two Bits, this is Whisper. Serenity has changelings in the vents, looking for a place to make an entrance.”

“Copy that, Whisper. We’ll keep them all under surveillance.”

I waited until I was sure he wasn’t going to say more before stowing the earbud again, and another twenty seconds before I dared move. Taking up the strap of my bag again, I crept up to the intersection.

There was only the sound of air slowly blowing through the duct.

I rounded the corner and moved on, ears perked and alert for further hostile changelings, but none presented themselves. Soon I had reached the central utility shaft, where the ducts, pipes, and conduits that served the Stable traveled between levels. It was my key to the rest of Serenity. The soft thrum of far-away fans flowed through the ducts.

I carefully moved forward, worried that I would run into another changeling, but none presented themselves. For the moment, I was alone.

Time to get started.

Step one was establishing a “safehouse” of sorts. A place where I could hide if necessary, where I wouldn’t be found. I already knew where to go.

The bag hung from the strap in my mouth as I slid my way down to a duct two levels below, then started making my way out. About half an hour after I entered the vents, I finally reached my temporary safe-haven: the end of one of the ducts over Serenity’s zoology department. I remembered my first visit to Serenity, and the cluster of hostile contacts the wildlife there had shown. I was still within E.F.S. range of the scattered ponies on the surface, but I might as well gather every advantage I could.

So I hid myself in the cluster of hostile contacts and stashed my bag. The only thing I took with me was my pistol, with the holster strapped securely around my chest.

With my safehouse established, I moved on to step two: planning for extraction. As important as my mission was, I wasn’t ready to declare it “assets expendable” at the moment, so that meant planning on how to get me out of here.

Fortunately, that ended up being easier than I had dared hope for. On the opposite side of the zoology department was an equipment storage room. It was a large room with a single entrance, and plenty of shelves to hide behind. I retrieved my PipBuck before prying open the vent and dropping in.

I removed my holster and resumed my natural form, armor and all, and started radioing directions to Echo. Not long after, there was a purple flash. I blinked away the spots in my eyes, blinded until Echo’s horn lit up again, casting the room in a soft purple glow.

She looked around and nodded. “Yes, this should—”

“Shh!” I hissed, scooting in close to whisper. “Quiet. We can’t let them know we were here!”

She frowned, then nodded.

I led her to the back of the room before whispering again. “When I call for extraction, I’ll be hiding here, if possible.”

She nodded again.

“Okay, good. That’s it. Just make sure someone is always awake and monitoring our channel.”

She nodded once more.

“That’s it, then. Head on back. And… thank you.”

She smiled. Then her horn flashed again, leaving me alone in the dark.

I returned to my raccoon disguise and slipped into the duct once more. I let the vent swing down again, resting on its frame but not quite shut. Next, I returned to my safe-point, stashing the PipBuck before heading out again.

Step three was the most involved yet, as it involved the thorough reconnaissance of multiple levels of the Stable. It was a solid three hours of scurrying through air ducts and peering through vents, but it proved valuable. My understanding of the space rapidly improved, and I got a better impression of the disposition of Serenity’s defenses. Regular guard posts had been established near major rooms and intersections, with small clusters of soldiers ready to respond to any threat that might materialize out of thin air. A good number of the other changelings going about their business were armed, though I have no idea if those arms were distributed before or after our attack.

I ran into the first stumbling block when I made my way down to the utility levels. I was making my way down a duct in the central shaft when I heard a clatter and burst of conversation below. With adrenaline burning in my veins, I dove into an offshoot and froze, ears perked. There were two voices, and both were slow and awkward. I was familiar with that sound; these were changelings who had taken on a different form, but either not skilled enough or simply not wasting the effort required to make their voices sound normal.

Between the distance, the soft thrum of machinery, and the echoing of the ducts, I could only barely make out the louder voice. They were complaining.

“...doing maintenance while ponies are running around in our hive! I swear, Shale has the most idiotic priorities. The whole hive could be on fire and she’d still have us checking the water recyclers for contaminants and—”

A soft, metallic clank cut off her words.

I waited in silence for almost a minute before I heard a distant thump and metallic whine. Lying still as I was, I could feel the subtle change in airflow through my fur, and hear the distant sound of machinery. A couple seconds later, there was another metallic clank, and everything returned to how it was before, save for the quiet sound of someone moving through the duct. I waited, listening. About ten seconds later the same series of events repeated, and afterwards, the sound of movement was gone once more.

I waited another minute, and this time, there was no disturbance. I cautiously resumed my journey, keeping hiding spots in mind.

I had a good idea of what I was going to find. Sure enough, there was a place where the duct had been cut open, a latching door had been welded into it, and a series of bars had been welded along one side of the duct like a ladder.

That complicated matters, but maybe it could help me. They were using at least part of the duct system for travel between levels. The chance of a random changeling coming across me went up. Heck, they could open the door as I was traveling past it.

On the other hoof, it meant that seeing someone in the ducts wasn’t necessarily an unusual event. I wouldn’t be able to adequately explain my presence or stand up to scrutiny, but I might escape peripheral detection.

Still, I made every effort to move past the traveled area as quickly as possible, keeping hiding spots at the front of my mind. Fortunately, traffic was low. Perhaps they were more focused on the intrusion several levels up. Either way, I didn’t see anyone, and had soon mapped out a route that avoided those entrances.

It was spaces like this that made the Stable a self-enclosed ecosystem, and not just a bunch of quarters with some public spaces. It was a proper hive, much like home, but packed even more tightly. The utility levels, with their spark generators, air and water filtration, and other systems necessary for life, were only part of it. One level held massive artificial farms, with orchards and rows of crops. Another level was dedicated to industry, a whole factory full of priceless industrial machines. One vent looked in on a small room full of bins, holding hundreds of pounds of bottle caps, all freshly stamped and painted.

As I explored further, one of the key details I sought out was the various storage rooms. A Stable was intended to last for decades without resupply, and that meant plenty of room to store everything that could be needed. That included multiple armories, though peering through the vents showed that they were mostly empty. Presumably, most of their weapons had already been distributed. One was particularly well-guarded, with at least a dozen guards around and inside it. My heart-rate leaped as I peered through grates of the vent at the swirling, sickly-green color of the balefire bomb within. I had never wanted to be close to such a terrifyingly destructive device, and I was acutely aware that I was currently stuck in here with it, with my closest exit several minutes away.

My final stop was the one place that might be even more uncomfortable, but was just as vital: the Overmare’s office and quarters, where Queen Chrysalis the Sixth ruled her hive. According to the map, that’s where I had met her. No surprise that she’d claim that space as her own.

Of course, it wasn’t quite so simple to get there. At some point, someling had decided that measures should be taken to preserve the queen’s privacy. To do so, they had welded a couple of plates into the vent and bolted a grate with heavy, thick bars in place, blocking off the vent.

This was a complication, obviously. A quick test with my magic proved that the bolts were far too secure for me to remove by magic alone. I eventually had to backtrack to my extract point and coordinate an equipment drop from Echo.

When I returned, it was with a small set of wrenches. They gave me the leverage I needed, though it was still awkward. I had to slip them through the bars and work half-blind, and even then I had to go slowly to keep them from squeaking, a sound that was disturbingly loud in those bare ducts.

I had to be quiet. I could hear voices echoing faintly down the duct.

After several minutes of very careful work, I slid the grate out of place, laid it flat, and slipped past.

The Overmare’s office had been converted to something of a throne room. It was where I had first seen Queen Chrysalis the Sixth, when she had been talking about ending the reign of ponies. Now she sat there fuming, eyes narrowed, as she listened to a trio of soldiers discussing how to deal with the rapidly devolving situation. They were avoiding her gaze as they talked among themselves.

“...could be an opportunity, if we can take it,” one was saying. “We have them contained, now. Their teleportation is reliant on a single individual. That means low throughput, and a single point of failure. If we can take out that alicorn, then we have them trapped. If we can’t, they’re still limited in how quickly they can get out. A swift strike might be able to overwhelm their defenses and kill a significant number of them.”

“They’re too heavily dug in,” another said. “The only way to dislodge them is to either use a great amount of explosives to break their defenses, or force a massive assault to overwhelm them. Either would constitute a significant loss of assets. We risk destroying an entire simulation chamber, and we’ll certainly lose an unacceptable number of our soldiers.”

Chrysalis spoke, her voice icy. “How many?”

The second soldier hesitated, her unease apparent. “In an assault of that scale, down long halls with no cover? I think we’d be lucky to suffer only a hundred casualties. It’d probably be closer to two, and even if we wiped out the entire raiding force in the process, it’d hurt us more than it hurt them.”

“We need to find a way around them,” the third soldier said. “We might not have found a good place to stage an attack through the ventilation system, but there are other ways of bypassing their defenses. Our engineers have already identified a few places where we can breach walls and floors to gain entry. With enough breaches, we could overwhelm them in short order.”

“And wreck half the level in the process,” the second soldier said, shaking her head. “At the very least, we’d be writing off Simulation Chamber One, and given how thorough their internal security is, we’d probably face stiff resistance. They seem to be expecting some sort of trick.”

“And their forces are all masked up,” the first one said, “so we can’t gas them out.”

“Enough,” Chrysalis said, waving her hoof dismissively. “I’m tired of this. You are the military experts, you’re supposed to handle this. Just tell me, is there any chance they will be able to break out and threaten the rest of the hive?”

They were all silent for several long seconds before the second soldier eventually replied. “With their current forces, I would say very likely not, unless they’re able to pull something unexpected. The problem is, they can presumably keep teleporting soldiers in and become an even greater threat.”

Chrysalis paused, a smile slowly spreading as she tapped a hoof against her chin. “Hmm…” After a few moments, she set her hoof down, fixing the second soldier with a firm stare. “Good. Now stop bothering me with this and resolve the situation. If you can not do so by noon tomorrow, then you will keep the pressure on, encourage them to bring in reinforcements, and then we will take more drastic measures.”

“Drastic measures?” the soldier said, ears flattening. “Like what?”

“Like giving the last balefire egg to one of our soldiers, and using it to kill that pesky alicorn. Then, when they’re trapped, we can kill them at our leisure.”

“What? But that would destroy most of the chamber!”

“And that’s why I’m giving you until noon to find a better solution. If you can’t, then I will gladly sacrifice that small part of our hive for victory. It doesn’t matter how much damage this hive takes if we can break their army. They are the ponies’ last, dying gasp, and the only thing standing between me and victory. It doesn’t matter if this Stable ends up as a radioactive crater; so long as I survive and they do not, our hive will end up ruling this land.”

She stood up, tall and lean. I was struck again by just how young she looked. Her youth clashed with my own concept of an older, more experienced queen. She must have been several years younger than me. “I don’t want to hear any more about this, unless something significant happens. I expect you to do whatever it takes to secure our victory. Now go, and tell Ocelli to enter on your way out.”

They bowed and hurried out, while Chrysalis returned to her cushions. Soon, another changeling I recognized entered the room: Ocelli.

She bowed deep and respectfully. “My queen?”

Chrysalis fixed her with a cold glare. “Have you reestablished contact with any of our Infiltrators topside?”

“Only briefly,” Ocelli said, rising to stand once more, though she kept her head low. “We’ve had no word from our asset within the enemy army, but we’ve been getting regular updates from another asset currently on external observation of the target. She’s been trying to infiltrate the pony army, but it’s been much too densely packed to do so without being detected, even during the storm. It’s possible our asset within their army hasn’t been able to get the privacy necessary to contact us, and now that the ponies have activated their radio jammer, communications will be iffy.

“Our external asset’s last report was… concerning. She noted the army spreading out, and that an infiltrated agent should have been able to find a moment to send an asset-intact report, especially after missing so many reporting windows. She’s concerned that the asset may be lost.”

Chrysalis wore a deep frown. “Or they’ve joined the other traitors.”

“That seems unlikely, but... possible. Even if they did betray us, we’ve exercised strict information compartmentalization, and any sensitive information they might have somehow acquired would be at least a week out-of-date. I don’t think they’ve turned, but if they have, they won’t be able to cause any damage with their information.”

“I don’t care about information,” Chrysalis said, scowling. “I care about losing another Infiltrator, right when we need them the most! That vile little queen is sitting up there, laughing at us while the ponies she’s manipulating are rampaging through our hive! I want her dead.”

“We’ll certainly try,” Ocelli said, still looking at the floor. “There’s standing orders to eliminate Queen Whisper if at all possible, but—”

“I’m not talking about ‘if it’s convenient’,” Chrysalis snapped back. “I want our Infiltrators focusing on killing her at all costs. She’s the one behind all of this.”

“She is,” Ocelli said, with a cautious tone to her voice. Her gaze finally lifted, looking to Chrysalis with concern. “But at this point, I don’t think her death would meaningfully affect the army.”

Chrysalis’s eyes narrowed. “I disagree. You have your orders.”

Ocelli ducked her head again. “Yes, my queen. But… even if we were able to get a message out past the ponies’ interference, I’m not sure if we have enough assets in place to effect an assassination. She is very well-protected. The alicorn has powerful shields and seemingly refuses to leave her side.”

“The alicorn is preoccupied with teleporting ponies into my hive,” Chrysalis said, nearly spitting out the words in distaste. “Their queen is vulnerable.”

She stood, advancing until she stood right before Ocelli, who kept her head respectfully bowed. Chrysalis didn’t allow this. Instead, she reached down, hooking a hoof under the smaller changeling’s chin and lifting, forcing her to look up. When she spoke, her voice was surprisingly gentle. “She has slipped through your hooves once before. I am tasking you with this because you are more motivated than anyone else in the hive to see her end. Do not let her slip away again.”

Ocelli swallowed, squaring her shoulders. “Yes, my queen.”

Chrysalis nodded. “Go.”

Ocelli bowed deep, then turned and left.

I lingered a while longer, but there was nothing more of interest. Queen Chrysalis the Sixth was apparently done with business, and I didn’t feel the need to watch her eat. I waited a few more minutes to see if anything interesting turned up, but it seemed she was done with meetings.

I slipped away, scouting out the rest of the area, including what I could see of her quarters, but there was little of interest.

Having completed my reconnaissance, I returned to my hiding place to wait.

☢

And that’s where we’re at right now. I’ve been hiding here for the past few hours. I had a brief exchange with Two Bits. I passed on word to not bring in too many reinforcements, no matter the situation. Better to retreat and vacate the hive than bring in too many to evacuate. He passed on that not a single changeling had surrendered. The conversation took only a few minutes, and then I was back to waiting. I had some time to kill, and once I had gotten past some preliminary planning, I had nothing to occupy my mind.

Fortunately, my hiding spot is far enough from any vents that I can speak quietly without any risk of being overheard, so I’ve been passing the time with my recording. It’s a good way to keep myself occupied on something other than worrying. After all, I’m in about the most hostile place I could possibly be, surrounded by hundreds of changelings that would happily kill me, and my only way out relies entirely on the actions of someone else. De-stressing is good.

If I’m being entirely honest, it’s not the only reason I’m doing this. I may have started these recordings of my experiences as a way of managing stress and sorting out my own thoughts, but it soon became more than that. It became a way of preserving those experiences in a way others could understand, even if I wasn’t there to present it to them. It could be a way of showing ponies what changelings, or at least my hive, are really like.

But more than that, it could tell that tale to those of my hive.

My journey has been rife with danger. My profession is a constant series of hazards. There have been many times where I could have died, and all those experiences would have been lost. I’ve now insured the continuation of my hive, at least in body. I’m sure that, if the worst were to happen to me, my friends would do their best to raise my hive’s children to be good people, but it would still be incomplete. My hive is more than just a lineage. It’s a vast collection of knowledge, and above all of that, tying it all together, an ideal.

So I’ve made these recordings, weaving in the knowledge and ideals of our hive, and illustrating how they have guided my actions. It’s my hope that, if worst comes to worst, I will at least have this one gift to guide those who come after me.

Once I’m done recording this, I’ll be encrypting the audio files and sending a copy to Starlight’s PipBuck. She already knows the password to decrypt them. I do hope she won’t listen to it before we’re done here, though. I don’t want to worry her with this sort of talk.

If you are listening to this before I get back, don’t mistake this for me being fatalistic. I’m just being “depressingly practical” again. You know how I am. And to be perfectly honest, I really doubt anything bad will happen to me. I’m in a good position, with a clear way forward, and fairly easily managed risks. This is just a reasonable precaution before a major, potentially game-changing event.

After all, at this moment, there are two changeling queens in this hive. By noon tomorrow, at least one of us will be dead.

Chapter 49: Endgame

“Queen Chrysalis, this is Queen Whisper. Please respond.”

I released the button once more, starting another thirty second count. I’d been broadcasting unencrypted for a couple of minutes, now, with the jammer temporarily switched off. Serenity surely had someling handling sigint work, but it might take time for them to come across my broadcast, and even more to get word to their queen. I mentally reviewed the path through the ducts that would lead me back to my exit-point. Then I pressed the button again.

“Queen Chrysalis, this is Queen Whisper. Please respond.”

I had counted to twenty when the radio crackled and came to life in my ear, filled with an icy, contempt-laced voice. “This is Queen Chrysalis. What do you want?”

My heart pounded at hearing such contempt from a changeling queen. I had to remind myself that I was a queen as well, or at least playing at being one.

I took a quick, calming breath before depressing the button and speaking. “I am still hoping to negotiate an end to the bloodshed. Your hive can not win this fight, but it doesn’t have to be wiped out for a hopeless cause. Please—”

“Oh, shut up,” she snapped into the radio. “You will never defeat us, and I am not interested in making deals with a backstabbing traitor like you. I would rather die free than cower at your hooves. There will be no negotiations.”

“Please,” I said again, pouring every ounce of sincerity into my voice. “You have no source of love. Your—”

“And we have you and your scheming to thank for that! You wipe out our love supply, then try to act like you’re here to help. Well I see through you. Do you really want to end this? Then you come and meet me, face to face, and we can end this like true queens!”

I wasn’t exactly sure how to reply to that. Obviously, I wasn’t going to openly face her. I had no idea how dangerous she might be, but with the outcome of this war inevitable, it was a risk I didn’t have to take.

She correctly interpreted my silence as a refusal. “I thought not. You’re not a queen. You’re just a cowardly pretender, skulking in the shadows and sending pawns against us. If you find some courage in that treacherous heart of yours, then come and face me. Until then, I don’t want to hear another poisonous word from you.”

I sighed, but didn’t reply. The truth is, I hadn’t expected it to work. Despite that expectation, I still had to make an attempt, even if all it got me was the ability to honestly say that I tried.

☢

Step four of my infiltration involved establishing a safeguard. This, in turn, took me to the depths of the hive, where the most secure armory was located.

Six soldiers were stationed outside, weapons ready. Moving through the ducts to the armory itself, I could see four more stationed within, with two wearing pegasus power armors. All were sitting by a table, chatting just ten feet from the balefire bomb.

I slowly made my way through the ducts, taking my time. I couldn’t risk making a single sound. I’d left almost all my equipment behind. All I carried was a single small bundle wrapped in scrap cloth, weighing barely over a pound.

At each grate, I stopped and observed, looking over the shelves and crates filling the room. While most of the weapons had been distributed, the storage equipment gave ample cover.

Eventually I found a vent I liked. It was on the far side of the room, and was hidden from the guards by a cluster of boxes on the top of a shelf.

Being an armory, the vents were more secure, held in place with heavy screws. Having already scouted out the location, I was prepared. I slipped out the head of a screwdriver from my bundle, grasping it in my magic, and slid it through the grate.

Working blind, without the physical feedback of touch, is surprisingly difficult, but I was patient. I had time. It took almost a minute, but I finally got the screwdriver head into the slot of the screw, and started turning. Even this took time, as I had to rotate the screw slowly to quiet the squeaking. Finally, it came free, and I started on the next.

It took a good fifteen minutes to get that vent open. A tiny voice in the back of my head screamed to get on with it, but I knew better than to listen to it. Patience was key. Better to take my time than risk discovery.

With the last screw removed, I slid the grate away, setting it gently atop the shelf. Next I scooted back several feet; I wanted to transform without those guards seeing the flash. Even my hybrid-racoon form felt too obtrusive for this. Instead, I took on the form of a large rat. Small, sneaky, and easily overlooked. It was also about the most difficult and draining form I had ever taken. Significant changes in mass are like that.

I made my way out the vent and onto the top shelf, dragging my bundle with me. The loose cloth gave me an easy grip with my teeth, and though the bundle was still fairly heavy to me, it let me haul it along without too much difficulty.

Slowly, I picked my way down the shelf, until I was forced to hop down the last couple of feet. I landed hard, but given my size, that didn’t mean much. If any of the guards heard me, I didn’t notice a reaction.

The shelves hid my movement as I made my way around the armory, until the balefire bomb was directly between me and the guards.

The bomb was set on a heavy flatbed cart, secured with thick straps. It was the closest I had gotten yet to the bomb, and I could see far more details. The center of it glowed with a pulsing, sickly green, and this close, I could see it was covered in intricate shapes. I started tracing the edges…

I had to physically pull my gaze away, nearly falling off my paws. There was something deeply unsettling about the magic surrounding it, as if it was trying to draw me in. I glanced at it, and could practically feel my awareness seeping away. From that point on, I made sure to not look directly at it.

Around the core was a protective metal shroud. There had been letters stenciled on it, but centuries in the desert had left most of them faded and chipped away. I couldn’t tell what was originally written on them, but it appeared to be in the Equestrian language. Perhaps the shroud was part of the Equestrian Army’s experiments, or maybe just some extra precaution to prevent accidentally detonating it with a careless jostle.

I slowly crept up to the cart, dragging my little bundle with me. Climbing up onto the bed of the cart was easy enough, though hauling my bundle up was a little awkward and took a few tries. I tried to be silent. Every little slide of my paws on the cart, or faint tap of my bundle bumping against it, made my fur stand on edge.

The guards just kept talking, oblivious to me.

“I just think we should shove this creepy thing out the front, shut the door, and blow it up. Stables are built to take shit like that!”

“Yeah, except those ponies will shoot anything that comes out. Some dumb pony would blow us all up.”

“Besides, even if they didn’t, I wouldn’t count on the Stable door stopping it. Look at everything else those Stable-Tec ponies got wrong!”

I only halfway listened to them, mostly for any sign of noticing my presence. I focused instead on my bundle, heaving it up along the side of the cart as quietly as I could. As soon as I got it up, I slowly slid up to the shroud, and untied the cloth.

Inside was a single explosive charge. I gave it one final check. There were five remote initiators. Four were on the same channel, set to the maximum delay of ten seconds. I wanted full redundancy. No failures could be permitted. The last initiator was set to a separate channel, with no delay. It was an additional backup, in case some unforeseen circumstance came up where ten seconds was too long.

Everything was correct, just like the two times I had checked before setting out. I made my way to the edge of the shroud, peering over the lip to the inside. The bolts and seams inside gave a perfect place to pack the explosives. I hefted the charge up and gingerly slid it into place, then started working at it, trying to pack it into the crevice as securely as possible with my tiny paws.

Having the core of the balefire megaspell right behind my head was one of the most unnerving things I’d experienced. The glow steadily warped and shifted, reflected in the dull metal of the shroud. Even without looking at it, I could feel the world trying to pull away. The rest of the room seemed to recede into darkness, and I put all my effort into focusing on what I was doing. Even the conversation of the guards grew distant, as if heard through a long tunnel. The balefire swirled and twisted behind me, as if trying to suck me in.

I swear I heard whispers coming from the damn thing, just on the edge of my perception.

When I finally stepped away from the megaspell, satisfied that the explosives were properly secured, I found that I was shaking. The guards were still talking, as clear as ever. The walls still stood there, lit and unmoving.

I shuddered, taking a couple of calming breaths before slipping away, leaving that terrifying device behind me. I had much more to do.

☢

Step five finally kicked off at three in the morning, the culmination of more than four hours of investigating, observing, and waiting.

I’d taken my time. Every inch of the space had been carefully mapped out in my mind. Every step of my course was planned. Strategic vents had been loosened in preparation, so they required only the lightest of pressure to open. Every object in the area had been carefully investigated. I had gone over my equipment three times, carefully ensuring that it would all function correctly when I needed it.

I waited, peering out the thin grate of the vent, into the quarters of Queen Chrysalis the Sixth.

She was asleep. She had been asleep for well over an hour. Still I waited, observing.

She was just ten yards away, tucked into her huge plush bed and oblivious of the world around her, but still I waited. I had one shot at this, and no idea how capable she might be if awoken. I needed to get closer, so I waited.

Finally, I saw the faint movement of her eyelid as her eyes moved beneath them. It was what I was waiting for. I rose from my position, silently slinking down the duct.

All sleep is not equal, and when your job might involve sneaking away from or past individuals who are sleeping, those details become part of your training. REM sleep, signaled by its rapid eye movements, is the most easily identifiable and exploitable phase of sleep. Not only is it harder to wake from, it induces a form of paralysis to prevent an individual from acting out their dreams. That paralysis can potentially linger for several seconds after being woken, and being woken from REM sleep can leave a person disoriented for a few minutes.

As I said, I had one shot at this, so I was taking every advantage I could get. REM sleep lasts about ten minutes on average, and my plan should need no more than two.

I reached the bathroom vent, where I had stashed my bundle of equipment: my pistol, PipBuck, and remote detonator. A quick glance through the slats of the vent confirmed once more that the bathroom was empty, and I gripped the vent in my magic, gently pressing until it slid silently from the frame. I levitated a towel from the nearby rack and laid it on the counter, then carefully placed the vent atop it on the sink counter, soft and silent. Then I clutched my bundle of equipment and hopped down.

My magic wasn’t strong enough to levitate myself, but it slowed and guided my fall. I landed on the thick bath-mat, which I knew from earlier investigation had a rubber backing that prevented sliding. It was as perfectly silent as I could hope for.

I set the equipment down, and moved to the other end of the mat where I wouldn’t accidentally disturb it. With that, I called up my magic to transform. The form I took was mostly like my natural form, but with blunted fangs and soft cat-like paws instead of hooves. I also kept my armor hidden. As well-fitted as it was, it wasn’t perfectly silent, and I was taking no risks.

I buckled the PipBuck to my leg, letting the E.F.S. calibrate as I slipped the detonator’s lanyard around my neck. Finally, I took up my pistol in my teeth and stepped up to the door, my paws near silent even on the polished tile. I did a quick final check. The pistol was loaded, a round chambered, the safety off. S.A.T.S. was fully charged.

I pressed the button beside the door, and it opened as quietly as during my earlier tests. Quietly, however, is not the same as silently, so I wasted no time. The moment the door was open, I advanced in a smooth glide, much as I had seen Dusty move. I turned left, my pistol fixed on the form of the sleeping changeling queen as I moved up. I advanced until I was less than two yards away, my sights aligned over the back of her head.

Once again, I was struck by how young she looked. She was barely an adult, and lying there asleep, she seemed so peaceful. She had taken a genocidal course of action, and had spoken directly to me about her plans, yet it was difficult to connect that knowledge with the gentle-looking individual lying before me, asleep and helpless.

More than that, this was a queen. She wasn’t my queen, but I couldn’t help but feel a little of the significance of her title. It was a revered position. The highest place of honor among changelings. Even if we disagree with their actions, it was a position that commanded some respect. A changeling queen should be able to face her fate head-on. She deserved better than being slain in her sleep.

Three shell casings clattered on the hard tile floor. Queen Chrysalis the Sixth was dead.

I lowered the pistol as she gave a few twitches, the last firings of a dying nervous system. It was a victory for us, but I didn’t feel any elation. I just felt tired and hollow. Weeks of struggle, a full-blown war, the infiltration of a hostile hive, all ending with a whimper in a darkened bedroom. If I’d heard tales of such a thing during my training, the assassination of a changeling queen in the heart of her hive, I would have thought it the most amazing covert action in history. Living it, it felt anticlimactic and dirty. It had been the right call, but I couldn’t say I felt happy about it.

My eyes lingered on the ruined back of her head as the blood poured out, soaking into the plush bed. I shuddered, turning away.

It wasn’t the blood that made the sight so unsettling. I’d seen enough over the last few months to lose any squeamishness I might have had about the subject. No matter how gruesome a sight it might be, it would always be secondary to the mere fact that this was the corpse of a changeling queen. Despite what Queen Chrysalis had done, it was all too easy to picture Queen Ephema in her place. Worse yet, it was easy to imagine just how much impact her death would have on the changelings of her hive. I was about to devastate them.

But I’d already known that. In fact, I had planned on using that. I turned, sweeping up my spent casings before walking over to the intercom. A quick flip of a switch on the door panel locked it. It would only be a matter of minutes before they could open it, but that was more time than I needed. I just needed perhaps thirty seconds. That was enough time to broadcast a final goodbye from an exhausted and disillusioned Queen Chrysalis, summon up flames to consume the scene, and escape into the ventilation system once more. If anything could convince these changelings that the fight was lost, surely the suicide of their own queen would do so.

I called up my magic, focusing on my queenly disguise, with the minor alterations to mimic the voice of the young Queen Chrysalis. Then I drew in a deep breath, raised my hoof to the intercom… and after several seconds, rested it on the wall. I stared at the button, almost as if willing it to press on its own. I didn’t want to press it myself.

As an Infiltrator, you have to become comfortable with doing things you would rather not do, but this felt different. This didn’t feel like a matter of personal taste, some unpleasantness that I would rather avoid. Now that I was there, ready to follow through on the plan, with the queen’s corpse behind me, it simply felt wrong.

The plan made sense, of course. Remove the focal point for their fanatical drive against ponies, subtly encourage them to surrender, all while hiding my own involvement so as to avoid becoming a focus for their despair and outrage. It made logical sense, but I was no longer so certain it was the right thing to do.

I stood there, thinking on the subject, and put myself in their hooves. I thought of Queen Ephema’s death and my own reaction to it. I had found her dead, and I had set out into a balefire-scoured Wasteland, without regard for my safety and only the slimmest hope of success. If our hive were under siege, and she died, how would I react? Would I surrender to our enemy?

Not as long as there was any chance of forwarding my hive’s goals. No, I would probably fight to the death, so long as I could guarantee some part of my hive survived. Serenity still had changelings outside the hive that would survive whatever happened in here. I would want to resist the attackers with everything I had, and inflict as much damage as possible. How would I do it?

A great number of possibilities presented themselves, but none were terribly relevant. Only the end states really mattered, and given the impossibility of fighting off the attackers and the eventuality of a horrible death to love starvation, there was really only one endgame: open the Stable door, throw out the balefire megaspell, and detonate it. If our lives were to be lost anyway, we would spend them destroying the greatest obstacle to our sisters who were still out there.

I shook my head, as if clearing away the scenario, and considered a new one: instead of my queen mysteriously dying or committing suicide, what if she were killed by a foreign queen? I’d be outraged, and would want vengeance for my murdered queen. The final outcome was the same.

It was a wash.

But maybe the scenarios weren’t quite as simple as I first supposed. I wasn’t some murderous queen looking to destroy them, though it was quite possible that they might see me that way. I had made every attempt to seem sympathetic and compassionate. Even if they didn’t believe it, it was out there.

My queen’s suicide might convince me that our goals were lost, and that the offer of a seemingly sympathetic queen might be the best way to preserve something of our hive. That was the idea I had originally considered when forming my plan.

But if that seemingly sympathetic queen had instead infiltrated my hive and killed my own queen? There were a surprising amount of warring emotions there. Certainly there was anger and distrust. If she were really so sympathetic to our plight, why would she kill our queen? On the other hoof, there was abject horror. She had killed the most well-protected and important individual in our entire hive. There was absolutely nothing that could stop her from killing any one of us. Yet there was also a degree of uncertainty and confusion. If she could so easily kill any of us, why was she offering seemingly generous terms of surrender?

Certainly, I could be trying to trick them into surrendering just to make things easier on myself. At the same time, perhaps it suggested a degree of restraint and a desire to minimize violence. Which would win out?

Making all of it worse, even the most fanatical of changelings were not of a single, homogenous mind. They would not all react the same, and that was particularly dangerous when a hopeless and suicidal changeling could have access to a megaspell.

It still seemed to be a wash, but one troubling thought occurred to me. Regardless of the outcome here at the hive, this was a decision that could have consequences years down the road. It wasn’t just about getting them to surrender. The choice wasn’t really between them thinking I had killed their queen versus thinking their queen had killed herself. Truth has a way of coming to the surface. This was a choice between me telling them I had killed their queen, or them finding out some time later that I had killed their queen and lied to them.

I was trying to convince changelings, some of whom had already surrendered, to give ponies some degree of trust. Hinging all of that on a lie would threaten to tear all of that down.

That made a far more convincing argument, and to tell the truth, Honesty gave a sense of doing the right thing. I just hoped that me doing the right thing wasn’t about to get a lot of people killed.

My hoof slid away from the intercom. I’d still be sending a message, but I wanted to be well away from here when I did.

With a new plan in mind, I set about implementing it. First was returning to the bed. I looked over the form of Queen Chrysalis one last time before reaching out, unlatching and removing her PipBuck. With that secured, I focused my magic, calling up green fire to consume her remains. As the flames rapidly spread to the bedding, I returned to the bathroom and retook my hybrid-racoon form. Getting back in the vent took a bit more work than getting down, especially with the extra PipBuck, but I didn’t have to be quiet this time.

With the vent securely in place, I scurried down the duct, while awkwardly speaking into my broadcaster. “Two Bits? This is Whisper.”

His voice was thick with fatigue when he finally replied. “Two Bits here. What’s up?”

“I may be wasting my time in telling you this, but make sure your forces are on full alert. I may be about to kick over an ant hill.”

There was a long pause before he replied. “I don’t even know what to say about that phrase coming from you. And what do you mean? What did you do?”

I was passing the vent overlooking the bedroom again. The fire was rapidly spreading through the room, and smoke was starting to fill the duct. “Queen Chrysalis is dead.”

Dead air for a solid five seconds. “Holy shit.”

“Yeah. I can’t say exactly how they’re going to react. They might be willing to surrender, or they might go suicidal on you. I’d say get an initial feel for it, then decide if you’re staying or going. I’ve got my own way out.”

“Understood. We’ll hold tight for now.”

“Good to hear. While you’re at it, get ahold of Dusty or whoever’s awake topside. Tell them they should start stage one evacuations. He’ll know what I mean.”

“...I’ll do that. That sounds bad.”

“You’ll be well away from here before it matters. Also, get ahold of Echo, tell her I need her on alert and ready to start evacuation at a moment’s notice. I’ve got to go now.”

I’d left most of the smoke behind, but it was spreading quickly. Once I had gotten to the utility shaft, I couldn’t even smell it any more. On the other hoof, the Serenity changelings had to be noticing it by now, and would very quickly trace it to its source. I scurried down a level, then darted into the vacant hydroponics office I had noted earlier. I locked the door, then transformed into my regal form once more.

This time, there was no hesitation as I reached for the intercom, selecting the public address channel.

“Attention, changelings of Serenity.” My voice echoed strangely through the halls and rooms of the Stable, low and somber. “I’m sorry to inform you that… Queen Chrysalis the Sixth is dead. I regret that it has come to this, and while I’m sure my words carry little weight right now, I know how hard this must be for all of you. I wish there had been some other way.

“I want this bloodshed to be over. Despite everything that has happened, our offer of surrender is still open. Please, let this end. Put down your weapons and surrender, and we can all move on together. There’s been enough death already.”

I hesitated, feeling like I should add more, but no words came. I released the button, the speakers giving a final squeal before going silent. Maybe brevity would help.

With the message complete, I made my way back to where I had stashed the rest of my equipment, retrieving the respirator mask. Then I backtracked, making my way back to the Overmare’s office turned throne room.

The smoke filled the vents, even as the air system struggled to pump in clear air. I cinched the mask snugly over my head, though my form made it an imperfect fit. I had to hold it in place to keep from getting a lungful of smoke when I breathed, and visibility was down to only a couple of yards.

Despite that, I was able to make it back to the vent overlooking the office, now filled with changelings. They’d managed to open the door to Chrysalis’s quarters, and smoke was still wafting out of the open door, though it looked like they’d put out the fire.

The emotions I saw covered the whole spectrum. One of the heavily equipped guards, clad in black-painted Steel Ranger armor, was now just sitting beside the queen’s cushions, staring off into space. Another lay nearby, and from the slow shifting of her head and shoulders, looked to be on the verge of breaking down. A lightly armed soldier paced angrily. Two unarmored changelings were embracing, tears rolling down their cheeks.

Several more changelings emerged from the former queen’s room, looking dazed and exhausted. Others were entering the office from outside, including one I recognized: Ocelli.

She fell on the agitated side, and immediately took control of the scene. She demanded to know what had happened, how their queen could have been killed while locked in her own room. Noling had anything beyond speculation. The working theory was that Echo had teleported in an assassin.

In my earbud, Two Bits reported a hoofful of changelings had fearfully surrendered in one sector, while frantic attacks were launched in others. Every now and then, I could hear the distant thump of an explosion.

At least I had the satisfaction that I might have saved a few more lives, assuming I hadn’t just gotten a lot of ponies killed.

The discussion of how their queen could have been killed was interrupted minutes later when a messenger arrived, looking scared and confused. “Um, I… I’m not sure who to report to.”

There was a moment of confusion before Ocelli stepped forward. “Under the emergency protocols, I am assuming leadership of the hive until a proper chain of command can be established. Report.”

The messenger swallowed and nodded, then spoke. “Guard commanders are reporting a breakdown of order on the simulator level. Most forces are pressing the attack on pony positions, but taking heavy casualties. They’re not sure if they can sustain the pressure, but their soldiers are refusing to stand down. Additionally, one commander reported that a squad under her command has surrendered, and others are discussing whether they should follow suit.”

Ocelli’s eyes widened in rage. “What? Their queen was murdered, and they’re giving themselves over to the filth that did it? Those traitors!” She grabbed the messenger. “What was this commander’s name?”

“C-Coxa, ma’am.”

“Well you go back to Coxa, and tell her that any changelings promoting surrender will be considered to be giving support to our enemies in a time of crisis, and are to be shot as traitors!”

“Yes ma’am!”

As the messenger hurried off, Ocelli turned to another soldier. “You! Queen Chrysalis had a plan to take out their alicorn. Are you familiar with it?”

“Yes. She wanted to use a balefire egg to—”

“I know the plan,” Ocelli said. “I want you to find a volunteer to enact it. How soon can you have a volunteer armed and ready to go?”

“Um… ten, fifteen minutes?”

“Good. Make it happen. I want that alicorn dead!”

She quickly nodded and hurried off as well.

I quickly scurried back from the vent, until I was confident my whispering wouldn’t be overheard. I huddled around the PipBuck and hit the button to transmit. The respirator mask muffled my words. “Two Bits, this is Whisper.”

“Go.”

“I need you to evacuate immediately. They’re planning on bringing in heavy explosives through the vents, with the intent of killing Echo and trapping you. You’ve got ten, maybe fifteen minutes before they start enacting their plan.”

“Shit.” A moment of silence. “Understood. Echo is already here. It’ll be messy if they keep up the pressure like this, but we should be able to evacuate by then.”

I switched to my private channel. “Dusty, are you there?”

A few seconds later, I heard his voice. “Yeah, I’m here. What’s going on down there?”

“The situation is evolving,” I said, a neat non-answer. “Serenity’s new command structure is going to extreme measures more rapidly than I’d hoped. I just told Two Bits to make his exit. You’d better start stage two evacuations.”

“Already?”

“Yes, already.”

“And you’re sure about this?” he asked. “If we do that, there may be no coming back.”

“I understand, and yes, I’m sure.”

I heard him sigh across the radio. “Understood. Stage one and two should be complete in… about thirty minutes. Once Hail Burst is topside, I’ll put the Loyalists on door duty. That should make stage three take… maybe two minutes, tops.”

“Sounds good. Thank you.”

“Uh-huh. And Whisper? Be careful down there.”

I crawled back to the vent. The smoke was already thinning by the time I got there, while even more changelings had gathered in the room below.

Ocelli was discussing strategy with several of the soldiers, discussing plans to crush the remaining ponies once their teleporting alicorn was slain. I cast a glance in their direction. The E.F.S. was full of contact markers, but there was considerably less green there. In fact, there was less green all around. The amount of friendly ponies within range was rapidly dwindling. Before long, I would have little in the way of camouflage.

Several minutes later, the intercom speaker beside the vent came to life with a loud squawk. “All forces! All forces! Commander Coxa has gone rogue! Her unit has engaged friendly forces and is attempting to join the pony intruders!”

“What?!” Ocelli snapped, leaping to her hooves again. She rushed to the intercom, calling out across it, “Stop those traitors at all costs!”

“We’ll try,” came the reply. “Pony forces are falling back in all sectors. I think they’re teleporting out.”

“Well, stop them!” Ocelli shouted, then spun to face the soldier she had been talking with. “How long until the alicorn-killer is in place?”

“I don’t know,” the soldier replied, leaping to her hooves. “I’ll go find out.”

Minutes ticked by. The smoke thinned. Friendly contacts dwindled.

A powerful thump hammered at my ears, the air in the duct blasting one way, then the other. My ears were left ringing. Something massive had exploded.

I scurried back in the duct once more, returning to my broadcaster. “Echo!” I whispered urgently. “Are you there?”

The reply came thankfully swift. “I am. It seems they blew up part of the simulation chamber. I have gotten all of the raiding force out, though Two Bits and a few others were injured in the explosion.”

I gave a quick sigh of relief before a fresh concern mounted. “How bad are they hurt?”

“They will likely live, though Sickle will need several healing potions. Again.”

“...Okay. Get them taken care of and stand by. I’ll probably need extract in about thirty minutes.”

“I will be ready,” she said.

I returned to the vent. It was two minutes before a messenger arrived.

Ocelli was immediately on her hooves. “Well? Did they get that alicorn?”

The messenger hesitated, swallowed, and spoke. “I’m afraid not. They were in the main chamber, and engaged our agent when she emerged from the vent. It seems their gunfire detonated the egg prematurely, and the alicorn’s shield protected her.”

“Damn it,” Ocelli grumbled. “What about the rest of them? Did we get anyone?”

“I’m afraid all the ponies have escaped,” the messenger said, shifting her weight subtly from hoof to hoof. “Several ponies were wounded or killed while falling back, though they were able to extract their casualties. We did capture three of our rebelling soldiers, including Commander Coxa. The rest of her unit are either dead or escaped with the ponies.”

Ocelli muttered something far too quiet for me to hear before speaking to the messenger again. “Return to whoever is in charge down there. Inform them that the three prisoners are to be shot immediately. Go.”

The messenger gave a hasty salute and hurried off. He almost ran into the next messenger.

“Commander Ocelli! We just established communications with one of the army scouts, Ghost Two. She’s on one of the landlines. The pony army is pulling out. They’re using the motorwagons to ferry their ponies and about a hundred prisoners to a location roughly four miles away. She also reports that the only forces remaining on-site are about twenty Enclave ponies.”

I glanced around. Sure enough, there was only a single small cluster of green contact indicators.

Ocelli had gone very still, staring off in thought. The soldiers she had been talking with were just starting to speculate when she spun around to face one of them. “Move the megaspell, now. If one of those traitors told that alicorn where it’s being held, she could drop a bomb right on it.”

The soldier’s eyes widened. “Y-yes, right away! Where should we move it?”

“Anywhere else!” Ocelli said, then immediately corrected herself. “No, move it to the entry-level equipment storage. Go, now!”

As that soldier took wing and shot off, Ocelli trotted over to the intercom. “Attention! All active, reserve, and emergency forces are to equip and assemble immediately on the entry level. All unit commanders are to report to the throne room.”

One of the other soldiers followed her. “What’s the plan?”

“The plan is that we outnumber the ponies guarding the hive entrance tens of times over.” She turned to the pony who had brought in word of the scout, who was now at a terminal with a pair of headphones. “Have we re-established contact with the army?”

“Not by radio. Ghost Two can relay messages, but she says the army is less than fifty strong and completely combat ineffective.”

Ocelli muttered something.

I looked at my PipBuck. It had been about twenty minutes since Dusty had started the evacuation.

Soldiers started to arrive a couple of minutes later. The room steadily grew more crowded with changelings, all asking what was going on. Ocelli sat on the edge of the queen’s cushions, refusing to answer until the last commander had arrived.

Once they had, she stood. “Commanders. We have re-established communications with a topside scout. The pony army has withdrawn from the surface, and is regrouping a few miles away. They’ve left only twenty ponies guarding the entrance. They seem to think we are trapped. We are going to prove them wrong.

“I want you to prepare your units for a breakout. When that door opens, we will pour out and overwhelm the ponies guarding it. Once we have done so, we will establish a full presence on the surface. We can not be pushed back into the hive again, even if that means abandoning it. Understood?”

There were nods of assent, firm and confident. Faces still downturned and slack from the loss of their queen were looking up as a glimmer of hope returned.

“How soon can you be prepared to move out?”

“We should be fully prepared within an hour,” one of the commanders said, and several others nodded.

“Good, because once we have secured the entrance of our hive, we must deal with their army,” Ocelli paced before them. “We still have the megaspell. Many of our sisters gave their lives to deliver it to us. Now we must be ready to give our lives to use it. Commander, how many soldiers do each of your units have?”

She had stopped in front of one of the soldiers, who replied, “About forty, ma’am.”

“Good,” she said, nodding as she resumed her pacing. “Their army is gathering together just a few miles from our hive. I need four volunteers, whose units will ensure that the megaspell is delivered to that army, regardless of the cost.”

She stopped, staring at them with a fierce glare. “We have come so close to losing everything, but we have this one opportunity to reclaim our future. If we are able to destroy this army, then we will have won, and all the death we have suffered will have guaranteed a future where we are never put under the hooves of ponies, ever again. We can not fail our sisters. We can not fail our slain queen.” She raised her head, standing proud. “Who is willing to take up this duty?”

Sure, I saw signs of hesitation, and deep breaths to build up courage, but one by one, all ten stepped forward.

Ocelli smiled, small and proud. “We only need four,” she said, and proceeded to pick four herself. She stopped by the closest, reaching out to pat her on the shoulder. “Today, through your effort, we will reclaim our destiny. You will bear down on their army like the swarms of old, and deliver destruction to our enemies. The hive’s future rides on your shoulders.”

The commander before her held her head high, her eyes bright and eager. “We will not fail. For Queen Chrysalis and the hive!”

The others carried the cheer. And Ocelli stepped back, smiling. “I’m proud of all of you. Now go, prepare your soldiers, and let us repay these ponies for every wrong they have dealt us!”

The commanders cheered again, and turned to leave. Their heads were held high as they marched out, even those who had just been condemned to death. Ocelli remained in the office-turned-throne-room, watching with a proud smile, like a miniature queen.

The door shut. Ocelli’s smile slid away, replaced with a grim expression. She turned to the changelings gathered nearby. “We should discuss contingency plans. These ponies have proven far too tricky to count on this attack succeeding. Aphid, how quickly can we enact evacuation protocols?”

The changeling in question shifted awkwardly on her hooves. “With the emergency defense ‘lings called up, we’re short-staffed. In ideal situations, we would need only half an hour. With current numbers, I think we’d need at least an hour. Maybe two.”

Ocelli was silent for several long seconds. “Hypothetical. Assume only one hundred of our combat forces remain, from the emergency forces, along with all remaining non-combat population. Would that be sufficient to take Mareford?”

Another changeling checked her PipBuck. “Given the last reports after the army’s departure, they have only armed civilians for defense. I’d give a pessimistic estimate of twenty four hours to pacify the entire settlement, with minimal losses, assuming we want to take all ponies and structures intact.”

“We won’t be able to hold it,” another changeling noted. “Not if their army survives.”

“We don’t need to hold it,” Ocelli said. “We just need to take a few dozen ponies to feed on, and any supplies we might want. We can destroy the rest and move on. Let their army starve.”

There were nods of agreement all around. “Good,” Ocelli said. “Aphid, begin evacuation protocols. This pony-made shelter has served us for many generations, but its usefulness is at an end. We no longer need to hide.”

I had been so focused on her words that I didn’t hear the soft clattering until the large radroach rounded the corner of the duct, just five feet from me. It had come from the duct that served only the queen’s chambers, and was wearing a PipBuck.

I immediately had my gun out and firing before the radroach could fully recognize the situation she had stumbled into. Four rapid-fire rounds smashed into her, and with a flash of green flame, the radroach was replaced by the crumpled form of a changeling, jammed into a duct far too small for her.

“The hell?” someone blurted from below. “Were those gunshots?”

I grabbed my equipment, turned, and scurried away as fast as I could. I could already hear shouts, and seconds later, the duct lit up with vivid flashes of green and red as soldiers fired into the vent mere feet behind me.

I rounded a corner, now outside of the room, which put a solid wall between me and them. Still, I didn’t stop. There weren’t enough friendly contacts to hide me. Now that they knew I was there, they would have no trouble tracking the lone hostile contact.

The duct routed through more walls, then hit an intersection. As I continued on, I pulled off my respirator mask, pressing my broadcaster’s button with my magic. “Echo, are you there?”

“I am. Is it time to go?”

“Yes! Tell Dusty to start stage three evacuation right now!”

“I will.” There were several long seconds of silence as I hit the central utility shaft, sliding down the duct for several levels. “He says they will begin evacuating immediately. The Loyalists should be at a safe distance in two minutes.”

I heard the deep, earth-shaking rumble from above. Stage one had been the initial movement of half the army to establish a new camp a safe distance away, as well as all the heavy equipment. Stage two had been the removal of the rest of the army, leaving only a small force to keep the door shut. Now that stage three was enacted, those ponies were now speeding off, but not without leaving one last obstacle for Serenity. The rumble I heard was the sound of fifty pounds of strategically placed explosives collapsing the exit tunnel. The door to Serenity should now be buried behind a few hundred tons of concrete.

Serenity could dig their way out, of course. This move would only delay them, but it was more of a delay than I would need.

“Echo, I’m almost to the extraction point. I need you to disable the jammer and meet me there.”

“A building just fell on the jammer,” she said. “It is as disabled as it is going to get.”

“Good!”

I scrambled down another series of ducts. My trip down the utility shaft obscured what level I was on, but it bought me very little time. They would eventually find me, even if it required searching every level.

I heard sharp cracks from ahead, but I didn’t slow. When I finally got to the vent leading to the storage room I had chosen as my extract point, I burst out of the duct, only to be immediately caught in a field of magic. Echo stood there, grim-faced, with the smoldering corpses of two changelings beside her.

“Ready to go?”

“Wait!” I said, calling up my magic and transforming into my regal form. I dropped out of Echo’s magic, cushioning my fall with a quick flutter of my wings, and hastily latched my PipBuck onto my leg. I called up the time. I still needed another minute.

I floated up Queen Chrysalis’s stolen PipBuck. A quick check confirmed the radio settings, and I hit the button to transmit. “Ocelli, this is Queen Whisper. Please respond.”

My heart hammered. Several seconds later, the radio came to life. “I can’t wait for them to bring me your corpse.”

“This isn’t going to end the way you think it will,” I said. “My offer still stands, but we are out of time. This is your last opportunity. Please. For the good of your hive and the hundreds of changelings that will perish with you, surrender.”

“Save your empty threats,” Ocelli said, her voice practically a growl. “I will never fall for your treacherous words again.”

A bang drew my attention back to reality. Echo’s shield was up, having just taken a shot from a changeling at the door. She responded with a blast of electricity, and followed it up by hurtling a heavily laden shelf at the door, thoroughly blocking it.

I turned back to the broadcaster. “This isn’t a threat, Ocelli. This is an inevitability. I’ve tried everything I could to save lives, but you are forcing my hoof. If you do not surrender, every changeling within this hive will die.”

“You are a coward and a liar,” Ocelli said. “We will never surrender to you.”

The rapid discharge of multiple magical energy weapons filled the air, blowing away parts of the shelves blocking the door. The angle left us safe, but it wouldn’t hold long. Echo threw another shelf onto the heap. “We need to go!” she snarled.

I looked down at the clock. It was time.

I took a deep breath, and sighed it out. Then I pressed the broadcast key one last time. “I’m sorry.”

Then I lowered the stolen PipBuck, and took the detonator in my magic. A quick look confirmed it was on the correct channel.

A sharp bang filled the air, muffled by Echo’s shield. Some Serenity soldier had tried throwing a grenade in past the shelves, to no avail.

I moved the switch from “Safe” to “Arm”. The red light lit.

My heart hammered. Several magical bolts slammed into the toppled shelving as the Serenity soldiers continued to try and clear the door. Echo shoved another pair of metal chests into the pile.

I flipped the safety, unblocking the trigger.

“Echo.”

Her head snapped around, eyes narrowed in grim determination. I turned the detonator so she could see it clearly.

I hit the trigger.

“Now.”

With a flash of purple, we were gone.